[
  {
    "question": "Which of the following factors will lead to an increase of ground distance during a glide, while maintaining the appropriate minimum glide angle speed?",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following factors will lead to an increase of ground distance during a glide, while maintaining the appropriate minimum glide angle speed?",
    "feedback": "Tailwind."
  },
  {
    "question": "The take-off distance of an aircraft is 600m in standard atmosphere, no wind at 0 ft pressure-altitude. Using the following corrections: \"± 20 m / 1 000 ft field elevation\" \"- 5 m / kt headwind\" \"+ 10 m / kt tail wind\" \"± 15 m / % runway slope\" \"± 5 m / °C deviation from standard temperature\" The take-off distance from an airport at 1 000 ft elevation, temperature 17°C, QNH 1013,25 hPa, 1% up-slope, 10 kt tail wind is:",
    "feedback": "755 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the the Long Range Cruise Chart and find %N1 and KIAS for a weight of 250000 kg during a cruise flight in a pressure altitude of 28000 ft.",
    "feedback": "78.2%, 309 kts"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are taking off on a runway with a contaminated surface and you are VMCG limited, how can you improve performance?",
    "feedback": "Derated thrust to decrease VMCG"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the landing-climb performance of an airplane is correct?",
    "feedback": "The worst climb performance is obtained with a high outside air temperature and high pressure altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is the most limiting situation on landing?",
    "feedback": "downslope with tailwind"
  },
  {
    "question": "Concerning the landing gear, which of the following factors would limit the take-off mass?",
    "feedback": "Rate of rotation of the wheel at lift off and brake energy."
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual SEP1, Fig. 2.2)\nCalculate the gross take-off distance, given the following data:\nTake-Off Mass: 3300 lbAirfield PA: 3500 ftTemperature: 26°CHeadwind Component: 15 ktUpslope: 0.7%Surface: Dry grass",
    "feedback": "2360 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor in a turn in level flight with constant TAS depends on",
    "feedback": "the bank angle only."
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual MEP1, Fig. 3.1)\nGiven the following information, what is the Field Length Limited Take-Off Mass?\nTORA: 2250 ftRunway Surface: GrassRunway Condition: DryNo clearway and no stopway availableAirfield Pressure Altitude: 2000 ftAirfield Temperature: +11°CHeadwind Component: 5 kt",
    "feedback": "3550 lbs"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the flap setting is increased from 5° to 10°, the ground roll distance will ......",
    "feedback": "reduce due to the increase in lift, which reduces the stall speed and required take-off speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the outside air temperature and pressure altitude affect the climb performance of an aeroplane?",
    "feedback": "The worst performance will occur with a combination of high outside temperature and high pressure altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following conditions exist at an airport of intended landing:\nLanding rwy. 13, Wind  140° at 30 Kt.\n\nA pilot can determine that the crosswind component is approximately",
    "feedback": "5 Kt."
  },
  {
    "question": "For a turbojet aircraft, what is the difference between range and endurance speeds? Maximum range is flown at ......",
    "feedback": "1.32 VMD minimum drag speed and maximum endurance is flown at VMD"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the alternatives represents the correct relationship?",
    "feedback": "VMCG and V1 should not exceed VR"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the take-off mass of an aeroplane is tyre speed limited, downhill slope would",
    "feedback": "have no effect on the maximum mass for take-off."
  },
  {
    "question": "The lowest take-off safety speed (V2 min) is:",
    "feedback": "1.13 VSR for two- and three-engine turbo-propeller and turbojet aeroplanes"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual MRJT1, Fig. 4.22)\nDetermine the gross level off altitude and optimum driftdown speed:\nGiven:\nMass: 44000 kgOAT: ISA +7°C",
    "feedback": "28300 ft, speed 196 kts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Reduced take-off thrust",
    "feedback": "has the benefit of improving engine life."
  },
  {
    "question": "What should be considered when calculating take-off performance for a ferry flight of an MRJT at very cold temperatures?",
    "feedback": "VMCG can limit V1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the graphs illustrate the effect on total drag when total mass is increased?",
    "feedback": "Figure 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "To maximise the specific range of an aeroplane:",
    "feedback": "True airspeed must be high, and the fuel flow must be low"
  },
  {
    "question": "A change of runway in use from a runway slope of 1 % downhill to a runway slope of 1 % uphill will:",
    "feedback": "increase take-off run, increase take-off distance"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a given configuration the endurance of a piston engined aeroplane only depends on:",
    "feedback": "altitude, speed, mass and fuel on board."
  },
  {
    "question": "At a given altitude, when a turbojet aeroplane mass is increased by 5% - assuming the engines specific consumption remains unchanged -, its hourly consumption is approximately increased by:",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a given altitude, when a turbojet aeroplane mass is increased by 5% - assuming the engines specific consumption remains unchanged -, its hourly consumption is approximately increased by:",
    "feedback": "5%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ignoring the effect of compressibility, the effect a change of altitude has on the value of the coefficient of lift is that it:",
    "feedback": "is independent of altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Field length is balanced when",
    "feedback": "take-off distance equals accelerate-stop distance."
  },
  {
    "question": "The departure airport reports an air temperature of -5°C. Using the data below, which statement is correct? (SEL OAT is equivalent to the assumed temperatur of FLEX).\nV1: 132 ktFlaps: 5°VR: 132 ktSEL OAT: +59°CV2: 139 kt",
    "feedback": "SEL OAT will force the engine control computer to think the air temperature is +59°C and therefore that the air density is low and the engine requires less fuel to maintain the correct fuel/air ratio. This leads to less thrust being produced"
  },
  {
    "question": "The second segment begins",
    "feedback": "when landing gear is fully retracted."
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle of climb with flaps extended, compared to that with flaps retracted, will normally be:",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle of climb with flaps extended, compared to that with flaps retracted, will normally be:",
    "feedback": "Smaller."
  },
  {
    "question": "With a positive rate of climb, the difference between the climb angle and the climb gradient is that the gradient ....",
    "feedback": "value is always higher than the angle value"
  },
  {
    "question": "The requirements of the take-off flight path for a Class A aeroplane assume:",
    "feedback": "the failure of the critical engine on a multi-engined aeroplane at VEF"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement related to a take-off from a wet runway is correct?",
    "feedback": "A reduction of screen height is allowed in order to reduce weight penalties"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stalling speed in landing configuration is defined as the stalling speed",
    "feedback": "with flaps in landing configuration and gear down."
  },
  {
    "question": "The MSTOM of a multi-engine piston aeroplane is 12500 lbs. Referring to the given table, find the maximum regulated take-off mass with 0° flaps under the following conditions (dry, level runway, zero wind):\nASDA: 5980 ftTORA: 4730 ftTODA: 5320 ftPA: 3000 ftOAT: -20°C",
    "feedback": "11000 lbs"
  },
  {
    "question": "The requirement with regards to obstacles in is that the net take-off flight path should clear all obstacles by",
    "feedback": "minimum 35 feet vertically"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can the length of a stopway be added to the runway length to determine the take-off distance available ?",
    "feedback": "No."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements defines the power required?",
    "feedback": "The power that is needed to maintain unaccelerated level flight for a set of conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "During certification flight testing on a four engine turbojet aeroplane the actual take-off distances measured are:\n- 3050 m with failure of the critical engine recognised at V1\n- 2555 m with all engines operating and all other things being equal\n\nThe take-off distance adopted for the certification file is:",
    "feedback": "3050 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under which condition should you fly considerably lower (4 000 ft or more) than the optimum altitude ?",
    "feedback": "If at the lower altitude either considerably less headwind or considerably more tailwind can be expected."
  },
  {
    "question": "How is obstacle clearance assured in a pull-up?",
    "feedback": "By minima calculations"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the certification flight testing of a twin engine turbojet aeroplane, the real take-off distances are equal to:\n- 1547 m with all engines running\n- 1720 m with failure of critical engine at V1, with all other things remaining unchanged.\nThe take-off distance adopted for the certification file is:",
    "feedback": "1779 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "For this question use CAP 698, Figure 4.29\nGiven the following information, what is the Climb-Limited Landing Mass?\nOAT + 10°CPressure Altitude 2000 ftFlap Position 30°A/C Packs AUTOEngine & Wing Anti-ice ON",
    "feedback": "59050 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "What margin above the stall speed is provided for a Class A aeroplane by the landing reference speed VREF?",
    "feedback": "1.23 VSO"
  },
  {
    "question": "What issue you may experience with the take-off, if you were to pick up a new aircraft from a factory in Europe on a cold day?",
    "feedback": "A high VMCG which may lead to controllability issues in the event of an aborted take-off"
  },
  {
    "question": "(For this Question use Performance Manual MEP1, figure 3.2)\nWith regard to the graph for the light twin aeroplane, will the accelerate stop distance be achieved in a take-off where the brakes are released before take-off power is set?",
    "feedback": "No, the performance will be worse than in the chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering a jet transport aeroplane, Specific Fuel Consumption SFC ......",
    "feedback": "is the fuel flow per unit of thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "A headwind component increasing with altitude, as compared to zero wind condition, (assuming IAS is constant)",
    "feedback": "has no effect on rate of climb."
  },
  {
    "question": "Uphill slope",
    "feedback": "increases the take-off distance more than the accelerate stop distance."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the minimum width of a clearway?",
    "feedback": "500 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying a glideslope on a ILS with a headwind with same descent speed (CAS)",
    "feedback": "the rate of descent is lower and more power is needed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Two identical turbojet aeroplanes (whose specific fuel consumption is assumed to be constant) are in a holding pattern at the same altitude. The mass of the first one is 95 000 kg and its hourly fuel consumption is equal to 3100 kg/h. Since the mass of the second one is 105 000 kg, its hourly fuel consumption is:",
    "feedback": "3426 kg/h"
  },
  {
    "question": "V1 for a balanced field is calculated when:",
    "feedback": "the acceleration/stop distance available is equal to the take-off distance available"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the value of the declared distance that must be used in order to calculate the Landing Distance Required (LDR) on Runway 23 at Glasgow airport EGPF?",
    "feedback": "2356 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum rate of climb that can be maintained at the absolute ceiling is:",
    "feedback": "0 ft/min"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual MRJT1, Fig. 4.1)\nGiven the following information, what is the maximum acceptable wind speed for take off?\nMax. Tailwind: 10 ktsWind Direction;:180°(M)Take-off Runway Direction: 060°(M)",
    "feedback": "20 kts"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual SEP1, Figure 2.3)\nDetermine the rate of climb by using the following information:\nPower setting: Full throttle (2700 RPM)Mass: 3500 lbPressure Altitude: 8000 ft (ISA conditions)",
    "feedback": "800 ft/min"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the following list of conditions those that must prevail in the second segment of the take-off net flight path for a Class A aeroplane:\n1) Undercarriage retracted\n2) Undercarriage extended\n3) Flaps up\n4) Flaps in take-off position\n5) All engines at take-off thrust\n6) Operative engine(s) at take-off thrust\n7) Climbing speed of V2 + 10 kt\n8) Climbing speed of 1.3 VS\n9) Climbing speed of V2\n10) Commencing height 35 ft",
    "feedback": "1, 4, 6, 9"
  },
  {
    "question": "The approach climb requirement is established to safeguard:",
    "feedback": "Obstacle clearance in case of an overshoot with one engine inoperative."
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual MRJT1, Fig. 4.24)\nGiven the following information and assuming a drift down after engine failure, what is the time travelled, ground distance travelled, and fuel burned from the point of engine failure?\nDrift down from pressure altitude: 37000 ftDrift down to pressure altitude: 21000 ftGross Mass at engine failure: 50000 kgOAT: ISA +20°CHeadwind: 50 KTBleed configuration: Engine and wing anti ice offA/C: Auto (High)",
    "feedback": "27 minutes, 124 NM, 800 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "(For this question use Performance Manual MRJT 1 Figure 4.5)\nConsider the take-off performance for the twin jet aeroplane climb limit chart. Why has the wind been omitted from the chart?",
    "feedback": "The climb limit performances are taken relative to the air."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement regarding V1 is correct ?",
    "feedback": "VR may not be lower than V1"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual SEP1, Fig. 2.4)\nGiven:\nOAT: 18°CPressure Altitude: 3000 ft AMSLWind: 21010KTMass: 3120 lbRunway: Paved, wet\nUsing the graph, determine the ground roll distance of an aircraft, landing on runway 15:",
    "feedback": "1188 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, which one of the following statements concerning the landing distance for a turbojet aeroplane is correct?",
    "feedback": "When determining the maximum allowable landing mass at destination, 60% of the available landing runway length should be taken into account."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane executes a steady glide at the speed for minimum glide angle. If the forward speed is kept constant, what is the effect of a lower mass?  Rate of descent / Glide angle / CL/CD ratio",
    "feedback": "increases / increases / decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what altitude would a propeller aircraft reach its maximum endurance?",
    "feedback": "A piston engine at sea level"
  },
  {
    "question": "The flight manual of a light twin engine recommends two cruise power settings, 65 and 75 %. The 75% power setting in relation to the 65 % results in:",
    "feedback": "an increase in speed, fuel consumption and fuel-burn/distance."
  },
  {
    "question": "For multiengine aircraft weighing less than 5700 kg in normal CAT, the landing distance required on destination must not exceed:",
    "feedback": "0.7 x landing distance available"
  },
  {
    "question": "The optimum long range cruise altitude for a turbojet aeroplane:",
    "feedback": "increases when the aeroplane mass decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum demonstrated crosswind component is equal to 0.2 VSO and the\nfollowing conditions exist at an airport of intended landing:\nVSO 70 Kt, Landing Rwy 35, Wind 300° at 20 Kt.",
    "feedback": "maximum demonstrated crosswind component is exceeded."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, for turbo-prop aeroplanes, the required runway length at a destination airport:",
    "feedback": "is the same as at an alternate airport."
  },
  {
    "question": "You depart from Madrid, where the gradient of the SID is 5 %. Your average ground speed is 250 kts. What is the minimum rate of climb you have to maintain (approximately) in order to comply with the gradient?",
    "feedback": "1300 ft/min"
  },
  {
    "question": "The speed used to determine the \"maximum tyre-speed limit\" is the:",
    "feedback": "groundspeed"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift- off speed and take-off safety speed (V2) when flap position is changed from 10° to 5° will:",
    "feedback": "increase\tand\tincrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Below the optimum cruise altitude",
    "feedback": "the Mach number for long range cruise decreases continuously with decreasing altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use CAP 698, Figure 4.7)\nGiven the following information, what is the Maximum Take-Off Mass (MTOM) eventually limited by VMBE for the MRJT aeroplane?\nPA: 1457 ftSlope: 0.4% downQNH: 1013.25 hPaOAT: 19°CV1: 148 ktTailwind: 10 kt",
    "feedback": "64000 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the definition of \"wet ice\", regarding contaminated runways?",
    "feedback": "Ice with a layer of water (any depth) on top of it, or ice that is melting"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual SEP1, Figure 2.1)\nWith regard to the take-off performance chart for the single engine aeroplane and with regard to the commencement of a commercial flight, determine the maximum allowable take-off mass. Given:\nOAT: ISAPressure Altitude: 4000 ftHeadwind Component: 5 ktsFlaps: UpRunway: Tarred and dryTODA=TORA=ASDA: 2500 ftObstacle height: 50 ft",
    "feedback": "3240 lbs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which graph illustrates the movement of the total drag curve as density altitude increases?",
    "feedback": "Figure 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the all-engines climb gradient for a twin-engine aeroplane with the following data given?\nThrust per engine: 33000 lbsMass: 89500 kgLift to drag ratio: 7.8:1g = 10 m/s2",
    "feedback": "20.7 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of an engine failure recognized below V1",
    "feedback": "the take-off must be rejected."
  },
  {
    "question": "You are steadily climbing with a multi-engine piston airplane. What happens to VX and on the angle of climb, in case of an engine failure and with the propeller of the failed engine in the feathered position?",
    "feedback": "VX increases and the angle of climb decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Runway 30 is in use and the threshold elevation is 2139 feet, threshold elevation of runway 12 is 2289 feet. Take-off run available is 1720 metres and clearway is 280 metres. What is the slope of the runway in use?",
    "feedback": "2.65% uphill"
  },
  {
    "question": "For this question use CAP 698, Figure 3.7\nWhat is the time required by a multi-engined piston aeroplane to climb 2400 ft? Assume that the rate of climb is constant throughout the climb and equals the rate of climb at 6000 ft pressure altitude. Use the following data:\n2 engines operating at maximum continuous powerGear retractedOAT +17°CPressure altitude 6000 ftMass 4000 lb",
    "feedback": "1 minute 33 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is preparing for a flight and manually extracts the relevant data from the aircraft performance charts. He then goes to cross check this data with his EFB and notices a difference in the values. What may be the cause for this variance?",
    "feedback": "The EFB is more accurate as it does not interpolate the parametres"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following an engine failure on a twin-engined aircraft the thrust available is (1) ...... and the excess of thrust over drag is (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) reduced by 50 %, (2) reduced by more than 50 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "Besides lift, the forces that determine the gradient of climb of an aeroplane are:",
    "feedback": "weight, drag and thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "During pre-flight planning, the flight crew have calculated various performance limiting masses for two take-off flap/slat position settings. From the table, select the optimum flap/slat position and maximum PLTOM while ensuring compliance with the applicable operational requirements for Commercial Air Transport.",
    "feedback": "Flap/slat position setting 1 and 17000 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "For planning purposes, determine the net distance travelled down to 4000 feet for a  single-engine piston aircraft following an engine failure at 8000 ft. Given the following data:\nTAS: 120 ktsGS: 150 ktsGross gradient of descent 11 %Gross/net gradient decrement 0.5 %\nstill air distance (ft) = (height difference (ft) x 100) / % gradientGround distance = still air distance x (GS / TAS)",
    "feedback": "7.1 NM"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effect of a higher take-off flap setting up to the optimum is:",
    "feedback": "an increase of the field length limited take-off mass but a decrease of the climb limited take-off mass."
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual MEP1, Fig. 3.1)\nGiven the following information, what is the take-off distance?\nAirfield PA: 3000 ftAirfield Temperature: +16°CHeadwind Component: 6 ktTake-Off Mass: 4200 lb",
    "feedback": "1850 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "For take-off obstacle clearance calculations, obstacles in the first segment may be avoided",
    "feedback": "by banking not more than 15° between 50 ft and 400 ft above the runway elevation."
  },
  {
    "question": "How does a change in Pressure Altitude affect the climb performance with regard to the Rate Of Climb and the Climb Angle? Increasing Pressure Altitude results in ......",
    "feedback": "a decreased Rate of Climb and a decreased Climb Angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a segment of the take-off flight path an obstacle requires a minimum gradient of climb of 2.6% in order to provide an adequate margin of safe clearance.  At a mass of 110000 kg the gradient of climb is 2.8%.  For the same power and assuming that the sine of the angle of climb varies inversely with mass, at what maximum mass will the aeroplane be able to achieve the minimum gradient?",
    "feedback": "118455 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "300 feet before the start of the runway there is an obstacle 50 ft high. How much is the threshold displaced:",
    "feedback": "700 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual SEP1, Figure 2.1)\nWith regard to the take-off performance chart for the single engine aeroplane determine the approximate take-off distance to a height of 50 ft. Given:\nOAT: 30°CPressure Altitude: 1000 ftAeroplane Mass: 3450 lbsTailwind component: 2.5 ktsFlaps: upRunway: Tarred and dry",
    "feedback": "2500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "During certification test flights for a turbojet aeroplane, the actual measured take-off runs from brake release to a point equidistant between the point at which VLOF is reached and the point at which the aeroplane is 35 feet above the take-off surface are: - 1747 m, all engines operating - 1950 m, with the critical engine failure recognized at V1, the other factors remaining unchanged. Considering both possibilities to determine the take-off run (TOR). What is the correct distance?",
    "feedback": "2009 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the vertical speed of a three-engined turbojet with one engine inoperative? (Mass = 75000kg, TAS = 190kt, g = 10 m/s^2)",
    "feedback": "+ 1283 ft/min"
  },
  {
    "question": "With all other things remaining unchanged and with T the outside static air temperature expressed in degrees K, the hourly fuel consumption of a turbojet powered aeroplane in a cruise flight with a constant Mach Number and zero headwind,is as follows:",
    "feedback": "proportional to T"
  },
  {
    "question": "A decrease in atmospheric pressure has, among other things, the following consequences on take-off performance:",
    "feedback": "an increased take-off distance and degraded initial climb performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual MRJT1, Fig. 4.28)\nGiven:\nAirport Pressure Altitude: 4000 ftRunway Condition: dryField Length: 2100 mWind: 30 kts headFlaps: 15°Manual Spoilers and Anti-skid: Operative\nUsing the data, determine the Field Length Limiting Landing Mass (FLLLM):",
    "feedback": "57200 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the maximum specific range for a propeller aircraft?",
    "feedback": "VMD"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the thrust  available exceeds the thrust required for level flight",
    "feedback": "the aeroplane accelerates if the altitude is maintained."
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use CAP 698, Figure 4.7)\nGiven the following information, what is the Maximum Take-Off Mass (MTOM) eventually limited by VMBE for the MRJT aeroplane?\nPA: 130 ftSlope: 0.1 % upQNH: 1013 hPaOAT: 21°CV1: 149 ktTailwind: 5 kt",
    "feedback": "Greater than 68000 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the antiskid system is inoperative, which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "The accelerate stop distance increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Take-off run is defined as the",
    "feedback": "horizontal distance along the take-off path from the start of the take-off to a point equidistant between the point at which VLOF is reached and the point at which the aeroplane is 35 ft above the take-off surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "(For this Question use Flight Planning & Monitoring SEP1 Fig. 2.3.1) Using the Power Setting Table, for the single engine aeroplane, determine the cruise TAS and fuel flow (lbs/hr) with full throttle and cruise lean mixture in the following conditions:\nGiven :\nOAT:                          3°C\nPressure altitude:        6000 ft\nPower:                       Full throttle / 21,0 in/Hg./ 2100 RPM",
    "feedback": "134 kt and  55,7 lbs/hr"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the actual landing mass is higher than planned:",
    "feedback": "the landing distance will be longer"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual MEP1, Fig. 3.9)\nGiven:\nFlaps: 40°Aerodrome pressure altitude: Sea levelAmbient temperature: +15°CLanding weight: 4000 lbsWind: CalmRunway: Paved and dry\nWhat is the landing distance?",
    "feedback": "2400 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the value of the balanced V1 is found to be lower than VMCG, which of the following is correct ?",
    "feedback": "The take-off is not permitted."
  },
  {
    "question": "The pilot of a light twin engine aircraft has calculated a 4 000 m service ceiling, based on the forecast general conditions for the flight and a take-off mass of 3 250 kg.\n\nIf the take-off mass is 3 000 kg, the service ceiling will be:",
    "feedback": "higher than 4 000 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following combinations basically has an effect on the angle of descent in a glide? (Ignore compressibility effects.)",
    "feedback": "Configuration and angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "In the second segment  during take off, flap and gear are:",
    "feedback": "TKOF position/ retracted"
  },
  {
    "question": "A lower airspeed at constant mass and altitude requires",
    "feedback": "a higher coefficient of lift."
  },
  {
    "question": "For jet-engined aeroplanes, what is the effect of increased altitude on specific range?",
    "feedback": "Increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the best angle of climb and best rate of climb vary with increasing altitude?",
    "feedback": "Both decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "The picture shows dominant obstacles on runways 09/27 and on runway 18 at a particular aerodrome. For a take-off in a Class B aeroplane from runway 09, and given the following information, by what height would you clear the power lines?\nStill air gradient 5%10 kt tailwindTAS 135 KT1 NM = 6080 ftHeight difference = ((GDxTAS/GS) x gradient)/100",
    "feedback": "74 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The rate of climb is approximately equal to:",
    "feedback": "the still-air gradient multiplied by the TAS"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Take-Off Distance Available (TODA) is the length of the take-off run available, plus the length ......",
    "feedback": "of the clearway, if provided"
  },
  {
    "question": "Your route of the day is London-Paris-London in a performance class B aeroplane. During the approach into London, the QNH has reduced considerably since the earlier departure, with a small increase in temperature. You expect your aircraft's performance to (1) ...... as the landing distance required will (2) ...... and the missed approach climb gradient will (3) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) reduce, (2) increase, (3) reduce"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is V2 determined?",
    "feedback": "Highest of 1.13 x VSR and 1.1 x VMC"
  },
  {
    "question": "Higher gross mass at the same altitude decreases the gradient and the rate of climb whereas",
    "feedback": "VY and VX are increased."
  },
  {
    "question": "The effect on a too late rotation will be an",
    "feedback": "increase the ground roll but climb ability will be good"
  },
  {
    "question": "The engine failure take-off run is:",
    "feedback": "the horizontal distance along the take-off path from the start of the take-off to a point equidistant between the point at which VLOF is reached and the point at which the aeroplane is 35 ft above the take-off surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure and choose the correct statement below:",
    "feedback": "Point C represents the maximum angle of climb"
  },
  {
    "question": "With a decreased flap setting from 20° to 10° on take off the effect will be:-",
    "feedback": "VLOF  and V2 would both increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding unaccelerated horizontal flight, minimum drag is:",
    "feedback": "proportional to aircraft mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct for a descent without engine thrust at maximum lift to drag ratio speed?",
    "feedback": "A tailwind component increases the ground distance."
  },
  {
    "question": "VX is",
    "feedback": "the speed for best angle of climb."
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual MRJT1, Fig. 4.1)\nGiven the following information, what is the maximum allowed wind speed?\nAeroplane maximum allowed crosswind component: 25 ktRunway direction: 240°(M)Wind direction: 190°(M)",
    "feedback": "32 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual MRJT1, Fig. 4.4)\nGiven:\nTake-off Mass: 58500 kgPressure Altitude: 1000 ftOutside Air Temperature (OAT): -7°CFlaps: 15°Wind: 10 kts headRunway slope: 1% downAir Conditioning (A/C) Packs: Off\nUsing the above data, determine the take-off distance:",
    "feedback": "5500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The speed for maximum lift/drag ratio will result in :",
    "feedback": "The maximum range for a propeller driven aeroplane."
  },
  {
    "question": "Determine the Specific Range (SR), given:\nFuel flow: 28 IMP GAL/hrSpecific gravity: 0.72TAS: 154 MPH",
    "feedback": "1.46 NM air distance/kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "A difference between a reduced (flex) and a derated thrust take-off is that ......",
    "feedback": "on a flex take-off, the TOGA thrust remains available"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the difference between a flex temperature takeoff and derated thrust takeoff?",
    "feedback": "TOGA is always available when using flex temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following sequences of speed for a jet aeroplane is correct ? (from low to high speeds)",
    "feedback": "Vs, maximum angle climb speed, maximum range speed."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is flying westwards over the middle of the Alps when it suffers an engine failure. The operator has defined two possible escape routes from the area, both of equal distance and terrain profile. In order to maximise terrain clearance, which escape route should the pilots take, and what speed should they descend at?\n1) Escape route North, with a tailwind2) Escape route South, with a headwind3) Descend at high speed (close to VMO, maximum operating limit speed)4) Descend at low speed (close to VMD, minimum drag speed)",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "(For this question use Performance Manual MRJT 1 Figure 4.5)\nWith regard to the take-off performance of a twin jet aeroplane, why does the take-off performance climb limit graph show a kink at 30°C, pressure altitude 0?",
    "feedback": "At higher temperatures the flat rated engines determines the climb limit mass."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the minimum value of VR for a single engine piston aircraft according to EASA CS-23, with a stall speed of 68 kt?",
    "feedback": "68 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "From the screen height of 50 ft, a single-engined piston aeroplane performs a straight-out climb in visual meteorological conditions with a climb gradient of 9%, a TAS of 60 kt and a headwind component of 10 kt. What will be the expected height clearance of a group of trees that are 8 m tall and located at a distance of 250 m on the extended runway centre line from reference zero?",
    "feedback": "34 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual SEP1, Fig 2.2)\nGiven the following information and assuming runway conditions and power setting as given in the graph, what is the Field Length Limited Take-off Mass?\nTORA: 1820 ftTODA: 2200 ft (clearway installed)ASDA: 1820 ftRunway surface: PavedRunway condition: WetPressure Altitude: 2000 ftAirfield Temperature: 0°CHeadwind component:5 kts",
    "feedback": "3400 lbs"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following distances can the length of a stopway be included?",
    "feedback": "In the accelerate stop distance available."
  },
  {
    "question": "CS 25.125 specifies the requirements for determining the landing distance of an aeroplane. According to that rule, what is the earliest point at which wheel brakes may be applied by the pilot?",
    "feedback": "When only the main wheels are firmly on the ground, provided the nose gear can be lowered in a controlled manner"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual SEP1, Figure 2.2)\nWith regard to the take-off performance chart for the single engine aeroplane determine the take-off distance to a height of 50 ft. Given:\nOAT: 30°CPressure Altitude: 1000 ftAeroplane Mass: 3400 lbsTailwind component: 10 ktsFlaps: ApproachRunway: Tarred and dry",
    "feedback": "2500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The 'climb gradient' is defined as the ratio of",
    "feedback": "the increase of altitude to horizontal distance over ground expressed as a percentage."
  },
  {
    "question": "Following a take-off, limited by the 50 ft screen height, a light twin climbs on a gradient of 9%. It will clear a 800 ft obstacle in relation to the runway at sea level (horizontally), situated at 2 NM from the 50 ft point with an obstacle clearance margin of:",
    "feedback": "344 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A higher altitude at constant mass and Mach number requires",
    "feedback": "a higher angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "The use of reduced take-off thrust is permitted, only if:",
    "feedback": "The actual take-off mass (TOM) is lower than the field length limited TOM."
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding performance and safety for commercial air transport:\n1) Airplane performance required may limit the weight of a dispatched aeroplane2) The minimum level of safety is ensured through the combination of airworthiness requirements and operational limitations3) Net performance is the gross performance diminished to allow for various contingencies that cannot be accounted for operationally4) The safety margin required for public transport is based on the probability of an event/incident/accident being less than 1 in 1 billion when a passenger buys his/her ticket.\nThe combination regrouping all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The coefficient of lift can be increased either by flap extension or by",
    "feedback": "increasing the angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual SEP1, Figure 2.3)\nFind the rate of climb at an altitude of 12000 ft if the following information is given:\nGross mass: 2950 lbsClimb power: full throttleSpeed: 100 kts IASTemperature: ISA +15°CQNH: 1013 hPaHeadwind: 10 kts",
    "feedback": "740 ft/min"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compare a take-off at an airport with low air density with a take-off at an airport with high air density. A take-off with high air density ambient conditions leads to a/an ......",
    "feedback": "increased V2MIN"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Multi Engine Jet Aircraft with a passenger capacity of less than 9 and a MTOM of less than 5700 kg belongs to which performance class?",
    "feedback": "Performance class A, because all jet aircraft belong to this performance class"
  },
  {
    "question": "The optimum cruise altitude is",
    "feedback": "the pressure altitude at which the best specific range can be achieved."
  },
  {
    "question": "A twin engined aeroplane in cruise flight with one engine inoperative has to fly over high ground. In order to maintain the highest possible altitude the pilot should choose:",
    "feedback": "the speed corresponding to the maximum value of the lift / drag ratio."
  },
  {
    "question": "Performance data from two calculations using an Electronic Flight Bag are shown. ATC has received reports of windshear and, since the operator SOP is to use TOGA under such conditions, the pilot prepare for both a TOGA take-off and a take-off at an assumed/FLEX temperature of 41°C.\nThe pilots do not change any data other than the thrust setting. However, one result of the different calculations is that ....",
    "feedback": "the take-off using TOGA thrust is using the principle of a balanced field take-off as this gives the best relationship between distances and weight"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a glide at constant Mach number, the pitch angle of the aeroplane will:",
    "feedback": "decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cruise system gives minimum fuel consumption during cruise between top of climb and top of descent (still air, no turbulence)?",
    "feedback": "Maximum range"
  },
  {
    "question": "The absolute ceiling",
    "feedback": "is the altitude at which the rate of climb theoretically is zero."
  },
  {
    "question": "Density altitude is the",
    "feedback": "pressure altitude corrected for 'non standard' temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "The approach climb requirement has been established so that the aeroplane will achieve:",
    "feedback": "minimum climb gradient in the event of a go-around with one engine inoperative."
  },
  {
    "question": "Following a take-off, limited by the 50 ft screen height, a light twin climbs on a gradient of 5%.\nIt will clear a 160 m obstacle in relation to the runway (horizontally), situated at 5 000 m from the 50 ft point with an obstacle clearance margin of:",
    "feedback": "105 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering max range vs headwind :",
    "feedback": "higher speed for obtaining max range"
  },
  {
    "question": "(for this question use Performance Manual SEP1, Fig. 2.3)\nGiven the following information, what are the ROC and climb gradient?\nClimb Speed: 110 kt TASGross Mass: 3100 lbOAT: +13°CQNH: 1030 hPaAltitude: 6000 ft",
    "feedback": "1140 ft, 10.1%"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is in a power off glide at speed for minimum glide angle. If the pilot increases pitch attitude the glide distance:",
    "feedback": "decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Define the term \"screen height\":",
    "feedback": "The height at the end of the take-off distance required and at the beginning of the landing distance required"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Regulated Take-Off Mass (RTOM) table for runway 23L from take-off position VB. In each RTOM chart box, the following information is provided for a given wind component, and a given outside air temperature:\nMTOM (1000 kg) / limit code /V1/VR/V2 (+100 kt)\nUse the data below to determine the RTOM for departure. For this question do not interpolate. Choose the most conservative figures at all times:\nW/V 23005KTModerate rainOAT + 12°CQNH 1015 hPaEngine anti-ice OFFPacks OFFQuick line-up",
    "feedback": "77570 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum indicated air speed of a piston engined aeroplane without turbo charger, in level flight, is reached:",
    "feedback": "at the lowest possible altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "A turn has to be initiated in the second segment of the take-off flight path, where a net climb gradient of 2.0 % is required due to an obstacle. The bank angle of the twin-engine jet during the turn is 15° but the AFM gives a decrement of 0.5 % for the turn.\nWhat is the minimum required gross gradient before commencing the turn, if regulation and obstacle clearance must be considered?",
    "feedback": "3.3 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "The long range cruise speed is in relation to the speed for maximum range cruise.",
    "feedback": "Higher"
  },
  {
    "question": "During take-off the third segment begins:",
    "feedback": "when acceleration to flap retraction speed is started."
  },
  {
    "question": "You are departing with a single-engine piston airplane in VMC. At the screen height of 50 ft, you are climbing straight ahead with a climb gradient of 9 % and a TAS of 60 kt. There is a headwind component of 10 kt.\nWhat will be the expected height clearance of a group of trees with a height of 8 m and located at a distance of 250 m on the extended runway centre line from reference zero?",
    "feedback": "34 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of engine failure below V1, the first action to be taken by the pilot in order to decelerate the aeroplane is to:",
    "feedback": "reduce the engine thrust."
  },
  {
    "question": "The CS-25 regulations published by EASA specify definitions regarding climb gradients and net climb gradients. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "The net climb gradient is based on the gross climb gradient, reduced to account for safety margins based on the number of engines"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a turbojet aeroplane, what is the maximum landing distance for wet runways when the landing distance available at an aerodrome is 3000 m?",
    "feedback": "1565 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "All other criteria being equal, what factor can reduce the landing distance?",
    "feedback": "The use of spoilers"
  },
  {
    "question": "Maximum endurance for jet aircraft are found",
    "feedback": "where thrust required to maintain level flight is minimum"
  },
  {
    "question": "During take-off calculation, using a low V1 will, assuming other condition being equal give",
    "feedback": "a shorter accelerate stop distance required and a relative long take-off distance required"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are to be taken into account for the runway in use for take-off ?",
    "feedback": "Airport elevation, runway slope, outside air temperature, pressure altitude and wind components."
  },
  {
    "question": "With a true airspeed of 194 kt and a vertical speed of 1 000 ft/min, the climb angle is about :",
    "feedback": "3°"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a take-off in a Performance Class A aircraft, you will need to apply more than 15 degrees of bank. The required vertical obstacle clearance margin....",
    "feedback": "is increased from 35 ft to 50 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, in relation to the climb limited take-off mass of a jet aeroplane, is correct?",
    "feedback": "The climb limited take-off mass decreases with increasing OAT."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the criteria for Performance Class B aeroplanes as regards the Maximum Operational Passenger Seating Configuration MOPSC, Maximum Take Off Mass MTOM and engine? MOPSC of ......",
    "feedback": "9 or less, MTOM below 5700 kg, and propeller engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Other factors being equal , an increase in take-off weight will",
    "feedback": "increase lift off and stalling speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the copilot continuously feels unfairly treated by the captain in an unjustified way, then he should",
    "feedback": "duly point out the problem, reconcentrate on his duties and clear the matter in a more appropriate occasion"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Pilot Monitoring (PM) and Pilot Flying (PF) are good friends and have worked together many times. The PF is junior to the PM and respects and trusts him/her greatly. The PF decides not to call out all the required SOPs when using the aircraft's advanced cockpit automation as the PF feels they are excessive.\nWhat can this lead to?",
    "feedback": "Loss of crew communication, leading to loss of awareness of flight modes, input errors not being detected, lack of failure detection, and comprehension of the aircraft's status"
  },
  {
    "question": "What should a pilot do to keep his night vision (scotopic vision)?",
    "feedback": "Not smoke before start and during flight and avoid flash-blindness"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the content of Boyle's law?",
    "feedback": "The volume of a gas is inversely proportional to its pressure, with temperature remaining constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cognitive effects of stress may include :\n-1 : excessive haste.\n-2 : an improvement in memory.\n-3 : a complete block: action is impossible.\n-4 : a risk of focusing on a particular aspect.\n-5 : ease of decision-making.\n-6 : an increase in the rate of mistakes.\n\nThe combination which brings together all correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1,3,4,6"
  },
  {
    "question": "An unnoticed waypoint error entered in an aircraft data base is an example of:",
    "feedback": "latent failure/error"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the waste products of the metabolic process in the cell is :",
    "feedback": "carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "The crew of an Airbus A320 is flying towards an airport in severe thunderstorms and reported wind shear conditions. Due to several aircraft going around, delays are to be expected and the crew is cleared into a holding pattern. Preoccupied with the weather ahead of them, the crew fails to notice that they have accidentally pulled back the thrust levers too far, disabling the autothrottle. As airspeed drops and aerodynamic buffet sets in, it is interpreted by the crew as entry into turbulence. When the aircraft actually stalls, the crew is convinced to have encountered wind shear and performs the appropriate escape manoeuvre. As the manoeuvre includes applying full thrust, the crew can successfully recover from the stall and land safely.\nWhat is correct regarding the initial error?",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "The crew of an Airbus A320 is flying towards an airport in severe thunderstorms and reported wind shear conditions. Due to several aircraft going around, delays are to be expected and the crew is cleared into a holding pattern. Preoccupied with the weather ahead of them, the crew fails to notice that they have accidentally pulled back the thrust levers too far, disabling the autothrottle. As airspeed drops and aerodynamic buffet sets in, it is interpreted by the crew as entry into turbulence. When the aircraft actually stalls, the crew is convinced to have encountered wind shear and performs the appropriate escape manoeuvre. As the manoeuvre includes applying full thrust, the crew can successfully recover from the stall and land safely.\nWhat is correct regarding the initial error?",
    "feedback": "The error was due to internal factors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering hypoxia, which of the following statements are correct regarding Effective Performance Time (EPT)?\n1) EPT will be shorter than the Time of Useful Conciousness (TUC), for any given altitude2) The duration of EPT varies little between individuals3) The effect of stress on the duration of EPT is minimal4) For a person at rest EPT can be about 12 to 20 seconds, at a pressure altitude of 40000 ft.",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Decision-making can be influenced by the following factors:\n\n1. people tend to conform to opinions expressed by a majority within the group they belong to\n2. people always tend to keep the future decisions in line with those their superiors have made in the past\n3. people more easily tend to select data which meet the expectations\n4. people hardly base decisions on their personal preferences but rather on rational information",
    "feedback": "1,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an emergency, an alarm sounds and continues to do so after you have stopped being aware of it. Of what is this an example?",
    "feedback": "Habituation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The symptoms of hyperventilation are easily confused with those of",
    "feedback": "hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "The three coats of the eye are",
    "feedback": "sclera, uvea, retina"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is most true?",
    "feedback": "Regular exercise is beneficial to general health, but the most efficient way to lose weight is by reducing caloric consumption"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which are the two restorative processes that regulate the human body's pattern of sleepiness and alertness throughout the day?",
    "feedback": "Sleep/wake homeostasis and the circadian rhythm"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is on approach and experiences bad weather conditions very close to minimums. While the commander remarks that he can see the runway and that a landing seems possible, the Copilot explains that he is unable to see the runway..At the last moment the Copilot also states that he is now visual and the crew continues the approach and lands.\nWhat behaviour are they displaying?",
    "feedback": "Group risky shift"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the TUC at 18'000 FT?",
    "feedback": "about 30 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The group of tiny bones (the hammer, anvil and stirrup) are situated in",
    "feedback": "the middle ear"
  },
  {
    "question": "When spinning an aircraft, the predominating type of acceleration will be",
    "feedback": "angular acceleration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stress Exposure Training (SET) is a method to help pilots manage stress in flight. Pilots are first trained in stress control techniques, then during subsequent flight simulator sessions, the pilot must cope with an external, harmless source of stress while learning aparticular skill.\nWhich of the following statements is correct? This type of training:",
    "feedback": "Is a long-term stress management method that can improve performance in flight operations, if integrated in a continuous professional training programme"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are subjected to an illusion during night flying you should:",
    "feedback": "continue on instruments"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pressurized cabin helps to prevent:\n1. decompression sickness\n2 the problem of expansion of gases in the intestines\n3. hypoxia\n4. coronary disease",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 3 are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "Ozone",
    "feedback": "consists of molecular oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal visual acuity allows discrimination of two different points under an angle of",
    "feedback": "1 minute of arc"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Pilot's vertigo\":",
    "feedback": "is a sensation of rotation during flight due to multiple irritation of several semicircular canals at the same time"
  },
  {
    "question": "Trace elements should be obtained through:",
    "feedback": "a balanced diet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following describes an autocratic cockpit?",
    "feedback": "The captain's excessive authority considerably reduces communications and consequently the synergy and cohesion of the crew"
  },
  {
    "question": "The use of check lists must be carried out in such a way that:",
    "feedback": "their execution must not be done simultaneously with other actions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Typical signs and symptoms of decompression sickness are:",
    "feedback": "Tingling, dry cough, joint pain (bends) and dizziness"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft departs from a major airport. According to the preflight briefing, the Commander flies the departure procedure and the Copilot monitors speed, level, and communications. After departure, due to the distraction caused by ATC transmissions, the Copilot retracts the flaps without noticing that the speed is below that required for flap retraction. While responding to the subsequent speed warning, the Commander allows the aircraft to climb above its cleared altitude. What are the error types illustrated in this scenario?\n1) Communication error: Copilot fails to inform the Commander of the speed before retracting the flaps2) Communication error: Copilot fails to tell the Commander about the altitude deviation3) Handling error: Commander fails to control the speed and rate of climb4) Procedural error: Copilot fails to monitor the speed and altitude5) Procedural error: Commander fails to achieve the correct flap retraction speed6) Procedural error: Commander and Copilot fail to level the aircraft at the cleared altitude",
    "feedback": "3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "An increase in workload usually leads to:",
    "feedback": "a shorter and less frequent exchange of information"
  },
  {
    "question": "Underload decreases the performance capabilities of pilots. It is most likely to occur.....",
    "feedback": "On long flights"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what altitude (\"threshold for compensatory reactions\") does the human organism start with remarkable measures to compensate for the drop in pO2 when climbing?\nAt about:",
    "feedback": "6000-7000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "A line check captain is flying with a newly promoted captain who has successfully completed the command course. The new captain is flying in the commander's seat, and is being assessed as the commander. Which option is correct?",
    "feedback": "The new captain is the commander for this flight only if he/she has been designated as such by the operator"
  },
  {
    "question": "The body loses water via:\n1. the skin and the lungs\n2. the kidneys",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cognitive psychology identifies several factors that affect a person's level of attention. They include:",
    "feedback": "Environmental, physiological and task factors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option correctly identifies, from the items listed below, the effects of arousal on performance?\n1) It always reduces performance2) Optimum perfornace is obtained with optimum arousal3) Excessive levels of arousal weaken performance4) Insufficient levels of arousal weaken performance",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In civil air transport, linear accelerations (Gx):\n- 1 : do not exist\n- 2 : have slight physiological consequences\n- 3 : may, in the case of pull-out, lead to loss of consciousness\n- 4 : cause sensory illusions on the pitch axis",
    "feedback": "2,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dry air is a mixture of gases. Their volume percentage is about:",
    "feedback": "21% oxygen,78% nitrogen, 1% other gases"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role should automation play with respect to flight safety?",
    "feedback": "Automation should be used as an aid to the pilot and not as an end itself"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following factors tend to decrease your state of vigilance:\n1) Monotony2) Increased workload3) Constant and monotonous noise4) Low lighting5) Low ambient temperature6) Distracting tasks7) Sleep debt",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 4, 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vertigo can be brought on by:",
    "feedback": "disease, accelerations, pressure changes and flashing lights"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of the following statements, select those which apply to \"information\".\n-1 : It is said to be random when it is not intended for receivers.\n-2 : It is intended to reduce uncertainty for the receiver.\n-3 : It is measured in bits.\n-4 : Each bit of information reduces uncertainty by a quarter.\n\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "2 and 3 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The so-called Coriolis effect (a conflict in information processing in the brain) in spatial disorientation occurs:",
    "feedback": "on stimulating several semicircular canals simultaneously"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypoxia is:",
    "feedback": "a physical condition caused by a lack of oxygen to meet the needs of the body tissues, leading to mental and muscular  disturbances, causing impaired thinking, poor judgement and slow reactions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following mechanisms regulate body temperature when exposed to extremely high environmental temperatures?\n-1 : Shivering\n-2 : Vasoconstriction of peripheral blood vessels\n-3 : Sweating\n-4 : Vasodilation of peripheral blood vessels",
    "feedback": "3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The transfer of carbon dioxide from the blood to the alveoli can be described by:",
    "feedback": "the law of diffusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following operations are performed more effectively by people than by automatic systems ?\n1. Qualitative decision-making\n2. Waiting for an infrequent phenomenon\n3. Monitoring to ensure that certain values are not exceeded\n4. Detections of unusual conditions (smell, noise, etc.)",
    "feedback": "1,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name for  the sensation of rotation occuring during flight and which is caused by multiple irritation of several semicircular canals at the same time?",
    "feedback": "\"Pilot's\" Vertigo."
  },
  {
    "question": "After a rapid decompression at an altitude of 30.000 FT the first action of the pilot shall be:",
    "feedback": "maintaining aircraft control and preventing hypoxia (use of oxygen mask)"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a rapid decompression at 35000 feet, the Time of Useful Consciousness is about:",
    "feedback": "30 to 60 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Autokinetic illusion is:",
    "feedback": "an illusion in which a stationary point of light, if stared at for several seconds in the dark, may - without a frame of reference -  appear to move"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which would most likely result in hyperventilation?",
    "feedback": "Emotional tension, anxiety or fear"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following a flight that crosses numerous time zones, the associated shifting of Zeitgebers helps body clock re-synchronisation to the new local time at the rate of:",
    "feedback": "1.5 hours per day"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following answers are correct concerning the long term memory?\n\n1) Long term memory can be affected by expectation and suggestion\n2) Long term memory is also known as the working memory\n3) Long term memory is limited to plus or minus 7 pieces of disassociated pieces of information\n4) Long term memory is where motor programmes (skills) are kept",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cupula in the semicircular canal will be bent, when a rotation begins. This is because",
    "feedback": "the fluid (endolymph) within the semicircular canal  lags behind the accelerated canal walls"
  },
  {
    "question": "The ozone layer is",
    "feedback": "in the stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by the term CRM today?",
    "feedback": "Crew resource management"
  },
  {
    "question": "Very high ambition and need for achievement",
    "feedback": "disturb the climate of cooperation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option correctly lists, for pilots, the three most critical types of perception illusion and corresponding examples?",
    "feedback": "Visual illusion (blind spots); kinaesthetic illusion (having the leans), and auditory illusion (missed radio call)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The acquisition of a motor programme (skill) will mean that:",
    "feedback": "the more behaviour is automated, the less it requires conscious attention and thus the more it frees mental resources."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding personality?",
    "feedback": "Your personality develops during the first few years of your life"
  },
  {
    "question": "The rate and depth of breathing is primarily controlled by:",
    "feedback": "the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "Below are four statements about rods and cones. Which one is true?",
    "feedback": "Cones give the best visual acuity"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the decision making process in the cockpit:",
    "feedback": "the amount of time available has a large influence on the analysis of the situation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Smaller objects from a given distance are normally perceived as being further away than larger objects from the same distance. Which type of perception causes this?",
    "feedback": "Top-down processing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The volume percentage of oxygen in  the atmosphere at 30.000 feet remains at 21 %; but the partial pressure of oxygen :",
    "feedback": "decreases with decreasing barometric pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of the following statements, which apply to coordinated cooperation?\n-1 : It allows for synergy in the actions between the captain and the\n      pilot.\n-2 : It represents the simultaneous execution of a single action by \n       the various members of the crew.\n-3 : Communication in this mode has the function of synchronizing \n       actions and distributing responsibilities.\n-4 : Communication must be essentially focussed on temporal and\n       cognitive synchronisation.\n\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "1 and 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is decompression sickness ?",
    "feedback": "An sickness resulting from the formation of nitrogen bubbles in bodily tissues and fluids after a cabin pressure loss at high altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of the following alternatives, which objective effects are due to positive acceleration (+ Gz)?\n- 1: Decrease in heart rate\n- 2: Pooling of blood into lower parts of the body\n- 3: Drop in blood pressure above heart-level\n- 4: Downward displacement or deformation of soft or mobile organs",
    "feedback": "2,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft starts its take-off run with ice deposits remaining on its wings. The cabin crew was aware of the icing, because passengers had pointed it out. However, they were reluctant to inform the pilots. \nThe error which was committed by the cabin crew members is:",
    "feedback": "Social"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct regarding the use of cockpit lighting for night flight?",
    "feedback": "The use of regular white light, such as flashlight, will impair night adaption"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sleeplessness or the disruption of sleeping patterns \n\n1. can lead to symptoms of drowsiness, irritability and lack of concentration\n2. will make an individual more prone to make errors",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are both correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pain in the middle ear during descent may be eased by:",
    "feedback": "leveling off and possibly climbing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Man possesses a system for maintaining his internal equilibrium in the face of variations brought about by external stimulations. This internal equilibrium is called :",
    "feedback": "Homeostasis"
  },
  {
    "question": "By what action could the pressure gradient between the middle and the outer ear be balanced?",
    "feedback": "By swallowing"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is en route to the destination. The pilot in command briefs on the correct approach procedure and the copilot monitors height and speed on the approach. However, during the approach for landing, the speed increased above that required by the published approach procedure wihout the pilot's intention. This particular situation is an example of ......",
    "feedback": "a handling error by the commander and a procedural error by the copilot"
  },
  {
    "question": "The mechanism of accommodation is controlled by:",
    "feedback": "the functioning of the ciliary muscle around the lens"
  },
  {
    "question": "A balloon with 10 litres of air is brought from mean sea level up to 34 000 feet. What is the volume of the balloon at this altitude, provided the temperature is kept constant?",
    "feedback": "40 litres"
  },
  {
    "question": "Heart attack (myocardial infarction):",
    "feedback": "is a total blockage of a coronary artery leading to the death of a piece of heart muscle"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which biases relate to human decision making?\n1. Personal experience tends to alter the perception of the risk of an event occurring\n2. There is a natural tendency to want to confirm our decision even in the face of facts which contradict it\n3. The group to which an individual belongs tends to influence the particular decision\n4. There is natural tending to select only objective facts for decision-making purposes",
    "feedback": "1,2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Group norms:",
    "feedback": "regulate the interaction and the behaviour between the members of a group"
  },
  {
    "question": "A good way of dealing with long-term and chronic stress is to....",
    "feedback": "take care of the physical causes of stress"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are typical consequences of conflicts between crew members?\n-1  The quality of work performance decreases as a result of the \n      impoverishment of communications\n-2  A decrease in the quality of communications\n-3  In the case of a crew made up of experts, conflicts only result in \n      a deterioration in relations between the individuals\n-4  A decrease in the usage of available resources on the flight \n     deck\n\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In cumulative fatigue:",
    "feedback": "even in a normal flight duty period the fatigue may increase up to an unacceptable level"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stimuli must be of a certain strength for the receptors to pick them up. This is called:",
    "feedback": "sensory threshold"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at an altitude of 2000 feet. The aircraft must intercept the glide slope from above for an automatic ILS approach. The SPEED autothrottle mode is selected on the Mode Control Panel. Just before commencing descent, the left (number 1) radio altimeter reading drops to -8 ft, which automatically causes the autothrottle to close (RETARD). The right (number 2) radio altimeter reads 2000 ft. The pilots see the change in the autothrottle setting, but, as the number 2 radio altimeter is still operating, they assume that it still controls the autothrottle and that the RETARD mode is normal for the descent. They do not adjust the settings on the Mode Control Panel. On intercepting the glide slope, the pilots assume the autothrottle will automatically enter the SPEED mode, and do not detect that the throttles actually remain closed until the loss of airspeed becomes critical.\nWhat does this scenario indicate about the pilot's assessment of the situation?",
    "feedback": "The pilots have mode confusion and an incorrect mental model created by the cognitive illusion that the autothrottle is operating normally"
  },
  {
    "question": "Blood-pressure depends on:  \n1. the cardiac output  \n2. the resistance of the capillaries (peripheral resistance)",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "To reduce the risk of coronary artery disease, exercise should be",
    "feedback": "double the resting heart rate for at least 20 minutes, three times a week"
  },
  {
    "question": "The partial pressure of oxygen in inspired air:",
    "feedback": "is a highly significant factor in ensuring that oxygen diffuses from the lungs to the blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "When hyperventilating you should:",
    "feedback": "control your rate and depth of breathing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Among the factors which affect visual acuity are:",
    "feedback": "Hypoxia, age and angular distance from the fovea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Conductive hearing loss can be caused by:  \n1. damage to the ossicles in the middle ear caused by infection or trauma \n2. a damage of the auditory nerve \n3. an obstruction in the auditory duct \n4. a ruptured tympanic membrane",
    "feedback": "1,3 and 4 are correct, 2 is false"
  },
  {
    "question": "The time of useful consciousness without oxygen at an altitude of\n25 000 ft is:",
    "feedback": "2 – 3 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the most frequent results of an self-centred captain on the flight deck ?",
    "feedback": "In a two-pilot flight deck, the co-pilot is ignored and may react  by disengaging, showing  delayed responses or demonstrate the scapegoat effect"
  },
  {
    "question": "In-flight incapacitation of a pilot is most frequently caused by:",
    "feedback": "acute gastrointestinal disorders"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the statement which correctly describes the retention of skills:",
    "feedback": "Skills are stored in long-term memory. When skills are not practised for certain periods, they become less automated and a period of re-training is required"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is correct regarding the five stages in the sleep patterns?",
    "feedback": "About 50% of sleep is stage 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "When travelling in developing and tropical areas of the world, aircrew should avoid:\n\n1) ice cubes in drinks\n2) swimming in local lakes or rivers\n3) eating unpeeled fruit\n4) local ice cream and salads\n5) wearing short clothing in the evenings",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which flight manoeuvre will most likely induce vertigo? Turning the head while",
    "feedback": "banking"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pilot fitness to fly includes periodic medical examinations by specialized aviation medical personnel. Included in that examination is an assessment of the pilot's sensory system. In addition to sight and sound, which of the following are basic human senses?\n1) Intuition2) Thermoreception3) Touch4) Proprioception5) Smell6) Sixth sense7) Taste",
    "feedback": "3, 5, 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following applies for the physical properties of gases:",
    "feedback": "at sea-level a gas has 1/3 of the volume it would have at 27000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The performance of the man machine system is above all :",
    "feedback": "a combination which is based on decreasing the pilot's workload and increasing his time for supervision"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cockpit automation is traditionally intended to:",
    "feedback": "Relieve the pilots from certain routine tasks"
  },
  {
    "question": "The atmospheric pressure",
    "feedback": "at sea level is twice the amount of the pressure at 18 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum number of unrelated items that can be stored  in working memory is:",
    "feedback": "about 7 items"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following statements are true except",
    "feedback": "cones are responsible for night vision and are most densely in the fovea centralis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Barotrauma of the sinuses of the nose (aerosinusitis)",
    "feedback": "is caused by a difference in pressure existing between the sinus cavity and the ambient air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Success in achieving the objectives of a message requires:",
    "feedback": "the matching of verbal, non-verbal and contextual meanings"
  },
  {
    "question": "What effect does haze have on the abilities to see traffic or terrain features during flight?",
    "feedback": "Haze creates the illusion of being at a greater distance than actual from the runway and causes pilots to fly a lower approach"
  },
  {
    "question": "An efficient flight deck (synergetic cockpit) will be observed when:",
    "feedback": "decisions are taken by the Captain with the help and participation of the other crew members"
  },
  {
    "question": "Define Hypoxia and explain why living tissues require oxygen:",
    "feedback": "Hypoxia is the lack of sufficient oxygen to meet the needs of the body tissues which require oxygen for oxidation of carbohydrates from food to produce energy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is one function of communication in a well co-ordinated team?",
    "feedback": "All members of the crew can participate in the decision making process"
  },
  {
    "question": "The physiological effects of accelerations to the human body depend on:\n1. the duration of the G-forces  \n2. the onset rate of the G-forces\n3. the magnitude of the G-forces  \n4. the direction of the G-forces.",
    "feedback": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the initial phase of flight training the relationship between confidence and expertise can be described as:",
    "feedback": "the pilot is competent enough to fly the aircraft at this stage, but does neither have a great deal of confidence in his/her abilities nor in the whole system"
  },
  {
    "question": "As a pilot's workload is increased, what happens to his performance level?",
    "feedback": "The standard of performance increases until an optimum level of workload and performance is achieved"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypoglycaemia can be caused by:",
    "feedback": "Not eating regularly and fasting"
  },
  {
    "question": "Between which components, with reference to the SHELL Concept, covers pilot misinterpretation of the old three-point altimeter?",
    "feedback": "Liveware - Hardware"
  },
  {
    "question": "The rate of accidents in commercial aviation (excluding sabotage and acts of terrorism) :",
    "feedback": "is approximatively 1 accident per million airport movements"
  },
  {
    "question": "Physiological stressors include:",
    "feedback": "Noise, temperature (low or high), humidity, sleep deprivation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Long-term memory is an essential component of the pilot's knowledge and expertise.",
    "feedback": "It is desirable to pre-activate knowledge stored in long-term memory to have it available when required"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following factors are typical examples of the effects on the flight crew of short-term, acute fatigue?\n1) Tiredness and falling asleep for short periods without being aware that this happens2) Constant feeling of lethargy and lack of energy3) Reduced concentration and vigilance4) Increased error rate and slowed reaction times5) Increased mental and physiological health issues6) Increased irritability",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 4, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Susceptibility to carbon monoxide poisoning, as from smoking tobacco, increases as:",
    "feedback": "altitude increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "In periods of high workload, the use of \"professional language\" can ......",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "In periods of high workload, the use of \"professional language\" can ......",
    "feedback": "reduce the effects of stress on the crew"
  },
  {
    "question": "A fatigued pilot",
    "feedback": "will show signs of increased irritability"
  },
  {
    "question": "The thin walls of capillaries are permeable for :",
    "feedback": "gases"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the substances present in the smoke of cigarettes can make it significantly more difficult for the red blood cells to transport oxygen and as a consequence contributes to hypoxia. Which substance are we referring to?",
    "feedback": "Carbon monoxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main advantages that the human possesses over those of a machine in the decision making process?",
    "feedback": "Creativity, innovation and adaptability"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the absence of external reference points, the sensation that the vehicle in which you are sitting is moving when it is in fact the vehicle directly alongside which is moving is called :",
    "feedback": "illusion of relative movement"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hyperventilation can cause unconsciousness, because:",
    "feedback": "blood circulation to the brain is slowed down"
  },
  {
    "question": "A shining light is fading out (i. e. when flying into fog, dust or haze). What kind of sensation could the pilot get?",
    "feedback": "The source of light moves away from him"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main function of the red blood cells is",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main function of the red blood cells is",
    "feedback": "to transport oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "When faced with sustained cold temperature, how does the body resist this physical stress?",
    "feedback": "By intense vasoconstriction"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the context of the Threat and Error Management (TEM) model, what is the correct definition of \"undesired aircraft state\"?",
    "feedback": "It is an undesired flight situation associated with a reduction in margins of safety"
  },
  {
    "question": "A human breathing 100% oxygen at 33700 ft is the equivalent of breathing air at:",
    "feedback": "sea level"
  },
  {
    "question": "What can be said about the following statements?\n\n1. In case of conflicting information you can always trust your Seat- of-the-Pants-Sense.\n2. In case of conflicting information between the sensory organs and the instruments you must believe the instruments.",
    "feedback": "1 is false, 2 is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\n\n1. A person experiencing sleep loss is unlikely to be aware of personal performance degradation\n2. Performance loss may be present up to 20 minutes after awaking from a short sleep (nap)",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are both correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does not impair the function of the photosensitive cells?",
    "feedback": "Fast speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by presbycusis?",
    "feedback": "Gradual loss of hearing with age"
  },
  {
    "question": "The circulatory system, among other things, allows for :\n1. transportation of oxygen and carbon dioxide\n2. transportation of information by chemical substances",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Approaches at night without visual references on the ground and no landing aids (e.g. VASIS) can make the pilot believe of being",
    "feedback": "higher than actual altitude with the risk of landing short (\"ducking under\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "The decision making in emergency situations requires firstly:",
    "feedback": "distribution of tasks and crew coordination"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following would be a source of environmental stress in the flight crew compartment?",
    "feedback": "A flight in winter during which the cabin heater stops operating"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main advantages of the human over the machine?",
    "feedback": "Creativity, innovation and aptitude to deal with novel situations"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cognitive evaluation which leads to stress is based on:",
    "feedback": "the evaluation of the situation and the evaluation of capabilities to cope with it"
  },
  {
    "question": "You report for work as the Copilot of a two-person flight crew. Why could this crew be described as a group?",
    "feedback": "Because you and the Commander share similar professional characteristics and have the same flight safety goals"
  },
  {
    "question": "During hyperventilation:",
    "feedback": "acidity level of the blood is reduced"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the procedure to be followed when symptoms of decompression sickness occur?",
    "feedback": "Descend to the lowest possible level and land as soon as possible"
  },
  {
    "question": "Does noise (above 90 dbs) improve performance?",
    "feedback": "Never"
  },
  {
    "question": "If somebody starts breathing faster and deeper without physiological need",
    "feedback": "the blood turns more alkaline"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which part of the ear could be affected due to air pressure changes during climb and/or descent?",
    "feedback": "The eustachian tube and the tympanic membrane (ear drum)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technique should a pilot use to scan for traffic to the right and the left during straight and level flight?",
    "feedback": "Systematically focus on different segments of the sky for short intervals"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main problem caused by positive (+Gz) accelerations?",
    "feedback": "A pooling of blood in the lower portions of the body, and hence less blood available"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stress is a reaction to adapt a specific situation.\nThis reaction",
    "feedback": "may include various psychological and physiological elements which one can learn to manage"
  },
  {
    "question": "From the following list of stressors, which are psychological?\n\n1) noise\n2) loss of spouse or partner\n3) heat\n4) loss of job\n5) vibrations\n6) credit card debt",
    "feedback": "2, 4, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most dangerous sign of hypoxic hypoxia is",
    "feedback": "impaired judgment and self criticism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Decompression sickness symptoms may develop due to",
    "feedback": "cabin pressure loss when flying at higher altitudes (above 18000 FT)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Boyle's law is directly applicable in case of:",
    "feedback": "the expansion of trapped gasses in the human body with increasing altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sunglasses  with variable filtration (phototrope glasses)",
    "feedback": "can have disadvantages when used in the cockpit due to their dependence on ultraviolet light which is screened by the cockpit glass"
  },
  {
    "question": "The volume percentage of oxygen in the atmosphere  is  21% which",
    "feedback": "is constant for all altitudes conventional airplanes can reach"
  },
  {
    "question": "After performing the pre-flight checks, the aircraft approaches runway intersection B2, ATC clears the aircraft for an immediate take-off. However, the pilot replies \"unable\", since the departure checks are not yet completed.\nWhich kind of behaviour is shown in the scenario?",
    "feedback": "Self discipline"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term is used to describe an atmosphere in which crew members can confidently report safety concerns and are not afraid of blame?",
    "feedback": "Reporting culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct ?",
    "feedback": "70% of information processed by man enters via the visual channel"
  },
  {
    "question": "What strategy should be put in place when faced with an anticipated period of stress?",
    "feedback": "A strategy of preparing decisions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which behaviour does most likely promote a constructive solution of interpersonal conflicts?",
    "feedback": "Active listening."
  },
  {
    "question": "The effect of experience and repetition on performance",
    "feedback": "can both be beneficial and negative"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following measures can reduce the chance of a black-out during positive G-manoeuvres?",
    "feedback": "A tilt back seat."
  },
  {
    "question": "Stress may be defined as:",
    "feedback": "a normal phenomenon which enables an individual to adapt to encountered situations"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a normal blood pressure?",
    "feedback": "Diastolic 80 mm Hg\t\tSystolic 120 mm Hg"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are typical examples of the effects of long-term fatigue in flight crew?\n1) General reduction in performance2) Tiredness and falling asleep for short periods without being aware that this happens3) Inability to sleep4) Increase in physiological and mental health problems5) Reduction in visual acuity",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to completely  resynchronise with local time after zone crossing, circadian rhythms require",
    "feedback": "less time when flying from east to west"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "About 89 % of the nuclei are hydrogen (protons), 10 % helium and about 1 % heavier elements. The common heavier elements (such as carbon, oxygen, magnesium, silicon and iron) are present in about the same relative abundances as in the solar system."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct ?\n-1: Modern aircraft allow for 50 - 60% relative humidity in the cabin air under any conditions of flight, which is satisfactory for the body\n-2: Thirst is a belated symptom of dehydration\n-3: Dehydration may lead to clinical manifestations such as dizziness and fatigue\n-4: Drinking excessive quantities of water must be avoided since resistance to periods of low hydration will otherwise be lost",
    "feedback": "2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct statement from below:",
    "feedback": "stressors at home can add to the effects of the stressors in the cockpit"
  },
  {
    "question": "Analysis of accidents involving the human factor in aviation shows that :",
    "feedback": "there is hardly ever a single cause responsible"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cornea and the crystalline lens of the eye:",
    "feedback": "cause the convergence of light rays onto the retina"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stages of performance decrements due to hypoxic hypoxia are",
    "feedback": "indifferent stage up to 6'000 ft, disturbance threshold at 12'000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cockpit is being prepared during the start-up phase. The copilot performs the different checkpoints according to the checklist, acting with high vigilance. A student pilot is on the observer seat watching both pilots, understanding their actions. The commander completes a final check quickly, and with ease. In terms of learning a skill, what phases are demonstrated by the commander, copilot and student pilot in this scenario?",
    "feedback": "Commander autonomous, copilot associative, student pilot cognitive"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aerodrome is located near to the southern edge of a large town. Directly to the north of the town, there is a high mountain. The approach to the aerodrome is straight-in, from the south, over a large unpopulated desert. What hazard should the pilots be aware of when approaching the aerodrome?",
    "feedback": "In night VFR, the visual illusion of being too high due to the runway lights appearing to be in a lower position than expected on the windscreen, and the risk of descending too early and landing short."
  },
  {
    "question": "Civil aviation is generally recognized for being:",
    "feedback": "an open culture activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot, accelerating or decelerating in level flight may experience:",
    "feedback": "the illusion of climbing or descending"
  },
  {
    "question": "What would be the priority aim in the design of man-machine interfaces and in the creation of their application procedures for combatting problems associated with human error ?",
    "feedback": "To reduce the risks of the appearance or non-detection of errors entailing serious consequences"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which measure(s) will help to compensate for hypoxia?\n1. Descend below 10 000 FT.\n2. Breathe 100 % oxygen.\n3. Climb to or above 10 000 FT.\n4. Reduce physical activities.",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is true about the usage of social language (as opposed to professional language) in a high workload situation? Assume the crew speak the same native language.\nSocial language.....",
    "feedback": "can be imprecise, leading to false assumptions"
  },
  {
    "question": "When using the Body Mass Index (BMI) formula, when is a pilot considered to be obese?",
    "feedback": "Over 30 for males, over 29 for females"
  },
  {
    "question": "The response to unfavourable environmental conditions, and how the body reacts to demands placed upon it is ......",
    "feedback": "Stress"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a layover in a tropical country, a pilot visits a local market. In the dense crowd of people, a woman next to her suddenly starts coughing and she feels some droplets hit her face. She then takes a picture with a small monkey sitting on her shoulder to send it to her partner. While feeding it a peanut, the animal bites her finger. On the way back to the hotel, she buys some grapes and starts eating them. When showering, she sees at least 10 mosquito bites on her uncovered arms and legs. Soon, she develops nausea, and a few hours later, she suffers from vomiting and watery diarrhoea. From the massive loss of water, she feels dizzy and confused. Later, the physician diagnoses her with cholera.",
    "feedback": "The grapes have been washed in water contaminated with faeces"
  },
  {
    "question": "A slight lack of coordination which can make it difficult to carry out delicate and precise movements occurs when the level of alcohol in the blood is exceeding",
    "feedback": "0.05 % blood alcohol"
  },
  {
    "question": "The ossicles (the malleus, incus and stapes) are:",
    "feedback": "located in the middle ear"
  },
  {
    "question": "What level of received noise can cause noise induced hearing loss (NIHL)?",
    "feedback": "A one-time exposure to impulse noise above 120 dB and/or continuous exposure to noise above 85 dB"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which force(s) affect(s) the otoliths in the utriculus and sacculus?",
    "feedback": "Gravity and linear acceleration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following responses lists most of the common hazardous thought patterns (attitudes) for pilots to develop?",
    "feedback": "Anti-authority, impulsiveness, invulnerabilty, resignation, machismo complex"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a skill?",
    "feedback": "The capacity to accomplish successfully something requiring special knowledge or ability"
  },
  {
    "question": "What methods can be used to combat human error?\n1) Reducing error-prone mechanisms\n2) Improving the way in which error is taken into account in training\n3) Sanctions against the initiators of error\n4) Improving error detection techniques\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Short term memory retains a lager amount of information, with:",
    "feedback": "A process called \"chunking\""
  },
  {
    "question": "The kinesthetic sense does not orient an individual to his surroundings, but informs him of",
    "feedback": "the relative motion and relative position of his body parts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which part of the vestibular apparatus is responsible for the impression of angular acceleration?",
    "feedback": "The semicircular canals"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most dangerous characteristic of perception is, that it",
    "feedback": "is extremely resistant to correction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pain in the Joints (\"bends\"), is a symptom of:",
    "feedback": "decompression sickness"
  },
  {
    "question": "What could the crew do in order to avoid air-sickness with passengers?\n1. Avoid turbulences.\n2. Avoid flying through rough weather.\n3. Seat passenger close to the center of gravity.\n4. Give pertinent information.",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In January 1989, a Boeing 737-400, which had just recently been delivered to the airline, was operated by two pilots who had only been flying the previous version before. The aircraft suffered a structural failure of a turbine blade of its No. 1 engine, causing vibrations, followed by a smell of smoke in the cockpit. Due to their experience with the previous version of the aircraft, the crew figured that the malfunctioning engine had to be No. 2, as this had been the engine supplying cabin bleed air on their previous type. Consequently, No. 2 engine was shut down and thrust on No. 1 was increased. As this action stopped the vibrations, both pilots were convinced that they had acted correctly and planned their diversion to East Midlands Airport.\nMeanwhile, the damage to engine No. 1 in combination with the high demands placed upon it caused a fire, which was noticed by the cabin crew and several passengers. The pilots, however, failed to detect the corresponding indications. On final approach, the thrust produced by engine No. 1 suddenly decreased to a level which was insufficient to carry the aircraft, which was fully configured for landing, over the bank of a road less than 900 metres in front of the runway.\nSelect the threat to aeronautical decision making which did not play a role in the accident:",
    "feedback": "Groupthink"
  },
  {
    "question": "The best method to avoid confirmation bias is to:",
    "feedback": "search for information that will falsify the hypothesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A healthy young subject should have the following lung volumes",
    "feedback": "a residual volume of 1.2 liter"
  },
  {
    "question": "The autocratic leadership style is synonymous with:",
    "feedback": "an authoritarian style"
  },
  {
    "question": "There are several sources for radiation. What is the maximum allowable dose per year for a pilot which is in contact with galactic radiation?",
    "feedback": "5 milli-Sieverts"
  },
  {
    "question": "The blood in the pulmonary artery is:",
    "feedback": "lacking in oxygen and rich in carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average Time of Useful Consciousness after a rapid decompression at 40,000 ft ?",
    "feedback": "About 12 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens in problem-solving when the application of a rule allows for the situation to be resolved ?",
    "feedback": "Actions return to an automatic mode"
  },
  {
    "question": "What impression do you have when outside references are fading away (e.g. fog, darkness, snow and vapor)?",
    "feedback": "It is difficult to determine the size and speed of objects"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sound waves are transferred from the outer ear to the inner ear by:",
    "feedback": "the ossicles"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ozone in the air of a pressurised cabin can be eliminated by:",
    "feedback": "ozone converters"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO, which statement is correct with regard to the fatigue risk management system (FRMS)?",
    "feedback": "FRMS is a data-driven means of continuously monitoring and managing fatigue-related safety risks and can be different for every employer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vibrations can cause blurred vision. \nThis is due to tuned resonance oscillations of the:",
    "feedback": "eyeballs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Blood pressure is normally measured in:",
    "feedback": "mmHg"
  },
  {
    "question": "Up to what altitude is blood oxygen saturation reduction unlikely to affect a pilot's judgement?",
    "feedback": "10000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is learning?",
    "feedback": "Gaining knowledge through study and past experience"
  },
  {
    "question": "Visual acuity is best within ….. degrees of the fovea and reduces ….. towards the periphery of vision:",
    "feedback": "2-3, rapidly"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot approaching an upsloping runway:",
    "feedback": "may feel that he is higher than actual. This illusion may cause him to land short."
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot may suffer from hypoxia:",
    "feedback": "after decompression at high altitude and not taking additional oxygen in time"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following can be observed when the internal body temperature falls below 32°C :",
    "feedback": "mental disorders, and even coma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following symptoms can mark the onset of hyperventilation?",
    "feedback": "Dizzy feeling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Constantly processing information from one source at a time by careful allocation of one's available mental resources is described as....",
    "feedback": "selective attention"
  },
  {
    "question": "Synergy is a commonly used term. What does it mean?",
    "feedback": "The output from the group is better than the sum of the output from each individual in the group"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is generally considered that the most serious non-professional stressor is:",
    "feedback": "death of a spouse or partner"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Rasmussen's model, errors in rule-based control mode are of the following type(s) :",
    "feedback": "errors of technical knowledge"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is most likely to be overlooked should a pilot make a rushed decision?",
    "feedback": "Analysis of the actual situation and applying a prepared decision instead"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the statements below relate to an external error within the cockpit that was caused by a social error?",
    "feedback": "Commander struggles to understand the Copilot due to a strong accent"
  },
  {
    "question": "Excessive intake of aspirin can cause:",
    "feedback": "Gastric bleeding"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which phenomenon is common to hypoxia and hyperventilation?",
    "feedback": "Tingling sensations in arms or legs."
  },
  {
    "question": "The phases of General Adaptation Syndrome are:",
    "feedback": "alarm, resistance, exhaustion."
  },
  {
    "question": "If coping with a stress situation is impossible, one will remain in the state of:",
    "feedback": "distress"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where on the arousal/performance graph is a pilot best placed to cope with a difficult task without performance degrading?",
    "feedback": "Below the \"breakpoint\""
  },
  {
    "question": "The semicircular canals of the inner ear monitor",
    "feedback": "angular accelerations"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot, trying to pick up a fallen object from the cockpit floor during a tight turn, experiences:",
    "feedback": "coriolis illusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following three conditions will decrease the G-tolerance:",
    "feedback": "obesity, alcohol, sleep deprivation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"gestalt laws \"formulates :",
    "feedback": "basic principles governing how objects are mentally organized and perceived"
  },
  {
    "question": "Differences of opinion should be regarded as:",
    "feedback": "helpful"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the most frequent and the least appropriate reactions on the part of a co-pilot when faced with a highly authoritarian captain ?\n1. Self-assertion\n2. A scapegoat feeling\n3. Delayed reactions to observed discrepancies\n4. Disengagement",
    "feedback": "2,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "One issue with operating propeller-driven or rotor-driven aircraft in bright sunlight is the flicker effect of the light passing through the rotating blades.\nWhat is the most significant problem associated with the flicker effect?",
    "feedback": "At certain flicker frequencies, it can cause nausea or other physical discomfort and possibly epileptic fits"
  },
  {
    "question": "An airline captain is extremely focused on getting things done, but shows very little interest in making the crew work as a\nteam. Where is this captain likely to be on the Blake and Mouton diagram?",
    "feedback": "High on task orientation, low on relationship orientation, a \"Rambo\" type"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about autoflight systems are correct or incorrect?\n1) Autoflight systems are designed to assist and reduce the workload of the pilot and possess the creativity to deal with unforeseen situations2) An autoflight system is, at its core, a computer, operated by logic, and is not capable of performing with the same personal motivation as a pilot, with regard to safety",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can a pilot prevent the effects of the black hole illusion when flying VFR at night?",
    "feedback": "Avoid making a straight and long approach"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to provide optimum human performance it is advisable to",
    "feedback": "establish strategies for planning, automating and managing resources (in real time)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following routes will cause the worst Jet lag?",
    "feedback": "Flight from Oslo to Tokyo"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a decompression at 43 000 FT the TUC (Time of Useful Consciousness) will be approximately:",
    "feedback": "5-15 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "A highly automated aircraft is being flown. The flight crew do not communicate effectively with each other. What effect can this have?",
    "feedback": "Loss of awareness of the flight mode"
  },
  {
    "question": "A stereotype and involuntary reaction of the organism on stimulation of receptors is called:",
    "feedback": "reflex"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Captain running a \"laissez-faire\" cockpit will:",
    "feedback": "make few suggestions or decisions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the Threat and Error Management (TEM) model, which of the following situations is considered an error?",
    "feedback": "Inadequate control inputs resulting in a hard landing and the collapse of the landing gear"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the main positive capabilities in an individual's decision making process is:",
    "feedback": "Creativity"
  },
  {
    "question": "The individual's perception of stress depends on:",
    "feedback": "the subjective evaluation of the situation and one's abilities to cope with it"
  },
  {
    "question": "'Environmental capture' is a term used to describe which of the following statements?\n\n1.The tendency for a skill to be executed in an environment in which it is frequently exercised, even if it is inappropriate to do so\n2.The tendency for a skill acquired in one aircraft type to be executed in a new aircraft type, even if it is inappropriate to do so\n3. The tendency for people to behave in different ways in different social situations\n4. The gaining of environmental skills",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An executive aircraft is performing an approach to aerodrome A. However, due to bad weather, the pilot needs to divert to aerodrome B. A passenger, who is a part of the senior management of the company, insists on landing at aerodrome A. The pilot is conditioned to obey authority and continue the approach to aerodrome A. This is an example of......",
    "feedback": "National culture overriding the safety culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a healthy human being low saturated blood is found in the:",
    "feedback": "Pulmonary artery"
  },
  {
    "question": "Concerning the relation between performance and stress, which of the following statement(s) is (are) correct?",
    "feedback": "A moderate level of stress may improve performance."
  },
  {
    "question": "If someone hyperventilates due to stress his blood will get:",
    "feedback": "more alkaline"
  },
  {
    "question": "An airline captain in Safe Airlines Inc scores very high both on task orientation and on relationship orientation (ref. Blake and Mouton model). Which of the following will probably best describe his communication in cockpit?",
    "feedback": "The captain discusses the situation with his copilot, makes a decision based upon this discussion. The copilot is asked to evaluate the decision"
  },
  {
    "question": "Metacommunication is defined as",
    "feedback": "communicating about the communication"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following drawbacks are associated with automation?\n\n1. Reduced competence in manually controlling the aircraft\n2. Increased likelihood of slips while programming automatic systems   \n3. Difficulties in adapting to the use of a sidestick\n4. General decrease in technical reliability",
    "feedback": "1,2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a possible cause for a coronary disease which in turn might lead to angina pectoris and myocardial infarction?",
    "feedback": "A partial or complete blockage of coronary arteries"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the characteristics of the alarm phase of the stress reactions?\n-1 :  increased arousal level as a result of adrenaline secretion.\n-2 : an increase in heart rate, respiration and release of glucose.\n-3 : a decrease in stress resistance.\n-4 : activation of the digestive system.\n-5 : secretion of cortisol to mobilize attention.\n\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1,2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "A person can be expected to carry out the following pairs of tasks simultaneously:",
    "feedback": "fly straight and level and talk to ATC"
  },
  {
    "question": "What action should you take prior to boarding if you suspect a fellow flight crew member of being an alcoholic?",
    "feedback": "Ensure he/she is aware of the need to seek medical attention, and that misuse of alcohol makes a pilot unfit to fly until he/she is considered recovered by a medical professional"
  },
  {
    "question": "When might a pilot have the sensation of a nose-low attitude?",
    "feedback": "When decelerating in straight, horizontal flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1. The first information received determines how subsequent information will be evaluated\n2. If one has made up one's mind, contradictory information may not get the attention it really needs\n3. With increasing stress, channelizing attention is limiting the flow of information to the central decision maker (CNS)",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 3 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following applies to carbon monoxide poisoning?",
    "feedback": "Several days are needed to recuperate from a carbon monoxide poisoning."
  },
  {
    "question": "Night vision is significantly reduced (i.e. a loss of more than 25%) at 15000 ft in which stage of hypoxia?",
    "feedback": "Compensatory"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following answers is correct?",
    "feedback": "Behaviour is the outward result of personality and attitude and is adaptable"
  },
  {
    "question": "A barotrauma of the middle ear (aerotitis)",
    "feedback": "is more likely when the pilot is flying with a respiratory infection and during descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the case of changes to circadian rhythms, the readjustment to a new time zone:",
    "feedback": "is most rapid when flying westbound"
  },
  {
    "question": "Expired air contains",
    "feedback": "15% oxygen and 4% carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "Please mark the counter-measure a pilot can use against a barotrauma of the middle ear (aerotitis).",
    "feedback": "Stop descending, climb again and then descend with reduced sink rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are carrying out a visual approach to a runway which slopes upwards away from the touchdown end. \nWhat is the main risk in this case?",
    "feedback": "Landing short due to over-correcting for an apparent height increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Seat-of-the-Pants Sense is including receptors in the",
    "feedback": "muscles, tendons and joints sensitive to the position and movement of body parts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alcohol, even when taken in minor quantities",
    "feedback": "can make the brain cells to be more susceptible to hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of a fire, which of the following aircraft component parts or liquids give off toxic fumes when burnt?\n1) Fire estinguishers made of steel2) Anti-icing fluids3) Hydraulic fluids4) Furnishings and trimming materials",
    "feedback": "3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the various factors which guide attention ?\n1. The level of automation of behaviour\n2. Response time\n3. The salience of the information\n4. Expectations",
    "feedback": "1,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which gas most readily combines with haemoglobin?",
    "feedback": "carbon monoxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which factors can lead to a deterioration in vision?\n\n1) Hypoxia\n2) Smoking\n3) Poor diet, lacking Vitamin A\n4) Exposure to bright lights\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning personality is correct?",
    "feedback": "Heredity, upbringing, childhood, and life experiences all influence personality"
  },
  {
    "question": "The physiological rhythms of a pilot in a new time zone will resynchronise to this new time zone at a rate of about",
    "feedback": "1 - 1.5 hours a day"
  },
  {
    "question": "The low level of humidity found in a pressurised aircraft cabin:",
    "feedback": "should be compensated for by drinking water before one gets thirsty"
  },
  {
    "question": "1. Adaptation is a new state of equilibrium after having coped with a stressful situation. \n2. An individual's prospect of the situation and his/her abilities to cope with it will determine the type and strength of stress.",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are both correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is an example of a countermeasure that flight crew use to manage threats, errors, and undesired aircraft states?",
    "feedback": "Standard Operating Procedures (SOP)"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Rasmussen's model, errors are of the following types in skill-based behaviour:",
    "feedback": "Routine errors"
  },
  {
    "question": "A study by NASA has examined the relationships between incidents linked with ground-to-crew communication. Which of the following factors is the main reason for disturbances in the correct reception of a message?",
    "feedback": "Listening errors."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a typical \"error of commission\"?",
    "feedback": "Taxiing out to a wrong runway"
  },
  {
    "question": "Noise Induced Hearing Loss (NIHL) is:",
    "feedback": "governed by intensity and duration of noise in excess of 90 dB"
  },
  {
    "question": "Our mental model of the world is based",
    "feedback": "on both our past experiences and the sensory information we receive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vitamin A and possibly vitamins B and C are chemical factors and essential to good night vision:\n\n1. Vitamin deficiencies may decrease night vision performance\n2. An excess intake of vitamin A will improve night vision performance significantly\n3. Pilots should be carefully concerned to take a balanced diet containing sufficient vitamin A\n4. Vitamin deficiencies may decrease visual acuity in photopic vision but not in scotopic vision",
    "feedback": "1 and 3 are correct, 2 and 4 are false"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about role patterns in group situations?",
    "feedback": "Roles are partly defined by the expectations associated with a position"
  },
  {
    "question": "Depth perception when objects are close (< 1 m) is achieved through",
    "feedback": "seeing with two eyes (binocular vision)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The heart muscle is supplied with blood from:",
    "feedback": "the coronary arteries"
  },
  {
    "question": "On experiencing a vestibular illusion in straight and level flight, it is recommended that:",
    "feedback": "you avoid head movements and rely on your instruments"
  },
  {
    "question": "Altitude-hypoxia, when breathing ambient air, should not occur (indifferent phase)",
    "feedback": "below 3 000 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following list are symptoms of fatigue?\n\n1) Tiredness\n2) Faster reactions\n3) Diminished motor skills\n4) Tunneled concentration\n5) Increased long term memory capacity",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the commonest problem of the long term memory and how would you counteract it?",
    "feedback": "Unless an item is recalled regularly, it becomes more and more difficult to retrieve from the LTM store"
  },
  {
    "question": "Air-ground communication involves the transmission of information and meaning between pilots and air traffic controllers by means of verbal and non-verbal messages. Within this context, an aspect of non-verbal communication is.....",
    "feedback": "paralanguage, that is, a person's accent or volume of speech"
  },
  {
    "question": "The team spirit of a cockpit-crew most likely depends on both pilots:",
    "feedback": "respecting each other and striving for the same goals"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 1972, a psychologist named Edwards presented a concept of the interface between flight crew and other parts of the airspace environment. What is this concept called and the names of those elements involved?",
    "feedback": "The SHEL Concept: software, hardware, environment and liveware."
  },
  {
    "question": "The blood-pressure depends on:  \n1. the work of the heart \n2. the peripheral resistance  \n3. the elasticity of the arterial walls  \n4. the blood volume and viscosity",
    "feedback": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "When turning in IMC , head movements should be avoided as much as possible. This is a prevention against:",
    "feedback": "coriolis illusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot can be described as being proficient, when he/she:",
    "feedback": "has automated a large part of the necessary flight deck routine operations in order to free his/her cognitive resources"
  },
  {
    "question": "The common illusion created by linear acceleration or deceleration is:",
    "feedback": "a pitch up feeling when the aircraft accelerates"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the cruise, at night, when the workload is low, it is recommended that:",
    "feedback": "the lighting in the cockpit be increased in order to prevent low vigilance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Informal roles within a crew",
    "feedback": "evolve as a result of the interactions that take place among crew members"
  },
  {
    "question": "Coaction is a mode of coordination which recommends:",
    "feedback": "working  parallel to achieve one common  objective"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to TEM, which undesired aircraft state could lead to runway excursion after touchdown?",
    "feedback": "Stabilised approach turning unstabilised"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following illusions are brought about by conflicts between the visual system and the vestibular system?\n\n-1: Illusions concerning the attitude of the aircraft\n-2: Autokinetic illusion (fixed point viewed as moving)\n-3: Illusions when estimating the size and distance of objects\n-4: Illusions of rotation",
    "feedback": "1,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Non-verbal communication:",
    "feedback": "can serve as a substitute for oral speech"
  },
  {
    "question": "With hyperventilation, caused by high levels of arousal or overstress:",
    "feedback": "an increased amount of carbon dioxide is exhaled causing muscular spasms and  even unconsciousness"
  },
  {
    "question": "The human information processing system is highly efficient compared to computers because of its",
    "feedback": "flexibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Commander believes that the Copilot has made a radio call, but it will not be made for another 5 minutes due to poor prioritisation. The Commander does not ask for the Copilot to confirm that he/she made the radio call.\nWhich option best describes the Commander^s situation?",
    "feedback": "A false mental model"
  },
  {
    "question": "An important aspect of Situational Awareness is:",
    "feedback": "when a pilot's perception equals reality"
  },
  {
    "question": "The function of the Eustachian tube is to equalise the pressure between the:",
    "feedback": "middle ear and the external atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "Strict adherence to Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs) and normal checklists:",
    "feedback": "Is an effective method to prevent or mitigate crew errors, anticipate or manage operational threats, and therefore to enhance ground and flight operations safely"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can you determine if a person is suffering from a  barotrauma of the sinuses of the nose (aerosinusitis) or the middle ear (aerotitis) ?",
    "feedback": "Hearing difficulties will normally accompany aerotitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The body obtains its energy from:",
    "feedback": "carbohydrates, protein and fats"
  },
  {
    "question": "Back problems are common amongst pilots. Effective ways of preventing back pain are:\n1) Physiotherapy\n2) Loosing weight if person is overweight\n3) Good physical condition\n4) Hypnosis\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct concerning flight in an environment of low contrast (fog, snow, darkness, haze)?",
    "feedback": "It is difficult to estimate the correct speed and size of approaching objects"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is on an approach to an alernate aerodrome with marginal vertical visibility that the pilot has not flown to before. The pilot experiences positive stress. Which statement is correct for this situation?",
    "feedback": "The perceived demand is equal to or less than the perceived ability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about type 2 diabetes mellitus is correct?",
    "feedback": "It is usually diagnosed in adulthood, and a typical symptom is unexplained weight loss"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Commander of a twin engined aircraft is 40 years old and has logged 5800 total flight hours (1500 on type). The 55 year old Copilot, who used to be a Senior Commander, recently joined the Operator and has logged 11200 total flight hours (also with 1500 on type). The Copilot is Pilot Flying on approach. Below the Minimum Descent Altitude the crew still have no sufficient visual contact with the runway. The Ground Proximity Warning System then sounds \"too low - terrain\". The Copilot says \"we're going to make it\" and continues the approach, instead of starting the mandatory go-around procedure. The Commander does not challenge the decision of the Copilot and does not take control of the aircraft. The result is a crash, caused by a Controlled Flight into Terrain.\nWhich of the following options best explains the poor Crew Resource Management that is illustrated in this scenario?",
    "feedback": "Status and role are mixed: The less experienced Commander fails to assert his/her authority over the more experienced Copilot"
  },
  {
    "question": "Safety is often improved by applying the principles of CRM, e.g.:",
    "feedback": "expression of one's doubts or different opinion for as long as this doubt can not be rejected on the base of evidence"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can a pilot prevent spatial disorientation in flight?",
    "feedback": "Establish and maintain a good instrument cross check."
  },
  {
    "question": "The respiratory control center is primarily sensitive to",
    "feedback": "carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "Signs or symptoms of hyperventilation are",
    "feedback": "all above mentioned signs or symptoms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Less experienced pilots differ from experienced pilots in the following way :",
    "feedback": "inexperienced pilots refer to information more than experts when carrying out the same task"
  },
  {
    "question": "What action should a pilot take when he is suffering from a common cold, has no fever, but his nose is running and he is unable to clear his ears?",
    "feedback": "He should not fly, because there is a risk of not succeeding to equalize the pressure between middle ear and ambient air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Carbon monoxide in the human body can lead to: \n1. loss of muscular power\n2. headache  \n3. impaired judgement \n4. pain in the joints \n5. loss of consciousness",
    "feedback": "1, 2 , 3 and 5 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the remedy for decompression sickness, or \"bends\"?",
    "feedback": "increase the pressure on the body"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the major protective measures against illusions is:",
    "feedback": "Comprehensive briefing and de-briefing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypoxia is a situation in which the cells",
    "feedback": "have a shortage of oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "Drugs against allergies (antihistamines), when taken by an aviator can cause the following undesirable effects:\n1. Drowsiness, dizziness\n2. Dry mouth\n3. Headaches\n4. Impaired depth perception\n5. Nausea",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is yellow fever contracted?",
    "feedback": "A virus transmitted by infected mosquito"
  },
  {
    "question": "With too much cohesion, Groupthink can be:",
    "feedback": "negative"
  },
  {
    "question": "The eustachian tube is the passage way between the",
    "feedback": "nasopharynx and the middle ear"
  },
  {
    "question": "The confirmation bias of decision making is",
    "feedback": "a tendency to ignore that information which indicates that a  decision is poor;"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning working memory is correct?\nWorking memory is:",
    "feedback": "Sensitive to interruptions and limited in size"
  },
  {
    "question": "The long term memory is influenced by:",
    "feedback": "experience, repetition, suggestion, desires and expectations."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct as regards active errors?\nAn active error is.....",
    "feedback": "committed by the operator (e.g. pilot, air traffic controller) and has an immediate effect"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot should no fly immediately after donating blood because:",
    "feedback": "there is an increased susceptibility to fainting"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is one potential disadvantage of advanced aircraft automation with regards to crew communication?",
    "feedback": "Greater efforts are needed to ensure that communication will take place"
  },
  {
    "question": "The composition of the atmosphere at 50 000 ft is",
    "feedback": "78% nitrogen, 21% oxygen, ~1% argon, 0.03% carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dalton's law states",
    "feedback": "the partial pressure of a gas is proportional to its fractional concentration in a gas mixture"
  },
  {
    "question": "Perceptual conflicts between the vestibular and visual systems are :\n1 - classic and resistant when flying in IMC\n2 - sensed via impressions of rotation\n3 - sensed via distorted impressions of the attitude of the aircraft\n4 - considerable during prolonged shallow turns under IMC",
    "feedback": "1,2,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is automation complacency?",
    "feedback": "The circumstance where monitoring and cross-checking is reduced because of the belief in the infallibility of the automatic system"
  },
  {
    "question": "During training, a student pilot experiences some significant difficulties, including failing an examination and an important flight test. With the help of a supportive instructor, the pilot is able to successfully complete the pilot training.\nWhat effect are these events likely to have on the pilot's subsequent behaviour?",
    "feedback": "If the pilot has a stable personality and a positive attitude, he/she is likely to adopt the same adult approach as the instructor to overcome difficulties, and accept that others can sometimes make errors but still be competent pilots"
  },
  {
    "question": "Getting uneasy will affect:\n\n1. attention\n2. concentration \n3. memory \n4. prudence",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to overcome an overload of work during the flight, it is necessary to:\n\n-1 : know how to use one's own reserve of resources in order to ease the burden on the crew\n-2 : divide up tasks among the crew\n-3 : ensure that the long term memory is used as much as possible as short term memory will add to the stress\n-4 : drop certain tasks and stick to high-level priorities.\n\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The person with overall responsibility for the flight is the\n-1 Pilot in Command\n-2 Co-pilot\n-3 Navigator\n-4 Air traffic controller\n\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature lapse rate",
    "feedback": "within the troposphere is ~2°C per 1000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component of safety culture makes safety risk management more effective?",
    "feedback": "Informed culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "Spatial disorientation will be most likely to occur during flight:",
    "feedback": "if the brain receives conflicting informations and the pilot does not believe the instruments"
  },
  {
    "question": "Physiological problems due to increasing altitude are caused by :",
    "feedback": "decreased atmospherical pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "To avoid wrong decisions by the pilot, an aircraft system should at least be able to",
    "feedback": "report its malfunction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Otic Barotrauma is worse during the descent than climb because:",
    "feedback": "the air in the middle ear is at a lower pressure than the cabin, this closes the eustation tube so that the pressure cannot be equalised"
  },
  {
    "question": "The use of modern technology applied to glass-cockpit aircraft has:",
    "feedback": "facilitated feedback from the machine via more concise data for communication on the flight deck"
  },
  {
    "question": "The part of the eye that bends the light the most is:",
    "feedback": "the cornea"
  },
  {
    "question": "During flight, a pilot may get sensory illusion about the pitch and bank angle. This is caused by the misinterpretation of signals from the vestibular apparatus. Which of the following is an element of the vestibular apparatus?",
    "feedback": "The anterior semicircular canal"
  },
  {
    "question": "Circadian rhythms are governed by a biological \"internal clock\":",
    "feedback": "The internal clock adapts slowly, and beyond one's concious control, to changes in the daily schedule of sleeping, waking and eating"
  },
  {
    "question": "The proprioceptive senses (\"Seat of-the-Pants-Sense\")",
    "feedback": "give wrong information, when outside visual reference is lost"
  },
  {
    "question": "For what reason is it important to be familiar with the circadian rhythm of body temperature?",
    "feedback": "Peak performance occurs at the time of rising or high body temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering Rasmussen's model of information processing when making decisions based on weather information, the processing:",
    "feedback": "Involves the rule-based and knowledge-based levels"
  },
  {
    "question": "Having a serious cold it is better not to fly, due to the extra risk of:\n1. flatulence\n2. pain in the ear during descent\n3. pressure vertigo\n4. pain in the nasal sinuses",
    "feedback": "2,3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rising the sensory threshold of a sensory organ means:",
    "feedback": "a lesser sensitivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which element of human blood is responsible for oxygen transportation?",
    "feedback": "Red blood cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the alarm stage of response to stress what does the body do?",
    "feedback": "Recognises the stressor and prepares the body for action"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which phase of the GAS is cortisol released?",
    "feedback": "Resistance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Human behaviour is determined by:",
    "feedback": "biological characteristics, social environment and cultural influences"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot has taken an over the counter remedy for an upset stomach and is rostered to fly in 2 hours time. The pilot should consider the general rule that....",
    "feedback": "if pilots are so unwell that they require any medication, for any condition, then they should consider themselves unfit to fly"
  },
  {
    "question": "What physical symptoms can be attributed to stress?",
    "feedback": "Insomnia, loss of appetite and a dry mouth"
  },
  {
    "question": "Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs):",
    "feedback": "The correct answers are: Must be known thanks to operational skill training, Have their greatest benefit in small companies operating with many inexperienced pilots"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot meets the ground engineer in charge on the apron. Although the pilot has not been through flight preparation yet, he nevertheless instructs the engineer as to the amount of fuel to be loaded, since he is used to flying this route. This behaviour results from:",
    "feedback": "a decision bias due to habits (frequency basis)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Expanded abdominal air following rapid decompression at 30000 feet:",
    "feedback": "may be dangerous causing great pain"
  },
  {
    "question": "An increase in the amount of carbon dioxide in the blood leads to:",
    "feedback": "shortness of breath"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most dangerous symptoms of hypoxia at altitude are",
    "feedback": "euphoria and impairment of judgement"
  },
  {
    "question": "An identical situation can be experienced by one pilot as exciting in a positive sense and by another pilot as threatening. In both cases:",
    "feedback": "the arousal level of both pilots will be raised"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a steady climb above Flight Level 100 if cabin pressurisation fails:",
    "feedback": "the effects of hypoxia may be gradual and difficult to recognise"
  },
  {
    "question": "An experienced pilot:",
    "feedback": "prepares thoroughly for a flight and is able to anticipate the majority of possible problems"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1  Hypothermia affects physical and mental abilities.\n2  Man has effective natural protection against intense cold.\n3  Shivering makes it possible to combat the cold to a certain extent, but uses up a lot of energy\n4  Disorders associated with hypothermia appear at a body temperature of less than 35°C",
    "feedback": "1,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The needs of an individual lead to :",
    "feedback": "a change in the individuals motivation and consequently to an adaptation of the behaviour"
  },
  {
    "question": "How will the successful completion of a stressful task affect a pilot's performance when a similar situation is experienced in the future?",
    "feedback": "The amount of stress experienced will be less"
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew is performing a long-haul flight, wenn about 35 minutes into the cruise, with the autopilot engaged, they realise that they have failed to actively check the instruments in the last 10 minutes. They recognise the signs of hypovigilance.\nHypovigilance:",
    "feedback": "Is likely to occur during the cruise as effective monitoring has a high cognitive workload but is unrewarding, and can result in a passive attitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the definition of error tolerance in error management strategies?",
    "feedback": "Error tolerance means minimizing the effects of errors by making a system as tolerant as possible towards errors"
  },
  {
    "question": "The organism is mobilized by a process known as:",
    "feedback": "GAS : General Adaptation Syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "The flight is on the approach and experiencing bad weather, including thunderstorms with associated windshear and crosswinds. The Captain is Pilot Monitoring (PM) and the First Officer is Pilot Flying (PF). The FO says that he is unable to continue the approach and land due to exceeding the crosswind limit. The captain says \"we are close to the limit but it will not be exceeded, continue to land\".\nWhat does this demonstrate?",
    "feedback": "As a group the crew is willing to take more risk"
  },
  {
    "question": "When drugs against sleep disorders and/or nervosity have been taken and the pilot intends to fly, attention has to be payed to",
    "feedback": "the effect they have on reaction time and perceptional awareness"
  },
  {
    "question": "A person's attitudes define a set of learned dispositions (likes and dislikes) which:",
    "feedback": "influence a person's reaction and response to people, situations, etc."
  },
  {
    "question": "Compare the different forms of learning and choose the correct statement below:",
    "feedback": "Operant conditioning requires reinforcement"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the absence of external time cues, what is the approximate duration of a free-running circadian rhythm?",
    "feedback": "24 hours to 28 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dizziness and tumbling sensations, when making head movements in a tight turn, are symptoms of",
    "feedback": "\"Pilot`s vertigo\""
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct ?",
    "feedback": "Oxygen diffusion from the blood into the cells depends on their  partial oxygen pressure gradient."
  },
  {
    "question": "How can a pilot increase his tolerance to +Gz ?",
    "feedback": "Tightening of muscles, ducking the head and perform a kind of pressure breathing."
  },
  {
    "question": "The DECIDE model is based on :",
    "feedback": "a prescriptive generic model, taking into account the method which seems most likely to come up with  the solution"
  },
  {
    "question": "When is your body temperature at its lowest?",
    "feedback": "Early in the morning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following symptoms can indicate hypoxia?\n\n1. Blue lips and finger nails\n2. Euphoria\n3. Flatulence\n4. Unconsciousness",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 4 are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "In terms of decision-making, the intention to become integrated into the team, to be recognised as the leader or to avoid conflicts may lead to :",
    "feedback": "the attempt to agree on decisions made by other crew members"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can a person be infected by yellow fever?",
    "feedback": "From a contaminated mosquito"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the World Health Organisation (WHO) definition of alcoholism?",
    "feedback": "when the excessive use of alcohol repeatedly damages a person´s physical, mental or social life"
  },
  {
    "question": "To maintain sea level conditions at 25'000 ft, the percentage of oxygen breathing is",
    "feedback": "62 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "Among the factors that increase tolerance to long-duration g forces are?",
    "feedback": "Bending forward  or supine body position and tensing of the abdominal muscles"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is correct:\n\n1) Paradoxic (REM) sleep refreshes the brain, memory and body.\n2) Paradoxic (REM) sleep decreases during the night.",
    "feedback": "Neither"
  },
  {
    "question": "The percentage of oxygen in cabin air:",
    "feedback": "is the same as at sea level"
  },
  {
    "question": "When can the General Adaptation Syndrome activate?",
    "feedback": "Responding to an imaginary threat"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a night flight, you are about to fall asleep. What can help you to stay awake?\n1) Isometric excercises2) Have a meal3) Reduce the intensity of cockpit lighting4) Maintain active communication, human-machine interface",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning communication is valid?",
    "feedback": "Professional communication means: using a restricted and specific language, tailored to minimize misunderstandings."
  },
  {
    "question": "The behavioural mode that enhances the co-ordination of the flight crew is....",
    "feedback": "adult"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Eustachian tube connects:",
    "feedback": "the middle ear and the throat"
  },
  {
    "question": "Perceptional illusions are:",
    "feedback": "normal and can be prevented by trusting instrument read-out"
  },
  {
    "question": "The atmosphere contains the following gases:",
    "feedback": "78% nitrogen, 21%  oxygen, 0,03% carbon dioxide, rest: rare gases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The vestibular system is composed of\n-1: two ventricles\n-2 : a saccule\n-3 : an utricle\n-4 : three semicircular canals",
    "feedback": "2,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot experiences difficulties in the control of his aircraft and consequently omits to monitor the fuel level. This is caused by:",
    "feedback": "a lack of attention due to distraction"
  },
  {
    "question": "The respiratory process consists mainly of",
    "feedback": "the diffusion of oxygen through the respiratory membranes into the blood, transportation to the cells, diffusion into the cells and elimination of carbon dioxide from the body"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which behaviour is typically found in the resistance phase of the General Adaptation Syndrome (GAS)?",
    "feedback": "Fight or flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "The unique organisation of characteristics which determine the typical or standard behaviour of an individual is known as:",
    "feedback": "personality"
  },
  {
    "question": "Noise induced hearing loss is influenced by",
    "feedback": "the duration and intensity of a noise"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Rasmussen's model, errors are of the following type(s) in skill-based behaviour:",
    "feedback": "routine errors"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the procedure above 10.000 ft altitude when faced with explosive decompression?",
    "feedback": "Don an oxygen mask and descend to below 10,000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a normal and healthy person, personality traits are:",
    "feedback": "stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "The circulation of blood:\n\n1) transports oxygen to the body cells\n2) withdraws waste products from the cells\n3) conveys nutrients to the cells\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Experiencing stress depends on:",
    "feedback": "the individual interpretation of the situation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The phases of learning a motor programme are:",
    "feedback": "Cognitive, associative and automatic phases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Haemoglobin is:",
    "feedback": "in the red blood cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why must flight safety considerations consider the human error mechanism? \n\n-1 : It is analysis of an incident or accident which will make it possible to identify what error has been committed and by whom. It is the process whereby the perpetrator is made responsible which may lead to elimination of the error.\n-2 : If we have a better understanding of the cognitive error mechanism, it will be possible to adapt procedures, aircraft interfaces, etc. \n-3 : It is error management procedure which enables us to continuously adjust our actions. The better we understand the underlying  mechanism of an error, the better will be our means for detecting  and  adapting future errors.\n-4 : Since error is essentially human, once it has been identified by the use of  procedures, a person will be able to anticipate and deal with it automatically  in the future.\n\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "2 and 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "A copilot has passed an upgrading course to become a captain. Which psychological consequence is most likely?",
    "feedback": "His/her self-concept is going to change because of new roles and tasks which have to be incorporated."
  },
  {
    "question": "The three basic components of the Threat and Error Management (TEM) model are, from the perspective of flight crew, threats, errors and undesired aircraft states. With regard to errors, the TEM model ....",
    "feedback": "considers three categories of errors, namely aircraft handling, procedural and communications"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is correct?\n\n1) Stress is an inevitable part of human life and in small amounts is necessary to achieve optimum performance\n2) Each individual has a stress limit which, if exceeded, could result in inability to handle even a moderate workload\n3) Anxiety creates worry which may lead to stress\n4) Stress is often perceived by the brain as some form of threat which may cause adrenaline to be released into the blood stream\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The crew of a transport aircraft experience a landing gear issue meaning that they can not confirm that the landing gear is down and locked. In order to have time to prepare the aircraft for an emergency landing, a holding of 60 minutes is performed. Subsequently, on final approach, the aircraft runs out of fuel.\nWhich of the options best describes this event?",
    "feedback": "The crew have missed important yet basic tasks such as monitoring the fuel. This is a risk and should be taught in basic flight training"
  },
  {
    "question": "The workload may be said to:\n\n-1 : be acceptable if it requires more than 90 % of the crew resources\n-2 : be acceptable if it requires about 60 % of the crew resources.\n-3 : depend on the pilot's expertise.\n-4 : correspond to the amount of resources available\n\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The intensity of a sound is measured in",
    "feedback": "decibels"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effectiveness of the individual depends on:",
    "feedback": "the ability to balance the dictates of the individual's needs and the demands of reality"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is correct with regard to Glaucoma?",
    "feedback": "Is a condition detected by pressure testing the eye ball"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Time of Useful Consciousness may vary according to :\n1 : physical activity of the subjected crew\n2 : the experience of the pilot on the type of aircraft in question\n3 : the strength and time of decompression\n4 : the cabin temperature",
    "feedback": "1,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is characteristic for Rapid Eye Movement (REM) sleep?",
    "feedback": "The brain is highly active"
  },
  {
    "question": "What human function is most sensitive to lack of oxygen?",
    "feedback": "Night vision"
  },
  {
    "question": "We know that transverse accelerations (Gy)\n- 1 : are above all active in turns and pull-outs\n- 2 : are present during take-off and landing\n- 3 : are rare during routine flights\n- 4 : often lead to loss of consciousness",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "To prevent empty field myopia at higher altitudes:",
    "feedback": "it is recommended that a pilot uses short sharp scans, or periodically focuses on a distant object such as a wingtip or cloud edge"
  },
  {
    "question": "Prior to a night flight a pilot enters the cockpit, allowing the eyes to adapt to the dark. Which term is relevant to describe the change in the rods and the cones?",
    "feedback": "Sensitivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "CRM and MCC training are designed to improve:",
    "feedback": "the quality of crew performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying from Frankfurt to Moscow you will have a lay-over of 4 days. What time measure is relevant for your circadian rhythm on the 3. day?",
    "feedback": "LT (local time)."
  },
  {
    "question": "To avoid incapacity due to gastro-intestinal problems, it is recommended that a simple, easily digested meal before boarding the aircraft should be accompanied by:",
    "feedback": "non-carbonated water"
  },
  {
    "question": "Communication efficiency is most sensitive to:",
    "feedback": "workload and interruptions"
  },
  {
    "question": "The relationship which exists between crew error and flight safety :",
    "feedback": "is dependent on the social and technical system and also on the operational context created by the system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Disturbance of the biological clock appears after a:\n1. bad night's sleep \n2. day flight Amsterdam - New York \n3. day flight Amsterdam - Johannesburg\n4. night flight New York - Amsterdam",
    "feedback": "2 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of stress on performance ?\n-1 : It always reduces performance.\n-2 : Optimum performance is obtained with optimum arousal.\n-3 : Excessive stress weakens performance.\n-4 : Insufficient stress weakens performance.\n\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\n\n1. REM-sleep becomes shorter with any repeated sleep cycle during the night.\n2. REM-sleep is more important for the regeneration of mental functions than all the other sleep stages are.",
    "feedback": "1 is not correct 2 is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tolerance to decompression sickness is decreased by:\n1. SCUBA-Diving\n2. Obesity\n3. Age\n4. Body height",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 3 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Disorientation is more likely to occur when the pilot is: 1. flying in IMC 2. frequently changing between inside and outside references 3. flying from IMC into VMC 4. having a cold",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The total gas volume of the lung is the sum of:\n\n1) tidal volume\n2) inspiratory reserve volume\n3) expiratory reserve volume\n4) residual volume\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is one of the functions of communication within a well coordinated team?",
    "feedback": "All members of the crew can participate in the decision making process"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is the best definition of episodic memory?",
    "feedback": "It is the memory of events which are held in the long-term memory and can be influenced by suggestion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Perception is based upon:",
    "feedback": "information received as well as past experience and knowledge"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ergonomics are associated with:",
    "feedback": "the human/workplace interface"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the weather is foggy, on approach, a pilot may get a feeling of:",
    "feedback": "the airfield being further away than it actually is"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"Effective Performance Time\" or \"Time of Useful Consciousness\"  after a decompression at 35 000 ft is:",
    "feedback": "between 30 and 60 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "The optic system of the eye consists of",
    "feedback": "cornea, lens, vitreous humor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cataract is caused by:",
    "feedback": "a clouding of the lens"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is most correct regarding the Multi-Crew Co-operation (MCC) concept?",
    "feedback": "It includes many elements, such as good communication by all the crew members, effective and balanced leadership by the PIC leading to good teamwork, problem solving, decision making, and the acceptance of monitoring and cross-checking"
  },
  {
    "question": "In flight a Commander encourages a relaxed communication atmosphere, and his/her primary aim is to please the Copilot. During a weather-avoidance scenario in VMC the Copilot suggests an avoidance plan, the Commander remains passive, making no judgement and letting the Copilot make the decision.\nHow is this described trans-cockpit authority gradient and leadership style known as?",
    "feedback": "Laissez-faire cockpit"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option describes the symptoms that the aircrew and passengers are most likely to have during and shortly after a fume event on board an aircraft?",
    "feedback": "Irritation in the eyes, nose and air passages, and a possibility of gastrointestinal upset"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to illusions due to perceptive conflicts, it may be said that they:",
    "feedback": "are mainly due to a sensory conflict concerning perception of the vertical and the horizontal between the vestibular and the visual system"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are crossing the Alps in a non-pressurised aircraft at an altitude of 15.000 feet. You do not use the oxygen mask because you feel fine. This is unsafe, because:",
    "feedback": "your judgement could be impaired"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following factors may have an influence on medical disqualification?",
    "feedback": "High and low blood pressure as well as a poor condition of the  circulatory system."
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypoxia affects visual performance.\nA pilot may:",
    "feedback": "get blurred and/or tunnel vision"
  },
  {
    "question": "Starting a coordinated level turn can make the pilot believe to",
    "feedback": "climb"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is inadvisable to fly when suffering from a cold. The reason for this is:",
    "feedback": "the tissue around the nasal end of the Eustachian tube is likely to be swollen thus causing difficulty in equalising the pressure within the middle ear and the nasal/throat area. Pain and damage to the eardrum can result, particularly during fast descents"
  },
  {
    "question": "Action plans (SOP's) in a cockpit must :",
    "feedback": "be shared by the members of the crew and updated at each modification in order to maintain maximum synergy"
  },
  {
    "question": "The so-called \"Seat-of-the-Pants\" sense is",
    "feedback": "not suitable for spatial orientation when outside visual references are lost"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft operating with the FMS in LNAV VNAV mode is operating in a busy terminal area at the end of a flight. Bad weather in the area has resulted in ATC requiring the flight crew to make several changes to the aircraft's flight path.\nIn order to maintain the maximum awareness of their flight status, what is the best action for the pilots to take?",
    "feedback": "Re-programming of the FMS in den LNAV VNAV mode during periods of high workload can lead to errors and also cause a loss of situational awareness. Therefore, the pilots should downgrade to a lower, simpler level of automation such as ALT/HDG or even to manual flying"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is on final approach over uniformly rising terrain towards a flat runway. This creates the visual illusion of being too ....",
    "feedback": "high, which leads the pilot to increase the rate of descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "A typical example of an organisational threat according to the TEM model would be:",
    "feedback": "Heavy workload and minimum legal breaks for relaxation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why does a deficiency in vitamin A cause night-blindness?",
    "feedback": "Vitamin A is essential to the regeneration of visual purple"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the meaning of \"cohesion\" within a group?",
    "feedback": "Team spirit"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sensory input to the \"Seat-of-the-Pants\" sense is given by",
    "feedback": "subcutaneous pressure receptors and kinesthetic muscle activity sensors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Presbyopia causes a:",
    "feedback": "decrease of accommodation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What airplane equipment marked a substantial decrease in hull loss rates in the eighties?",
    "feedback": "GPWS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dalton's law explains the occurance of :",
    "feedback": "altitude hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stress management programmes usually involve:",
    "feedback": "the prevention and/or the removal of stress"
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in blood-pressure are measured by:",
    "feedback": "pressoreceptors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct combination which includes the different types of long-term memory:\n1) Episodic memory2) Cognitive memory3) Sensory store4) Semantic memory5) Procedural memory6) Working memory",
    "feedback": "1, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which combination of the following statements are true?\n1) Total gas volume of the lungs is not usable\n2) Total gas volume of the lungs is fully usable\n3) The average lung volume is 5-6 litres\n4) The process of gas exchange in the lungs is carried out by passive diffusion",
    "feedback": "1, 3 and 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Breathing 100% oxygen will lift the pilot's physiological safe altitude to approximately:",
    "feedback": "38 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The eustachian tube serves for the pressure equalization between",
    "feedback": "middle ear and external atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to communication in a cockpit, we can say that:",
    "feedback": "communication uses up resources, thus limiting the resources allocated to work in progress"
  },
  {
    "question": "At an altitude where the pressure is half of that at sea level a person will have to:",
    "feedback": "use supplementary oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a night flight at 10,000 feet you notice that your visual acuity has decreased. In this case you can increase your acuity by:",
    "feedback": "breathing supplementary oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "Autokinesis is",
    "feedback": "the apparent movement of a static single light when stared at for a relatively long period of time in the dark"
  },
  {
    "question": "Human errors are frequent and may take several forms :",
    "feedback": "an error can be described as the mismatch between the pilots intention and the result of his/her actions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider aviation as a safety culture. Responsibility for safety lies with the:",
    "feedback": "Individuals"
  },
  {
    "question": "How will hyperventilation cause the acid-base balance of the blood to be affected?",
    "feedback": "Hyperventilation causes too much CO2 to be removed from the blood causing the level of carbonic acid to fall"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following statement is true",
    "feedback": "increased carbon dioxide causes shortness of breath"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can one distinguish between cooperation and coaction?",
    "feedback": "Cooperation is joining forces for a common purpose. Coaction is when each person carries out their assigned part"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which part of the vestibular apparatus is affected by changes in gravity and linear acceleration?",
    "feedback": "The sacculus and utriculus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mark the physiological relevance of Dalton's Law:",
    "feedback": "Oxygen deficiency because of decreased oxygen partial pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is flying at 2500 ft. The \"SPEED\" mode is active for the autothrottle. The first radio altimeter starts to display a non-correct value (-8 ft). This behaviour of the radio altimeter will automatically cancel the SPEED mode of the autothrottle. The pilots noticed the malfunction of the first radio altimeter but did not notice the deactivation of the SPEED mode and, as the second radio altimeter was acting well, they continued on, using the second radar altimeter. When intercepting the ILS glide slope, both crew believed that the autothrottle was in in SPEED mode and therefore, they did not understand why the speed was not being actively managed by the aircraft. Which of the following terms describes the crew's lack of understanding in this situation?",
    "feedback": "Mode confusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Presbycusis causes initial loss of:",
    "feedback": "high tones"
  },
  {
    "question": "If runway slopes downwards, what is a pilot is likely to do:",
    "feedback": "land long"
  },
  {
    "question": "What can a pilot do to avoid \"Flicker vertigo\" when flying in the  clouds?",
    "feedback": "Switch strobe-lights off"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mental rehearsal is helpful to improve flying skills",
    "feedback": "at all levels of flying proficiency"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pilots are more easily inclined to take greater risks when:",
    "feedback": "they are part of a group of pilots and they feel that they are being observed and admired (e.g. air shows)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following statement about UV radiation is false:",
    "feedback": "UVB penetrates deeper into the skin than UVA and causes skin cancer"
  },
  {
    "question": "With respect to the \"Swiss Cheese Model\", an accident is likely to happen if:",
    "feedback": "the openings in the \"cheese slices\" momentarily align, thus creating an open trajectory for the accident opportunity."
  },
  {
    "question": "The Auxiliary Power Unit (APU) of an aircraft is inoperative. There are no ground-start facilities available at the aerodrome, but the APU is necessary to start the engines. Therefore, one engine is kept running while the aircraft is refuelled and ground serviced. The temperature is around 0°C and light snow is falling. De-icing treatment is permitted only with engines off. With all the engines shut down, the aircraft can only be re-started once the APU is repaired.\nTo depart from the aerodrome as planned, the Commander decides not to de-ice the aircraft. A few minutes after take-off, the aircraft develops ice accretion on the wings and, consequently, it stalls.\nWhich of the following statements most correctly explains the decision-making of the Commander?",
    "feedback": "The Commander fails to properly evaluate the options before take-off by underestimating the risk of ice formation during flight and/or ignoring the influence of ice contamination on aircraft performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "The average pulse of a healthy adult in rest is about:",
    "feedback": "60 to  80 beats/min"
  },
  {
    "question": "To facilitate and reduce the time taken to access information in long-term memory, it is helpful to:",
    "feedback": "mentally rehearse information before it is needed"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the blood vessels which carry blood away from the cells?",
    "feedback": "Veins"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is (are) typical deseases caused by contaminated water?",
    "feedback": "Typhoid, Dysentery, Cholera"
  },
  {
    "question": "The distribution of primary causes of accidents in the wordwide jet aircraft commercial fleet shows that human error is involved in:",
    "feedback": "about 70 % of cases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "Problems in the personal relationships between crew members are likely to hamper their communication process"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following list can cause fatigue?\n\n1) Sleep loss\n2) Jet lag\n3) Boredom\n4) Low levels of external stimulation",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the audible range of the human ear?",
    "feedback": "20 – 20 000 Hz"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term \"Irony of Automation\" is used to describe the paradox that automation can do those things which the pilot already knows how to do well much better than the pilot.\nAccording to this paradox, automation:",
    "feedback": "Eliminates some aspects required in flying that may be needed in an emergency and that a pilot would like to be competent in doing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following persons can be referred to as being complacent?",
    "feedback": "A car driver driving on green light, but he is not looking neither to the left nor to the right as he passes the light. It is quite safe to drive on green light."
  },
  {
    "question": "Expressed as a simple mathematical statement when considering a crew of two, good synergy is:",
    "feedback": "1 + 1 = > 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Positive g will cause the blood flow to the brain to:",
    "feedback": "decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are strategies for resolving conflict?\n\n1. Seeking arbitration\n2. Actively listening to other people\n3. Recognise the early signs of conflict and address them\n4. Becoming aware of cultural influences",
    "feedback": "1,2,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "During paradoxical sleep",
    "feedback": "rapid eye movements can be observed"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is haze effecting your perception?",
    "feedback": "Objects seem to be further away than in reality."
  },
  {
    "question": "Mode error is associated with:",
    "feedback": "automation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is one of the main purposes of a crew briefing?",
    "feedback": "To pre-activate information in the long-term memory that may be needed for the flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "Coriolis illusion, causing spatial disorientation is the result of:",
    "feedback": "simultaneous head movements during aircraft manoeuvres"
  },
  {
    "question": "The two types of fatigue are:",
    "feedback": "short-term and long-term"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pain in the joints caused by gas bubbles following a decompression is called:",
    "feedback": "bends"
  },
  {
    "question": "1. Psychosomatic means that a physiological problem is followed by psychological stress \n2. Psychosomatic complaints hardly occur in professional aviation because of the strict selection for this particular profession",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are both not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The ability of detecting relevant information which is not presented in an actively monitored input channel is known as",
    "feedback": "attention"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot  is prone to get vertigo, as visibility is impaired (dust, smoke, snow). What is the correct action to prevent vertigo?",
    "feedback": "Depend on the instruments"
  },
  {
    "question": "Breathing 100% oxygen at 38000 ft is equivalent to breathing ambient air at :",
    "feedback": "8 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Non-verbal communication:",
    "feedback": "constitutes approximately 70% of human communication"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by \"divided attention\"?",
    "feedback": "Switching of attention from one set of stimuli to another"
  },
  {
    "question": "The level of automation helps to conserve resources. On the other hand, it may result in:",
    "feedback": "routine errors (slips)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Up to what altitude will generally healthy people be able to stay without showing any signs of suffering from hypoxia?",
    "feedback": "Up to 10-12000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "The partial pressure of the respiratory gases within the pulmonary alveoli  is",
    "feedback": "40 mmHg pCO2, 47 mmHg pH2O, 100 mmHg O2"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the different phases of the General Adaptation Syndrome (GAS/Selye), which of the following statement/s is/are correct?\n1) During the alarm phase stress hormones (i.e. adrenalin) will cause a massive release of glucose into the blood, an acceleration of pulse and blood pressure as well as an increase in the rate and depth of breathing2) During the restistance phase the parasympathetic system uses a different type of hormone (cortisol) assisting for the conversion of fat into sugar3) During the exhaustion phase the body has to be given time to eliminate the waste products which have been generated excessively during the two preceding phases",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the various means which allow for better error detection?\n-1 : Improvement of the man-machine interface.\n-2 : Development of systems for checking the consistency of \n       situations.\n-3 : Compliance with cross-over redundant procedures by the\n      crew.\n-4 : Adaptation of visual alarms to all systems.\n\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do you do, when you are affected by \"pilot`s vertigo\"?\n\n1. Establish and maintain an effective instrument cross-check.\n2. Believe the instruments.\n3. Ignore illusions.\n4. Minimize head movements.",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Air at an altitude of 18.000 feet contains, approximately :",
    "feedback": "21% oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lowest level of Maslow's Model of the hierarchy of human needs is:",
    "feedback": "physiological needs"
  },
  {
    "question": "During running your muscles are producing more CO2, raising the CO2 level in the blood. The consequence is:",
    "feedback": "hyperventilation (the rate and depth of breathing will increase)"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a rapid decompression in a 2-crew aircraft, the other pilot becomes incapacitated. Your first action is to:",
    "feedback": "don your own oxygen mask"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is \"divided attention\"?",
    "feedback": "The management of several matters of interest dealt with individually one after the other"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the flying pilot becomes incapacitated, the most important action for the non-flying pilot is:",
    "feedback": "to take control of the aeroplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Out of the list of possible measures to counteract hyperventilation, the most effective measure is:",
    "feedback": "breathe into a plastic or paper bag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Barotrauma caused by gas accumulation in the stomach and intestinals can lead to:",
    "feedback": "pressure pain or flatulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning check list is correct?",
    "feedback": "The most important items should be placed at the beginning of  a check list since attention is usually focused here"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the pressoreceptors signal a lowering of the blood-pressure there are adaptation mechanisms which result in:\n1. an increase of respiratory activity\n2. the arteriols to constrict\n3. an increase of cardiac output\n4. the heart rate to rise",
    "feedback": "2,3 and 4 are correct, 1 is false"
  },
  {
    "question": "A stress reaction is:",
    "feedback": "the non-specific response of the body to every demand placed on a person"
  },
  {
    "question": "The condition of the normal eye when parallel rays are focused exactly on the retina and vision is perfect is called:",
    "feedback": "Emmetropia"
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens when arousal passes beyond the break point?",
    "feedback": "Both arousal and stress increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Having made an important decision, a commander of an aircraft should:",
    "feedback": "always try to make time to explain the reasons for the decision even if it is after landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Workload essentially depends on:",
    "feedback": "the current situation, the pilot's expertise and the ergonomics of the system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under normal circumstances, which gas will diffuse from the blood to the alveoli:",
    "feedback": "carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "The planning and anticipation of future actions and situations makes it possible to:\n-1 : create a precise reference framework.\n-2 : avoid saturation of the cognitive system.\n-3 : automate planned actions.\n-4 : activate knowledge which is considered necessary for the \n       period to come.\n\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The general gas law states",
    "feedback": "the volume of a gas multiplied by its pressure divided by its absolute temperature is constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding roles and norms within a group?",
    "feedback": "An airline captain must conform to a role as a leader in the aircraft, but can act as a follower in the yacht club."
  },
  {
    "question": "Rods (scotopic visual cells) allow for :",
    "feedback": "good night-vision after adaptation to darkness (30 min)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Thinking on human reliability is changing.",
    "feedback": "Human errors are now considered as being inherent to the cognitive function of human and are generally inescapable"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are the most favourable solutions to manage phases of reduced or low vigilance (hypovigilance)? 1. Eat a meal 2. Keep active, open communication between man and machine 3. Reduce the intensity of the light 4. Organise periods of rest during the flight",
    "feedback": "2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the Threat and Error Management (TEM) model. A flight crew experiences an undesired aircraft state (UAS). The most correct course of action is:",
    "feedback": "Take immediate countermeasures to recover to a normal operational state"
  },
  {
    "question": "Concerning circadian rhythm disruption (jet lag), the effects of adjustment to destination time :\n1. are longer for western rather than eastern flights\n2. are longer for eastern rather than western flights\n3. vary little between individuals\n4. may vary greatly between individuals",
    "feedback": "2,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The average annual amount of cosmic radiation received by crew members:",
    "feedback": "is about the same as the amount of background radiation"
  },
  {
    "question": "When exposed to decreasing barometric pressure, 1 litre of gas contained in the stomach and intestines at sea level will\nexpand to 8 litres at:",
    "feedback": "40 000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "The probability to suffer from air-sickness is higher, when",
    "feedback": "the passenger or student is afraid and/or  demotivated to fly"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of stress on a pilot's arousal state and performance?",
    "feedback": "Levels of stress that are higher than the optimum value reduce performance levels"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is understood by air-sickness?",
    "feedback": "A sensory conflict within the vestibular system accompanied by nausea, vomiting and fear"
  },
  {
    "question": "Most accidents are mainly caused by lack of:",
    "feedback": "good judgement"
  },
  {
    "question": "The symptoms of hyperventilation are caused by a:",
    "feedback": "shortage of CO2 in the blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning stress is correct?",
    "feedback": "Stress will be evaluated differently depending on whether it improves or reduces performance."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\nThe blood-pressure which is measured during flight medical checks is the pressure",
    "feedback": "in the artery of the upper arm (representing the pressure at heart level)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of acceleration has the most significant physiological effect upon the pilot?",
    "feedback": "Radial acceleration (+ Gz)"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the TEM model, threats are grouped in two basic categories. One of these categories refers to environmental threats and the other category refers to:",
    "feedback": "Organisational threats that occur due to the organisation in aviation structures"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the I.C.A.O. standard atmosphere, the temperature lapse rate of the troposphere is approximately",
    "feedback": "- 2 °C every 1000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "The level at which a pilot will experience a situation as stressful",
    "feedback": "depends on the individual's perception of available abilities in comparison to the situational demands"
  },
  {
    "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness",
    "feedback": "are bends, chokes, skin manifestations, neurological symptoms and  circulatory shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Signs of stress include:",
    "feedback": "Perspiration, dilated pupils, fast breathing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements best characterise a synergistic cockpit?\n1) Decisions are taken by the captain, but prepared by the crew2) There is little delegating of tasks3) Communications are few in number but precise and geared purely to the flight4) Fluid, consensual boundaries exist in regard to leadership-style, which fluctuate between authority and laissez-faire",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effects of sleep deprivation on performance:  1. increase with altitude 2. decrease with altitude 3. increase with higher workload 4. decrease with higher workload",
    "feedback": "1 and 3 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An individually given feedback improves communication. Which of the following rules should a feedback comply with?",
    "feedback": "The feedback should always relate to a specific situation."
  },
  {
    "question": "High arousal leads to:",
    "feedback": "faster but less accurate responses"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements best characterise  a self-centered cockpit ?",
    "feedback": "Without taking note of what the other members are doing, each one does his own thing while at the same time assuming that everyone is aware of what is being done or what is going on"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is true with reference to semantic memory?",
    "feedback": "It is the meaning of words and general knowledge of the world; it lasts for a longer period of time and tends to be more accurate than episodic memory"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following is an example of a \"hard\" systematic-based countermeasure that flight crew use to manage threats, errors, and undesired aircraft states:",
    "feedback": "Airborne Collision Avoidance System (ACAS)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Among the factors which affect night vision are:",
    "feedback": "age, cabin altitudes above 5000 ft, smoking and alcohol"
  },
  {
    "question": "The first cockpit tool that tends to suffer as a result of stress is:",
    "feedback": "cockpit communications"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement applies to hypoxia?",
    "feedback": "sensitivity and reaction to hypoxia varies from person to person"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot who smokes will lose some of his capacity to transport oxygen combined with hemoglobin. \nWhich percentage of his total oxygen transportation capacity would he give away  when he smokes one pack of cigarettes a day?",
    "feedback": "5 - 8%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying a  coordinated level   turn will",
    "feedback": "make the body`s pressure receptors feel an increased pressure along the body`s vertical axis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is learning how to recover from an undesired aircraft state (undesired aircraft situation). Which option is correct as regards the role of Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs) in reducing the risk of an accident?",
    "feedback": "SOPs can state the minimum attitude for the manoeuvre and the conditions under which the instructor should take control of the aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 'Graveyard Spin' is:",
    "feedback": "a spin in which the pilot, on recovery, tends to re-enter the spin due to the somatogyral illusion where the vestibular system no longer senses radial acceleration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Information received from the senses is lost:",
    "feedback": "within 10-20 seconds unless it is rehearsed and deliberately placed in the long term memory"
  },
  {
    "question": "Concerning the effects of drugs and pilot´s performance",
    "feedback": "the primary and the side effects have to be considered"
  },
  {
    "question": "Complete the following statement:\nSafety culture is ______ national culture",
    "feedback": "a subset of"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most probable reason for spatial disorientation is",
    "feedback": "a poor instrument cross-check and permanently transitioning back and forth between instruments and visual references"
  },
  {
    "question": "Heart attack (myocardial infarction):",
    "feedback": "is the commonest cause of death in men over the age of 40"
  },
  {
    "question": "With which risk is skill-based behaviour associated?",
    "feedback": "Action slip"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning hypovigilance is correct ?\nHypovigilance :",
    "feedback": "may occur at any moment of the flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the cruising phase of a short-haul flight the captain starts to smoke a cigarette in the cockpit. The flying copilot asks him to stop smoking because he is a non-smoker. The captain tells him: 'This is your problem', and continues smoking. What should the copilot do?",
    "feedback": "He should not further discuss this issue but should come back to this conflict during the debriefing"
  },
  {
    "question": "While assessing a risk two main factors have to be considered. What are they?",
    "feedback": "Probability of that risk and its severity"
  },
  {
    "question": "The area in front of a threshold descends towards the threshold.\nPossible danger is:",
    "feedback": "approach is higher than normal and may result in a long landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following situation on the flight deck of a modern airliner: The aircraft is descending and cannot maintain the desired flight path with the selected cost index. Without any active pilot input, it changes from VNAV Path Mode to VNAV Speed Mode. The crew notice the change in the automation mode, but do not understand that the automation is no longer maintaining the descent path.\nWhich term can be be used to describe the crew's lack of understanding?",
    "feedback": "Mode confusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the best visual cues for height during the round out?",
    "feedback": "apparent speed and texture of ground objects"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to limit stress when flying, a pilot should:",
    "feedback": "maintain his competence by practicing his professional skills and learning from past experiences"
  },
  {
    "question": "On average most human adults require approximately how many hours of sleep per night?",
    "feedback": "8 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying while suffering from a cold may expose a pilot to:",
    "feedback": "otic and sinus barotrauma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What seems to be the  main role of Orthodox sleep ?",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "What seems to be the  main role of Orthodox sleep ?",
    "feedback": "It essentially allows for physical recovery"
  },
  {
    "question": "Oxygen is transported through the walls of the alveoli according to",
    "feedback": "the Diffusion law"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the most decisive factor in regard to a very demanding stress situation?",
    "feedback": "The subjective evaluation of the situation by the individual."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by \"barotrauma\"?",
    "feedback": "Trapped gases inside your body create pain as ambient pressure decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "A TCAS Resolution Advisory (RA) sounds in flight. Which part of the inner ear carries the sound of the alert to the crew?",
    "feedback": "The fluid-filled cochlea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true concerning regular physical exercise?\n\n1) It increases pulse rate and stroke volume in the short term\n2) It reduces blood pressure and heart rate in the long term\n3) It reduces human tolerance to hypoxia",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot successfully completes a difficult and stressful landing at an aerodrome. The next time a landing is attempted under the same conditions and at the same aerodrome, is the pilot likely to experience:",
    "feedback": "a lower level of stress"
  },
  {
    "question": "You can overcome hyperventilation by breathing into a plastic  or paper bag. The intention is:",
    "feedback": "to raise the level of CO2 in the blood as fast as possible"
  },
  {
    "question": "CO (carbon monoxide) present in the smoke of cigarettes can lead to: \n1. reduction of time of useful consciousness   \n2. hypoxia at a much lower altitude than normal",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are both correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A good method to treat hyperventilation is to:",
    "feedback": "talk oneself through the relevant procedure aloud to emotionally calm down and reduce the rate of breathing simultaneously"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct regarding REM sleep?",
    "feedback": "REM sleep re-vitalises your brain after strenuous mental activity."
  },
  {
    "question": "The human vestibular system performs spatial orientation by:",
    "feedback": "measuring linear and radial acceleration within the inner ear"
  },
  {
    "question": "When oxygen is being transferred from the blood into the tissues and carbon dioxide from the body cells into the blood, it is called:",
    "feedback": "internal respiration"
  },
  {
    "question": "If one error is allowed to affect a whole system, the system is described as:",
    "feedback": "vulnerable"
  },
  {
    "question": "The sleep pattern is closely associated with?",
    "feedback": "Body temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to the level of automation of behaviours in the attention mechanism, we know that :",
    "feedback": "the more behaviour is automated, the less it requires conscious attention and thus the more it frees mental resources"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the ways human error in aviation currently being addressed is by 'error tolerance'. What is error tolerance?",
    "feedback": "The understanding of human limitations by determining how to live with errors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Symptoms of decompression sickness",
    "feedback": "sometimes can appear  with a delay after the airplane is on the ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of the following statements, regarding stress, which is correct?",
    "feedback": "Stress may be positive, fatigue is always negative"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alcohol degrades:",
    "feedback": "Paradoxical sleep"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the optical image forms in front of the retina; we are talking about",
    "feedback": "myopia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Glaucoma is characterised by:  1. disturbed light adaptation  2. progressive narrowing of the visual field  3. insidious onset and concealed progression  4. an increase in intra-ocular pressure",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The inner ear is able to perceive:  \n1. angular acceleration  \n2. linear acceleration  \n3. noise",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 and 3 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider emergency situations such as engine failure in a helicopter or an impending stall in an aeroplane. Audio and visual warnings and the aircraft's attitude are stimuli to which the pilot must very quickly react by carrying out the correct recovery manoeuvre (autorotation or upset prevention).\nWhat is the most effective form of learning to allow the pilot to react quickly to the stimuli and carry out the correct manoeuvre?",
    "feedback": "Operant conditioning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stress occurs:  -1 : only in a situation of imminent danger. -2 : only when faced with real, existing and palpable phenomenon. -3 : sometimes via imagination, the anticipation of a situation or its outcome. -4 : because of the similarity with a formerly experienced stressful situation  The correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In decision-making, the selection of a solution depends :\n1. on objective and subjective criteria\n2. on the objective to be achieved\n3. on the risks associated with each solution\n4. above all on the personality of the decision-maker",
    "feedback": "1,2,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Affinity to hemoglobin is best with:",
    "feedback": "carbon monoxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "Usually, the body has a remarkable store of the following gases",
    "feedback": "carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "The system which controls breathing, digestion, heart rate, etc., over which there is no voluntary control, is:",
    "feedback": "the autonomic nervous system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct with regard to the design of a check list?\n\n-1 : The longer a check list, the more it must be subdivided into logical parts\n-2 : The trickiest points must be placed in the middle of the check list\n-3 : Check lists must be designed in such a way that they can be lumped together with other tasks\n-4 : Whenever possible, a panel scan sequence should be applied\n-5 : Use should be made of upper case/bold/italics/colour with care to emphasize critical items or points\n\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 4 and 5 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following a rapid decompression at 30.000 feet, the time of useful consciousness would be about:",
    "feedback": "between 45 seconds and 1 minute 30 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main sources of error in a pilot's decision-making mechanism?",
    "feedback": "Assessment of the environmental circumstances"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypoxia is caused by",
    "feedback": "reduced partial oxygen pressure in the lung"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the decision making process, confirmation bias results in:",
    "feedback": "a tendency to look for information which confirms the validity of the decision"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which procedure is recommended to prevent or overcome spatial disorientation?",
    "feedback": "Rely entirely on the indications of the flight instruments."
  },
  {
    "question": "A certain amount of water vapour saturated air (i.e. intestinal gases) is transported from sea-level up to 34 000 ft. In  the same amount of dry air, the volume of this gas is :",
    "feedback": "larger"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do you understand the statement 'one cannot not communicate'?",
    "feedback": "Being silent as well as inactive are nonverbal behaviour patterns which express a meaning."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the statements below concerning blood pressure is correct?",
    "feedback": "It needs to be high enough to guarantee an adequate blood flow to the brain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the factors below can have a negative impact on human reliability?\n1) Complacency2) Distractions3) Fatigue4) Low and medium workload levels5) Lack of awareness",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a crew is having a stop-over of less than 24 hours before returning to their homebase, what coping strategy should be used for jet-lag?",
    "feedback": "Maintain eating and sleeping cycle based on home time"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Skill-based, Rule-based, Knowledge-based Model (Jens Rasmussen) is associated with:",
    "feedback": "behaviour"
  },
  {
    "question": "You fly VFR from your home base (runway width 45 m) to a small airfield (runway width 27 m). On reaching your destination there is a risk of performing a:",
    "feedback": "low approach with undershoot"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal arterial blood-pressure of a healthy adult is (systolic/diastolic):",
    "feedback": "120/80 mm Hg"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following provides the basis of all perceptions?",
    "feedback": "The intensity of the stimuli."
  },
  {
    "question": "Astigmatism is caused by:",
    "feedback": "a mis-shapened cornea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the most important parts of the eye in the order they are met from the direction the light enters the eye, until it reaches the visual cortex:",
    "feedback": "Cornea, iris and pupil, lens, retina"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are transporting a passenger who has to be at a certain destination for a meeting. The weather forcast at destination tends to be much worse than expected, so you consider to divert. The businessman offers you money if you manage to land there at any case.\nWhat is your appropriate way of action? You will",
    "feedback": "decide to divert if you think it is necessary."
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared with day operations, what differences should a pilot adopt when seeking to identify a possible collision threat at night?",
    "feedback": "Move the eyes in small arcs to induce a moving image on the retina for the rods to identify"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by Episodic memory?",
    "feedback": "memory of experienced events, held in the long term memory."
  },
  {
    "question": "An experienced pilot is flying on schedule and on time, the weather is above the minima for the destination airport. Suddenly, the visibility dropped below the minima and the pilot decided to continue the approach and at the end landed safely.\nWhat can explain why the pilot did not divert and decided to land without the required minima?",
    "feedback": "The pilot was anxious to land on time and wanted to avoid getting behind schedule for the next flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "A large number of medical preparations can be bought without a doctor´s prescription. In relation to using these preparations, which of the following is correct:",
    "feedback": "A pilot using any of these preparations should get professional advice from a flight surgeon if he intends to fly and self-medicate at the same time"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following characteristics form part of decision-making on the flight deck ?",
    "feedback": "A good decision depends on analysis of the situation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following indicates a high degree of situational awareness?",
    "feedback": "Both pilots mutually re-check their mental models due to new information"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the different phases of the \"General Adaptation Syndrom\" check the following statements:\n\n1. During the alarm phase stress hormones (i.e. adrenalin) will cause a massiv release  of glucose into the blood, an acceleration of pulse and blood pressure as well as an increase in the rate and depth of breathing\n2. During the resistance phase the parasympathetic system uses a different type of hormone (cortisol) assisting to convert  fat into sugar thus providing sufficient energy supply to the brain and body cells for sustained operation.\n3. During the exhaustion phase the body has to be given time to eliminate the waste products which have been generated excessively during the two preceeding phases",
    "feedback": "1,2 and 3 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a pilot suffers from hypothermia (e.g. after loss of cabin heating) his/her demand for oxygen will be:",
    "feedback": "initially increased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Concerning the light sensitive cells of the eye:",
    "feedback": "the cones detect colour vision and are highly sensitive to hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why does carbon monoxide (CO) lead to hypoxia?",
    "feedback": "CO in blood displaces oxygen from the blood corpuscles impairing oxygen transport"
  },
  {
    "question": "The acquisition of skill comprises three stages ( Anderson model):",
    "feedback": "cognitive, associative and autonomous"
  },
  {
    "question": "Linear acceleration when flying straight and level in IMC may give the illusion of:",
    "feedback": "climbing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Smoking cigarettes reduces the capability of the blood to carry oxygen. This is because:",
    "feedback": "hemoglobin has a greater affinity for carbon monoxide than it has for oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "With \"vertigo\" the instrument-panel  seems to  tumble . This is due to",
    "feedback": "the coriolis effect in the semicircular canals"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stress is a frequent aspect of the pilot's job. Under which of the following circumstances does it occur?\n1. Stress occurs whenever the pilot must revise his plan of action and does not immediately have a solution\n2. Stress occurs with unexperienced pilots when the situational demands exceed their individual capabilities\n3. Stress occurs if a pilot is convinced that he will not be able to find a solution for the problem he just is confronted with",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 3 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Once detected, an error will result in cognitive consequences which:",
    "feedback": "make it possible to modify behaviour with a view to adaptation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The relevance of check procedures during flight becomes even more important when:",
    "feedback": "flying an unfamiliar type of aircraft and experiencing mental pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is an environmental threat according to the TEM (Threat and Error Management) model?",
    "feedback": "A contaminated runway"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot has caught a cold. What may happen to his susceptibility to hypoxia?",
    "feedback": "it will increase due to the need to generate more oxygen which leads to a greater demand for oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "The errors resulting from an illogical indexing system in an operations manual are related to an interface mismatch between",
    "feedback": "Liveware - Software"
  },
  {
    "question": "The onset of presbyopia depends",
    "feedback": "on age and whether the subject is shortsighted, farsighted, or normal sighted"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can the consumption of alcohol affect sleep?",
    "feedback": "Yes, it affects the sleep patterns"
  },
  {
    "question": "What may the harmful effects of obesity include?",
    "feedback": "Sleep apnoea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which scanning technique should be used  when flying at night?",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which scanning technique should be used  when flying at night?",
    "feedback": "Look to the side (15 - 20 deg) of the object."
  },
  {
    "question": "The peripheral vision is important for:",
    "feedback": "detecting moving objects"
  },
  {
    "question": "On 8th July 2010, the crew of a Boeing 737 from Nice to Frankfurt was cleared by the controller of Sector L14 to continue its climb to FL320. In an adjacent sector, the crew of an Airbus 319 from London to Milan was cleared to leave FL390 and to descend to FL330. The instruction was read back correctly, but the pilots incorrectly entered FL320 into the FMS. Upon being handed off to sector L14, the Airbus called the controller:\n\"Easy 529 Yankee, descending FL320 on radar heading 133\".\nThe controller identified the traffic but did not realise the incorrect flight level reported by the Airbus. Shortly after, the two aircraft were converging on FL320 and triggered potential conflict alerts on both the controller's system and the on-board TCAS of each aircraft. Corrective action had to be taken by each aircraft to re-establish separation.\nWhat type of communication and associated disadvantage are illustrated by this serious incident of a \"level bust\" with resulting loss of separation?",
    "feedback": "Explicit communication, which is prone to confirmation bias, that is, we hear what we expect to hear and not what is being said"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statements are correct regarding Standard Operating Procedures (SOP)?\n1) SOPs must not be performed from memory, in order to avoid omissions2) SOPs are performed as skill-based and rule-based behaviours3) SOPs that are frequently amended are more likely to be correctly executed than SOPs that remain unchanged4) There is a higher risk of error due to reversion to previous habits when a pilot executes a recently modified SOP",
    "feedback": "2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct statement from the ones below:",
    "feedback": "The harmful effects of smoking are also detected in parts of the body other than the lungs (e.g. bladder, kidneys and blood vessels)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the following list the advantages of teamwork:\n\n1) workload is lessened\n2) conformity to group norm\n3) flight safety enhanced\n4) risky shift\n5) work stress is reduced\n6) improved decision making",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 5, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "A person experiencing light headaches, dizziness, tingling at the fingertips and breathing rapidly may be suffering from:",
    "feedback": "hypoxia or hyperventilation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The physiology of stress is now well known:",
    "feedback": "stress promotes an increase in physical strength rather than promoting mental performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main strategies for adapting to time constraints ?",
    "feedback": "The preparation of action and the prioritisation of tasks"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying at night the first sense to be affected by a slight degree of hypoxia is the",
    "feedback": "vision"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the effects of stress?",
    "feedback": "It increases vigilance and may focus attention"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following responses is an example of \"habit reversion\" (negative habit transfer):",
    "feedback": "A pilot who has flown many hours in an aircraft in which the fuel lever points forward for the ON position, may unintentionally turn the fuel lever into the false position, when flying a different aircraft, where the fuel lever has to point aft to be in the ON position"
  },
  {
    "question": "To prevent vertigo in flight we should",
    "feedback": "not move the head suddenly while we are turning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Retrograde amnesia causes loss of memory of events and ......",
    "feedback": "episodic memory"
  },
  {
    "question": "Any stimulus that causes stress is referred to as a stressor. In the cockpit, an example of an environmental stressor is......",
    "feedback": "Engine noise"
  },
  {
    "question": "Using a checklist prior start is a contribution to",
    "feedback": "safety,  because the concentration on the check list items will draw the pilot´s attention to flight related tasks, reducing distraction from personal stress"
  },
  {
    "question": "State the main component of an SMS:",
    "feedback": "Safety management"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to the practice of English, which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "All pilots should master it because the aeronautical world needs one common language."
  },
  {
    "question": "Gases of physiological importance to man are:",
    "feedback": "oxygen and carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Jens Rasmussen, riding a bicycle is:",
    "feedback": "skill-based behaviour"
  },
  {
    "question": "Perceiving a small object as further away or a larger object as being closer is an example of:",
    "feedback": "Top down processing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Having interrupted the captain for a sound reason, the co-pilot should:",
    "feedback": "remind him/her of his/her last action before the interruption"
  },
  {
    "question": "The damaging effects of noise on the pilot depends on:\n\n1) the intensity of the noise\n2) the frequency of the noise\n3) the exposure time to noise\n4) proper use of the headset in the cockpit\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Adaptation is",
    "feedback": "the adjustment of the eyes to high or low levels of  illumination"
  },
  {
    "question": "Presbyopia:",
    "feedback": "is common over the age of 50"
  },
  {
    "question": "Having a cold or an infection of the upper respiratory tract you:",
    "feedback": "should not fly because the congestion of the frontal sinuses may cause great pain which can seriously affect your ability to control yourself and the aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Through which part of the ear does the equalization of pressure  take place, when altitude is changed?",
    "feedback": "Eustachian tube"
  },
  {
    "question": "Judgement is based upon:",
    "feedback": "a process involving a pilot´s attitude to take and to evaluate risks by assessing the situation and making decisions based upon knowledge, skill and experience"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main purpose of a checklist?",
    "feedback": "To enable the crew to carry out a procedure in a well-defined and orderly manner"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hepatitis A infection:",
    "feedback": "can be prevented by gammaglobulin or vaccination"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many breaths per minute is the normal respiratory rate of an adult at rest?",
    "feedback": "10 to 15"
  },
  {
    "question": "Planning:",
    "feedback": "allows crew members to anticipate potential risky situations and decide on possible responses"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a stressor?",
    "feedback": "An external or internal stimulus which is interpreted by an individual as being stressful"
  },
  {
    "question": "A person experiences increased breathing rate. Which of the following is the most likely explanation?",
    "feedback": "a high level of waste carbon dioxide in the lungs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Once we have constructed a mental model we tend",
    "feedback": "to give undue weight to information that confirms the model"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements fits best the concept of latent error?",
    "feedback": "have been present in the system for a certain length of time and are difficult to understand as a result of the time lag between the generation and the occurence of the error"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vision of terrain relief (eg. hills, valleys, etc.):",
    "feedback": "is based on binocular vision at short distances and the rules of proportion and perspective for objects that are further away"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is true about complacency?",
    "feedback": "Complacency is a dangerous attitude because it leads to a loss of awareness of danger"
  },
  {
    "question": "The process of responding to a sender by confirming the reception of a message is called",
    "feedback": "feedback"
  },
  {
    "question": "Learning is called each lasting change of behaviour due to",
    "feedback": "practice and experience"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does error tolerance aim for?",
    "feedback": "Providing a margin so that any errors do not endanger the flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the Time of Useful Consciouness ?",
    "feedback": "The length of time during which an individual can act with both  mental and physical efficiency and alertness, measured from the moment at which he loses his available oxygen supply"
  },
  {
    "question": "The ozone layer",
    "feedback": "absorbs UVB better than UVA"
  },
  {
    "question": "During flight, a terrain proximity caution sounds on the flight deck. The pilot misidentifies the problem, believing that the auditory alert is associated with a configuration warning, subsequently applying the wrong procedures. \nThis error is associated with ......",
    "feedback": "rule-based behaviour"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the meaning of the \"S\" in the SHELL model?",
    "feedback": "Software"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a pilot has to perform two tasks requiring the allocation of cognitive resources :",
    "feedback": "the sharing of resources causes performance on each task to be reduced"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most fatal crash in aviation history occurred on March 29th 1977 at Tenerife Los Rodeos Airport, when a KLM Boeing 747 collided with a Pan American Boeing 747 in almost zero visibility conditions in severe fog.\nIn the course leading to the accident, the KLM aircraft received its route clearance, which was read back by the First Officer, finishing by saying \"we are now ready for take-off\". The controller's reply was \"OK, stand by for take-off\"; however, the KLM crew only received the \"OK\" part as the rest of the sentence was cut off by a simultaneous transmission from another aircraft on the same frequency (interference). The KLM captain interpreted the \"OK\" as take-off clearance and started his take-off run. However, at that time, the Pan American Boeing 747 was still taxiing down the runway, leading to the fatal collision.\nState which type of communication and associated disadvantage are illustrated by the above accident:",
    "feedback": "Explicit communication. Since it was interrupted, it should have required communication with the controller"
  },
  {
    "question": "Situations particularly vulnerable to \"reversion to an earlier behaviour pattern\" are :\n1. when concentration on a particular task is relaxed\n2. when situations are characterised by medium workload\n3. when situations are characterised by stress",
    "feedback": "1. and 3."
  },
  {
    "question": "The following statements are true except",
    "feedback": "poor circulation is called hypoxic hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "What can cause spatial disorientation?",
    "feedback": "False perception of orientation of the aircraft with respect to spatial references"
  },
  {
    "question": "How long should a pilot wait before undertaking flying duties after sub-aqua diving?",
    "feedback": "24 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are primary sources of motivation in day-to-day professional life ?\n1. Being in control of one's own situation\n2. Fear of punishment\n3. Success (achievement of goals)\n4. Social promotion, money",
    "feedback": "1,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to make communication effective, it is necessary to: \n\n-1 : avoid the synchronization of verbal and non-verbal channels.\n-2 : send information in line with the receiver's decoding abilities\n-3 : always concentrate on the informational aspects of the message only\n-4 : avoid increasing the number of communication channels, in order to simplify communication\n\nThe correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "only 2 is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The time an eye needs to adapt fully to the dark is about:",
    "feedback": "25 - 30 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning the term \"arousal\" is correct?",
    "feedback": "Arousal is the degree of activation of the central nervous system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following strategies is accepted as helping to reduce the effects of jet lag for aircrew after a long eastward flight that arrives at 11.00 Local Time?",
    "feedback": "Seek bright light in the evening and keep the curtains closed in the morning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding arousal, which of the following statements is wrong?",
    "feedback": "A medium level of arousal can be dangerous, since you have little spare mental capacity in this situation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering TEM, which of the following is an example of an organisational threat?",
    "feedback": "Using incorrect or expired charts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Professional languages have certain characteristics, for example:  1 : They use a limited vocabulary2 : They are rich and adapted to the context, which sometimes leads to ambiguities3 : Their grammar is rather complicated and complex4 : Context provides meaning, therefor reduces the risk of ambiguities  The correct statement(s) is (are):",
    "feedback": "1 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "When scanning, how does the eye move and how is smooth vision achieved?",
    "feedback": "The eyes move in short jerky movements called saccades. Smooth vision is achieved in the visual cortex"
  },
  {
    "question": "The first effect to be noticed on gradual exposure to high positive radial accelerations is",
    "feedback": "grey-out"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is included in the 8 core competencies that an ICAO licenced pilot must have?",
    "feedback": "Communication, leadership and teamwork, application of procedures, situation awareness"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Fatigue Risk Management System (FRMS) is a data-driven means of continuously monitoring and managing fatigue-related safety risks, based upon scientific principles and knowledge as well as operational experience that aims to ensure relevant personnel are performing at adequate levels of alertness.\nWhat kind of safety culture is established in a company using a FRMS?",
    "feedback": "Learning culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following statement about atmospheric humidity is true:",
    "feedback": "the relative humidity measures percentage of water vapor saturation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning hypoxia is correct?",
    "feedback": "It is a potential threat to safety."
  },
  {
    "question": "Feedback in communication implies that:",
    "feedback": "a message is measured and corrected against the original meaning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Safety culture is relatively enduring, stable and resistant to change. This statement:",
    "feedback": "is true"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot used to operating European short-haul flights is transferring to long-haul, with many tropcial destinations. Packing for the first long-haul tropical sector, which of the following would be advisable to include?\n1) Sun block for the more intense sunlight in the tropcis2) Tight-fitting dark-coloured clothing to repel mosquitoes3) Sunglasses to filter the strong infra-red light from the sun4) A wide-brimmed hat to protect the head from the intense sunlight",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why are Mnemonics used in aviation?",
    "feedback": "Because they help to increase retention of information"
  },
  {
    "question": "The retina of the eye",
    "feedback": "is the light-sensitive inner lining of the eye containing the photoreceptors essential for vision"
  },
  {
    "question": "The statement: Adjacent gases of different concentration mix until the concentration is balanced:",
    "feedback": "is known as Diffusion law"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying with a cold you might primarily experience problems with:",
    "feedback": "pain around the forehead"
  },
  {
    "question": "Angular accelerations are perceived by:",
    "feedback": "the semicircular canals"
  },
  {
    "question": "State which kind of culture is not typical for an aviation company with a working safety management system (SMS):",
    "feedback": "Closed culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to avoid hypoglycaemia:",
    "feedback": "a pilot should eat regularly and ensure he/she has a balanced diet."
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is skilled when he/she:\n\n-1 : trains or practises regularly\n-2 : knows how to manage himself/herself\n-3 : possesses all the knowledge associated with his aircraft\n-4 : knows how to keep resources in reserve for coping with the unexpected",
    "feedback": "1,2,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Conscious perception",
    "feedback": "is a mental process involving experience and expectations"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning synergy within a crew is most correct?",
    "feedback": "Synergy must be built up from the start of the mission (briefing) and be maintained until it comes to an end (debriefing)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Incorrect perception:",
    "feedback": "can be highly persuasive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hyperventilation is:",
    "feedback": "an increased lung ventilation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following signs or symptoms may be harmful effects of ozone except",
    "feedback": "bends and chokes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following can be called a \"stressor\"?",
    "feedback": "Increased cockpit noise"
  },
  {
    "question": "The semicircular canals form part of the",
    "feedback": "inner ear"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pressoreceptors are located in",
    "feedback": "the carotid and aortic arterial vessels"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements regarding interpersonal interactions are correct?\n\n1) If the sender perceives that the receiver is incompetent, he/she will simplify the message\n2) If the receiver is of non-native tongue, the sender will reinforce what he is saying by using more complicated words so as to optimize understanding\n3) If the sender considers there is doubt that the message has been correctly understood, he/she must seek clarification\n4) It is much safer to fly with a crew who know each other well because communication will always be excellent\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can a pilot avoid automation complacency?",
    "feedback": "Regard the automatic system as additional crew members that needs to be crosschecked as well"
  },
  {
    "question": "The approximate time required for complete adaption of the eye when moving from darkness to light is:",
    "feedback": "10 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the time limit between a pilot going snorkelling and the beginning of his flight duty?",
    "feedback": "There is no time limit"
  },
  {
    "question": "By \"long duration acceleration\" we mean that it lasts more than:",
    "feedback": "1 sec"
  },
  {
    "question": "If carbon monoxide poisoning in flight is suspected, which of the following actions should a crew member take?\n1) Turn the cabin heat off2) Turn the cabin heat on3) Select the maximum rate of fresh air ventilation to the cabin4) Turn off all fresh air ventilation to the cabin5) Open the window if the environment allows6) Land as soon as possible/practical and seek medical attention7) Avoid using supplemental oxygen",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 5, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "The part of blood without cell is called :",
    "feedback": "plasm"
  },
  {
    "question": "A passenger complains about a painful inflated belly at 8.000 feet.  You advise him to:\n1. unbuckle and massage the belly\n2. stand up and let go the gases out of the intestines\n3. eat less gas forming food and avoid carbonhydrated beverages \n     before flight in the future\n4. drink a lot of water throughout the flight",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 3 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following physical stimuli may cause stress reactions?\n-1 : noise.\n-2 : interpersonnal conflict.\n-3 : temperature.\n-4 : administrative problem.\n-5 : hunger.\n\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1,3,5"
  },
  {
    "question": "The  requirement of good sunglasses is to",
    "feedback": "absorb enough visible light to eliminate glare without decreasing visual acuity, absorb UV and IR radiation and absorb all colors equally"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which elements of communication are prone to malfunctioning?",
    "feedback": "The sender and the receiver as well as coding and decoding"
  },
  {
    "question": "Programming of autoflight systems can add to the pilot's workload, and slips can easily occur during programming.\nWhich of the following methods is the safest to use?",
    "feedback": "Avoid programming during critical stages of flight. Cross checking of programming should be completed prior to acceptance"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is distracted by a failure of his navigation equipment and consequently does not execute a planned turn. Afterwards, he lands at his intermediate airport and checks the weather at his final destination. As the weather looks good, he decides to take off without loading additional fuel. When he encounters an unexpected headwind, he barely makes it to his final destination with just enough fuel to perform one go-around and land at the destination. Which types of error did he commit? \n1) Forgotten turn: lapse2) Forgotten turn: violation3) Forgotten turn: slip4) Forgotten turn: rule-based error5) Fuel: violation6) Fuel: lapse7) Fuel: knowledge-based error",
    "feedback": "1, 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by \"feedback\" in communication?",
    "feedback": "The effect of a message is measured and corrected against the original meaning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Carbon monoxide is particularly dangerous because .....\n1) it is colourless2) its pungent smell can cause nausea3) it is highly toxic4) its effects are cumulative",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by the term \"Incapacitation\"?",
    "feedback": "The gradual or sudden loss of a crew member's ability to function"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what International Standard Atmosphere (ISA) altitude is the atmospheric pressure reduced by half?",
    "feedback": "18000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to perceive colour vision, it is necessary:\n\n-1 : for there to be considerable amount of light (ambient luminosity)\n-2 : at night to look at the point to be observed at an angle of 15°\n-3 : to allow the eye a period of time to get used to the light\n-4 : to avoid white light",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a final approach under bad weather conditions, you feel dizzy,  get tingling sensations in your hands and a rapid heart rate. \nThese symptoms could indicate:",
    "feedback": "hyperventilation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Is it possible to suffer from Aerodontalgia in the descent?",
    "feedback": "No"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which symptom does not belong to the following list:",
    "feedback": "leans"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight is made in severe weather with the following flight crew composition: The newly upgraded Captain has a total flight time of 5200 hrs, most of which is on the type currently flown. His Copilot, who has recently joined the company, has a total flight time of 15000 hrs. Previously he has been flying similar aircraft types. The Copilot is currently Pilot Flying (PF), the Captain is Pilot Monitoring (PM). On final approach, the DH is passed and sufficient visual contact cannot be made. The Copilot continues the approach with the words \"I will make it\", the Captain does not react.\nWhich statement is correct according to crew composition?",
    "feedback": "A mismatch of role and status occurred"
  },
  {
    "question": "The use of a checklist should be carried out in such a way that:",
    "feedback": "Their use is not simultaneous with other actions"
  },
  {
    "question": "During sustained positive G-forces the order of symptoms you can expect is:",
    "feedback": "tunnel vision,  grey out, black-out and unconsciousness."
  },
  {
    "question": "In an abnormal situation the pilot has an apparently correct explanation for the problem. The chance that he/she now ignores or devalues other relevant information, not fitting into his/her mental picture is:",
    "feedback": "increasing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Barotrauma of the middle ear most likely will occur",
    "feedback": "when descending rapidly"
  },
  {
    "question": "The fovea centralis is",
    "feedback": "the area of best day vision and no night vision at all"
  },
  {
    "question": "The purpose of action plans which are implemented during briefings is to:",
    "feedback": "initiate procedures and reactions for situations that are most likely, risky or difficult during the flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "An ideal professional pilot is in his/her behaviour:",
    "feedback": "both person and goal oriented"
  },
  {
    "question": "When accelerating in level flight  we could experience the sensation of a",
    "feedback": "climb"
  },
  {
    "question": "Healthy people are usually capable to compensate for a lack of oxygen up to",
    "feedback": "10.000 - 12.000feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about long-term memory are correct?\n\n-1: Information is stored there in the form of descriptive, rule-based and schematic knowledge.\n-2: The period of time for which information is retained is limited by the frequency with which this same information is used.\n-3: It processes information quickly and has an effective mode of access in real time.\n-4: Pre-activation of necessary knowledge will allow for a reduction in access time.",
    "feedback": "1 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "On ascent the gases in the digestive tract will",
    "feedback": "expand"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a physiological stressor?",
    "feedback": "A stimulous that produces a change in any of the homeostatic mechanisms of the body"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is dysbarism?",
    "feedback": "Dysbarism refers to the various medical problems caused by gas expansion induced by decreased barometric pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Organisational factors which affect or may have some influence on human error are:\n\n1) malfunction of technical systems\n2) fuel-saving policies\n3) rostering\n4) weather phenomena\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the \"critical threshold\" at which a pilot not using oxygen reaches the critical or lethal zone? It starts at:",
    "feedback": "22000 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component(s) is/are transporting the oxygen in the blood?",
    "feedback": "Hemoglobin in the red blood cells."
  },
  {
    "question": "Pulse rate is influenced by the following factors: 1. Adrenalin 2. Cortisol 3. Physical exercise. 4. Glucose concentration in the blood",
    "feedback": "1,2,3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cabin pressure in airline operation is",
    "feedback": "normally not exceeding 6 000 to 8 000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n  \n1. Smokers have a greater chance of suffering from coronary heart disease \n2. Smoking tobacco will raise the individual's physiological altitude during flight\n3. Smokers have a greater chance for lung cancer",
    "feedback": "1,2 and 3 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the pilot of an aircraft approaches a runway that is wider than normal, one of the possible consequences could be that:",
    "feedback": "The aircraft would touch down after he expects to"
  },
  {
    "question": "A rather prudent Commander is flying towards the destination airport with an inexperienced Copilot known to be an excellent glider pilot. They receive an ATIS announcing CB with associated severe turbulence and windshear. The Commander summarises: \"We are almost at our crosswind limit; if you can see the runway, then we can make it\". The Copilot knows that the Commander is highly experienced in poor-weather flying. He perceives flashing light, believing that they could be the runway and, despite an intitial uneasy feeling in his stomach, decides to make an approach to land.\nThis scenario is an example of:",
    "feedback": "Risky shift; the tendency of both pilots to take more risk than any of them would on his/her own"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a crew made up of members from a closed culture, the commander makes a decision that the copilot does not agree with. What will most likely happen?",
    "feedback": "The copilot will not speak up but act as the captain orders her/him to do"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of increasing altitude on the total pressure and partial pressure of the main gases in the atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "The total pressure will decrease and the partial pressures will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"The Bends\" as a symptom of decompression sickness consists of:",
    "feedback": "pain in the joints"
  },
  {
    "question": "Incapacitation is most dangerous when it is :",
    "feedback": "insinuating"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flights immediately after Scuba-diving, using compressed gas, to depths greater than 10 metres:",
    "feedback": "are forbidden"
  },
  {
    "question": "In tropical zones, it is recommended that:",
    "feedback": "cold drinks be taken from sealed containers"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following systems are involved in the appearance of motion sickness ?\n-1 : Hearing\n-2 : The vestibular system\n-3 : Vision\n-4 : The proprioceptive senses \"Seat-of-the-Pants-Sense\"\n-5 : The gastrointestinal system",
    "feedback": "2,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following errors occur at rules-based level ?\n1.Omission\n2.The application of a poor rule\n3. Attentional capture\n4. The poor application of a good rule",
    "feedback": "2,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "When accelerating forward  the otoliths in the utriculus/sacculus will",
    "feedback": "give the illusion of climbing (body tilting backwards, nose of the a/c going up)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Law that governs oxygen diffusion at the alveoli is:",
    "feedback": "Fick's Law"
  },
  {
    "question": "The momentum of gas exchange in respiration is",
    "feedback": "dependent on the pressure gradient between the participating gases during respiration"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a decompression at high altitude",
    "feedback": "nitrogen gas bubbles can be released in the body fluids causing gas embolism, bends and chokes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The symptoms of hypoxia include:",
    "feedback": "Visual disturbances, lack of concentration, euphoria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the Threat and Error Management (TEM) model. Which of the following is an example of an undesired aircraft state (undesired flight situation) resulting from aircraft handling?",
    "feedback": "Exceeding ATC speed restrictions during an approach"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following statements are true except",
    "feedback": "pulmonary veins contain venous blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following list are symptoms of fatigue?\n\n1) Diminished accommodation\n2) Slowed reactions\n3) Long-term memory access problems\n4) Being over-talkative\n5) Diminished motor skills",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Improvement of human reliability should entail:",
    "feedback": "an effort to understand the causes and find means of recovery for errors committed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Personality is based on:\n\n1. Heredity\n2. Childhood environment\n3. Upbringing\n4. Past experience\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1,2,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following can be classified as a latent threat to flight crew?",
    "feedback": "An equipment design issue"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main limitation of the long-term memory is:",
    "feedback": "unless information is accessed from time to time, retrieval of information can be difficult."
  },
  {
    "question": "The Autonomic Nervous System (ANS) regulates:",
    "feedback": "sweating, arterial pressure, body temperature and the General Adaption Syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "The barometric pressure has dropped to 1/2 of the pressure at sea level at",
    "feedback": "18 000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements summarises the impact that motivation may have on attention ?",
    "feedback": "It increases the mobilisation of energy and thus facilitates the quality of alertness and attention"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following describes good pre-planning and anticipation?\n1) On conducting a twin engine aircraft pre-flight the commander notices an oil leak but decides not to have a maintenance engineer look at it\n2) There is a full load of passengers and fuel. The flight is to depart at midday. The temperature is slightly higher than forecast. The Commander re-does the performance calculations and decides to delay the departure\n3) During a VFR flight, approaching high ground, the cloud base is lower than forecast. There is insufficient fuel to divert around and the flight must remain VFR. The Commander decides to turn back.",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the TEM model, what are the effective countermeasures used to detect and manage foreseeable threats?",
    "feedback": "Briefings and situational awareness"
  },
  {
    "question": "Nonverbal communication",
    "feedback": "supports verbal communication"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pilots need to keep hydrated. Water helps the body to....",
    "feedback": "absorb nutrients"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following list are advantages of teamwork?\n\n1) Personality clashes\n2) Workload is reduced by sharing\n3) Work stress should be reduced\n4) Conformity\n5) A decision arrived at by a group is likely to be better quality than that derived by an individual",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Motivation is an important attribute which contributes to flight safety.\n\nWhich of the following statements is correct with regards to motivation?",
    "feedback": "Excessive motivation leads to stress which adversely affects performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main limit(s) of long-term memory is (are):",
    "feedback": "Data retrieval as a result from a loss of access to the stored information"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to decompression sickness associated with flight, we know that :",
    "feedback": "age, obesity and scuba diving are risk factors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n-1: Scuba diving may be practiced without restriction\n-2: Many medicines have effects which are incompatible with flight safety\n-3: An adequate amount of fluid should be drunk when flying\n-4: Alcohol has no effect on the inner ear",
    "feedback": "2 and 3 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot did not take enough fuel with him. However, he landed at the time planned with fuel and no event occurred. The Operator decided to tell him to stay off duty for one week as a result of what he did. What type of culture does the Operator follow?",
    "feedback": "Just culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "The resistance phase of stress reaction is characterized by:\n\n-1 : activation of the autonomic nervous system (ANS).\n-2 : testosterone secretion which enables fats to be converted into sugar.\n-3 : a sudden fall in stress resistance.\n-4 : the appearance of psychosomatic disorders when lasting over a prolonged time.\n\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following operations are performed more effectively by automatic systems than by people ?\n1. Waiting for an infrequent phenomenon\n2. Long term controlling of a set value (e.g holding of trajectory) \n3. Monitoring to ensure that certain values are not exceeded (e.g    holding of flight path)     \n4. Qualitative decision-making",
    "feedback": "1,2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What distinguishes status from role ?",
    "feedback": "While role defines- via behaviour- the functions that must be performed by individuals, status defines the enjoyment of a hierarchical position and its recognition by the group"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main characteristics of active errors ?\nThey :\n1. are detectable only with difficulty by first-line operators\n2. have rapid and direct consequences on the action in progress\n3. are down to first-line operators\n4. have an impact on the overall action whose timing may be affected significantly",
    "feedback": "2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option correctly lists, from the items below, the main features of latent errors? They:\n1) remain undetected in the system for a certain length of time.2) may only manifest themselves under certain conditions. 3) are quickly detectable by the front-line operator whose mental schemas on the instantaneous situation filter out formal errors.4) lull the pilots into a false sense of security.",
    "feedback": "1,2 and 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "When considering the eating habits of pilots:",
    "feedback": "breakfast should bring about 25% of the daily calorie intake"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a hazardous attitude?",
    "feedback": "Domination"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a climb, we can observe the following with regard to the partial oxygen pressure :",
    "feedback": "an identical decrease to that for atmospheric pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Fatigue can decrease the performance of flight crew. Short-term fatigue can be caused by (1) ......, chronic fatigue can be caused by (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) lack of sleep, (2) stress at home or work"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the Threat and Error Management (TEM), from the perspective of the flight crew, which of the following options is a latent organisational threat?",
    "feedback": "Operational pressure resulting from delays, late arrivals, equipment changes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whilst flying a coordinated turn, most of your activity is",
    "feedback": "skill-based behaviour"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the following options the one that lists only monocular depth cues:",
    "feedback": "Obscuration, texture, atmospheric perspective"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cognitive Coping is associated with:",
    "feedback": "ignoring or rationalising the stress factor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following promotes safety culture in a company?",
    "feedback": "Upper levels of management provide required resources"
  },
  {
    "question": "Glaucoma is due to:",
    "feedback": "increase in pressure of the liquid within the eye"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to central vision, which of the following statements are correct?\n\n-1: It is due to the functioning of rods\n-2: It enables details, colours and movement to be seen\n-3: Its very active both during the day and at night\n-4: It represents a zone where about 150.000 cones per mm are located to give high resolution capacity",
    "feedback": "2,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by the term 'followership'?",
    "feedback": "The ability of an individual to effectively support a recognised leader by being a good team player"
  },
  {
    "question": "You suffered a rapid decompression without the appearance of any decompression sickness symptoms.\n\nWhat should you do before flying?",
    "feedback": "seek prompt aeromedical advice"
  },
  {
    "question": "Medical conditions such as high blood pressure, coronary problems and diabetes are associated with:",
    "feedback": "obesity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements in regard to motivation is correct?",
    "feedback": "Extremely high motivation in combination with excessive stress will limit attention management capabilities"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which answer only describes sub-categories of threats according to the TEM concept?",
    "feedback": "Organization, environment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct statement from the ones below:",
    "feedback": "Smoking reduces the oxygen transport capacity of the cardiovascular system"
  },
  {
    "question": "The individual's personality:",
    "feedback": "refers to unique psychological characteristics"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Short-term memory is affected by interruptions"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is performing a landing and on short final the mandatory airspeed and heights are not kept. During debriefing, his/her Commander pointed out that he/she did not follow the operating standards. The pilot roughly said that he/she is a good pilot and is very good at flying.\nWhat kind of attitude is this?",
    "feedback": "Macho"
  },
  {
    "question": "Having a serious cold, you are going to fly. What can you expect?",
    "feedback": "pain in the sinuses"
  },
  {
    "question": "The organ which metabolises alcohol from the body is the:",
    "feedback": "liver"
  },
  {
    "question": "If man is compared with a computer, it can be said that man :",
    "feedback": "has more effective means of action (output) and is above all capable of considerable synergy"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to short-term memory, we can say that :",
    "feedback": "it is made up of everyday information for immediate use, and is limited in its capacity for storing and retaining data"
  },
  {
    "question": "Symptoms of stress may include:\n1) Depression or anxiety\n2) Low blood pressure\n3) Sleep disturbances\n4) Abuse of psychoactive substances\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to the sleep/wake cycle of \"credit\" and \"debit\" system, 6 hours sleep will put the body in credit by:",
    "feedback": "12 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the cockpit, one pilot is from Ireland and another from the United States. They both therefore speak English natively. How will the use of social language instead of professional language affect their performance during an emergency situation?",
    "feedback": "The use of social language could interrupt communications during an emergency"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hearing tests are carried out during pilot medicals to:",
    "feedback": "detect early signs of deafness"
  },
  {
    "question": "What can be said concerning the following two statements?\n\n1) Euphoria can be a symptom of hypoxia\n2) Someone in an euphoric condition is more prone to error",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are both correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The human performance is generally",
    "feedback": "better when relaxed, independent of the period of day"
  },
  {
    "question": "A private pilot is waiting for a delayed passenger. When they finally depart, the pilot decides to do a checklist from memory instead of actually reading it. In flight, he notices that he has missed an item from the checklist.\nWhat is this an example of?",
    "feedback": "A violation, followed by a lapse"
  },
  {
    "question": "The resistance phase of stress:",
    "feedback": "allows fats to be transformed into sugars, thereby prolonging the mobilization of energy in the body"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an organization where a good safety culture is predominant, the accountability lies with the:",
    "feedback": "Management"
  },
  {
    "question": "To completely eliminate human errors is not possible. Error Management is the term used for the endeavours to reduce human error and its impact. Which of the following are known error-management strategies?",
    "feedback": "Error prevention, error reduction, error detection, error recovery, and error tolerance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Learning to fly naturally induces stress in a student pilot because he is lacking experience. Manifestations of this type of stress are:\n\n1. nervousness and chanellized attention\n2. being rough at the controls\n3. smoke and drink much more alcohol than usual\n4. airsickness, lack of sleep",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a complex task high levels of arousal",
    "feedback": "narrow the span of attention"
  },
  {
    "question": "Habits and routine can influence decision-making in a way that:",
    "feedback": "a tendency to select the most familiar solution first and foremost, sometimes to the detriment of achieving the best possible result"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Commander is taxiing to the holding point. He stops and does his checklist. When the tower calls him to continue taxiing, he does not comply with the instruction.\nThis is an example of ......",
    "feedback": "blinkered concentration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stress is:",
    "feedback": "a mechanism by which an individual can respond to situations which he/she may have to face"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mental training, mental rehearsal of cognitive pretraining is called the inner, ideomotor simulation of actions.",
    "feedback": "It is most important for the acquisition of complex perceptual motor skills"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following describe(s) situations where \"selective attention\" and \"divided attention\" are employed?\n1) During take-off, the Pilot Monitoring and Pilot Flying select relevant information, dividing the workloads according to their specific duties2) ATC instructs the pilot to climb to 2500 ft on QNH 1011. The pilot uses selective attention to listen to the radio, and selective and divided attention to check the altimeter settings and aircraft level3) A pilot training on basic instrument flying manoeuvres focuses attention on the basic instruments and divides attention in cross-checking their indications while controlling the aircraft",
    "feedback": "2. 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by \"risky shift\"?",
    "feedback": "the tendency for a group to accept a higher degree of risk then any individual in the group"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which are the two most important attributes for a positive leadership style?\n1) dominant behaviour\n2) examplary role-behaviour\n3) mastery of communication skills\n4)\"Laissez-faire\" behaviour",
    "feedback": "2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "With a heart rate of 72 beats per minute and a stroke volume of 70 ml the cardial output   is about:",
    "feedback": "5 liters/min"
  },
  {
    "question": "The occurrence of pain in the joints (bends) during decompression can be explained by the principle that:",
    "feedback": "the quantity of a gas dissolved in a fluid is proportional to the pressure of that gas above the fluid (Henry's Law)"
  },
  {
    "question": "TUC at 25'000 ft at rest is about",
    "feedback": "4 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "During poor weather conditions a pilot should fly with reference to instruments because:",
    "feedback": "perception of distance and speed is difficult in an environment of low contrast"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying a non-pressurised light aircraft at 9000 feet your passenger develops blue lips:",
    "feedback": "assuming he is suffering from hypoxia you reduce altitude and supply him with oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a multi-crew, highly automated flight deck. What is correct about crew call-outs?",
    "feedback": "They are used to increase mode awareness"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot experiences an acute fatigue when/with (1) ...... and a chronic fatigue when (2) ...... .",
    "feedback": "(1) lack of sleep, (2) stressed at home or at job"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pilot of a single-pilot aircraft received a wind shear warning in the cockpit during final approach. Incorrectly, the pilot decides to continue the approach. Incident investigation states that the pilot did not know about the procedure dictating a go-around. It is a human error and in the context of the SHELL model, it is the combination of \"Liveware\", representing the pilot, and ......",
    "feedback": "software, representing the procedures"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is 1.7 metres tall and weighs 57kgs. She is:",
    "feedback": "Normal"
  },
  {
    "question": "How long does it take to develop full night vision adaption?",
    "feedback": "30 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypoxia can also be caused by",
    "feedback": "a lack of red blood cells in the blood or decreased ability of the hemoglobin to transport oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "What optimises crew co-operation?\n\n1. Sharing and common task\n2. Confidence in each others capability\n3. Precise definition of functions associated with each crew members role",
    "feedback": "1,2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the correct remedial action if symptoms of hyperventilation occur at an altitude where hypoxia is not a consideration?",
    "feedback": "decrease rate and depth of breathing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The primary symptom of decompression sickness/illness is:",
    "feedback": "the bends"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characterises a good leader?",
    "feedback": "The situation, the goals and composition of the group."
  },
  {
    "question": "Presbyopia is:",
    "feedback": "far sightedness linked with age"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is automation mode awareness?",
    "feedback": "Being aware of the active mode(s) and understanding the corresponding actions and responses is necessary for proper use of the automated system."
  },
  {
    "question": "A go-around has already been initiated, when ATC delivers a long message, changing the missed approach procedure. What is correct regarding the pilots' attention and the risks associated with the above situation?",
    "feedback": "The attention of the Pilot Not Flying (PNF) could be diverted from the task of monitoring the aircraft parameters, which can lead to a loss of awareness of the aircraft's state"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is dengue fever transmitted?",
    "feedback": "By several species of mosquitos during daytime"
  },
  {
    "question": "You climb from 0 to 50.000 ft and measure the decrease of the pressure per 5.000 ft. The absolute difference in barometric pressure is greatest between :",
    "feedback": "0 and 5.000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Internal respiration:",
    "feedback": "is a metabolic process that takes place inside the cells during which oxygen is used and carbon dioxide produced"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regards to high workload situations on the flight deck, visual effects such as system messages ......",
    "feedback": "can interrupt the flow of work"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following combination of factors may be associated with the development of alcoholism?\n1) Genetics2) Access to cheap alcohol3) Race4) Socio-cultural background",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following could a pilot experience when he is hyperventilating?\n1. Dizziness\n2. Muscular spasms\n3. Visual disturbances\n4. Cyanosis",
    "feedback": "1,2 and 3 are correct, 4 is false"
  },
  {
    "question": "The organ that transfers vibrations to nerve impulses in your ear is called",
    "feedback": "the cochlea"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the following list you will find several symptoms listed for  hypoxia and carbon monoxide poisoning. \nPlease mark those referring to carbon monoxide poisoning.",
    "feedback": "Headache, increasing nausea, dizziness."
  },
  {
    "question": "Disagreements are a fact of life. However, when a disagreement escalates into a conflict on the flight deck then safety is seriously compromised. Which of the following statements best describes the process of escalation in human conflict?",
    "feedback": "An initial tension or verbal dispute among opposing parties escalates to a voicing of hostile threat and may or may not involve violence"
  },
  {
    "question": "When stopping the rotation of a spin we have the sensation",
    "feedback": "that we are starting a spin into the opposite direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are transporting a passenger who has to be at a certain destination for a meeting. The weather forecast at destination tends to be much worse than expected, so you consider to divert. The businessman offers you money, if you manage to land there at any case. \nWhat is your appropriate way of action? You will ......",
    "feedback": "decide to divert if you think it is necessary"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to the relationship between arousal and performance, the highest level of performance is achieved when the arousal level is:",
    "feedback": "optimum"
  },
  {
    "question": "The biological reaction to stress is identical regardless of the cause of stress. This mechanism occurs in three phases and is referred to, by Selye, as the \"General Adaptation Syndrome\". \nThe sequence is:",
    "feedback": "alarm phase - resistance phase - exhaustion phase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Conflicts in cockpit are a serious threat to flight safety. Conflict escalation is marked by ......",
    "feedback": "increasing verbal aggression and threats, and may or may not lead to violence"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of in-flight stress, one should :",
    "feedback": "use all available resources of the crew"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot who is hyperventilating for a prolonged period of time may even get unconscious. \nHyperventilation is likely to occur, when:",
    "feedback": "the pilot is emotionally aroused"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a pilot is staring at an isolated stationary light for several seconds in the dark he might get the illusion that:",
    "feedback": "the light is moving"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal rate of breathing is",
    "feedback": "12 to 16 cycles a minute"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can optimum arousal and vigilance be obtained?",
    "feedback": "Experts believe that arousal and performance are related by an inverted V-shaped curve. Deep sleep is at one end, extreme panic the other. Both result in poor performance. Optimum arousal and vigilance are obtained at the mid-point between the two."
  },
  {
    "question": "Barodontalgia",
    "feedback": "arises especially with irritations of the sensitive tissues close to the root of a tooth"
  },
  {
    "question": "You fly VFR from your home base (runway width 27 m), to an international airport (runway width 45 m). On reaching your destination there is a risk of performing a:",
    "feedback": "high approach with overshoot"
  },
  {
    "question": "The procedure to be followed in the event of decompression when flying above 10,000 ft must :",
    "feedback": "allow for the rapid supply of oxygen in order to prevent the pilot becoming hypoxic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypoxic hypoxia may be caused by:\n\n1) climbing to a high altitude without using additional oxygen\n2) malfuction in the oxygen supply system\n3) loss of cabin pressurisation at high altitude\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Environmental sources of stress in the cockpit could be:\n\n1) noise and vibration\n2) acceleration\n3) radiation\n4) extreme temperature\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct answers is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Somatogravic illusion gives the pilot a false impression of:",
    "feedback": "climbing or descending"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alcohol metabolism (elimination rate)",
    "feedback": "is approx. 0.015% per hour and cannot be expedited"
  },
  {
    "question": "The behaviour of a group can be affected by a number of factors including:",
    "feedback": "persuasion, conformity, compliance and obedience"
  },
  {
    "question": "When does the blind spot on the retina become significant for a pilot?",
    "feedback": "If another aircraft is on a converging course and the pilot's field of view is restricted on one side, the pilot might fail to see the other aircraft if it is positioned in the blind spot of the unobstructed eye"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which altitude is it necessary to breathe 100 % oxygen under pressure after a rapid decompression?",
    "feedback": "Approximately 40 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Decisions made by pilots in a cockpit:",
    "feedback": "remain valid for a limited time only"
  },
  {
    "question": "Motivation, crew-climate and confirmation bias are factors that:",
    "feedback": "can influence the situational awareness"
  },
  {
    "question": "The percentage of oxygen in the troposphere in dry air:",
    "feedback": "is independent of altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "An excessive need for safety",
    "feedback": "hampers severely the way of pilot decision making"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypoxia can be prevented when the pilot",
    "feedback": "is using additional oxygen when flying above 10.000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Phobic states or obsessional disorders will:",
    "feedback": "may require successful treatment before flying may be permitted"
  },
  {
    "question": "Galactic radiation is:",
    "feedback": "steady and reasonably predictable."
  },
  {
    "question": "The most significant item of technical equipment introduced in the 1980s and 1990s which has contributed to a reduction in accidents is:",
    "feedback": "GPWS"
  },
  {
    "question": "A typical example of an undesired aircraft state according to the TEM model would be:",
    "feedback": "Flying too fast and/or too high during an approach"
  },
  {
    "question": "From the following options, select an example of self-discipline of flight crew members which is important to flight safety:",
    "feedback": "Strictly adhering to standard operating procedures as a means of greatly reducing the risk of committing an error or omission"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning conflicts is correct ?",
    "feedback": "Conflict management involves the participation of all involved parties in finding an acceptable collective solution"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypoxia can affect night vision",
    "feedback": "at approximately 5000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Illusions of interpretation (cognitive illusions)  are :",
    "feedback": "associated with the task of mental construction of the environment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Adaptation to light",
    "feedback": "is done in both eyes separately"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft departs for a VFR flight. The route involves a descent into mountainous terrain. While en-route, an instrument fails, which makes it more difficult to fly without visual reference, as the weather deteriorates to IMC. The pilot continues to attempt to fly under VFR but crashes into the mountains.\nWhat type of error best characterizes this accident scenario?",
    "feedback": "Error chain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Decompression sickness/illness is characterized by:",
    "feedback": "over-saturated nitrogen gas molecules in the body tissues"
  },
  {
    "question": "The exchange of gases between the alveoli and the blood is due to:",
    "feedback": "diffusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dengue fever:",
    "feedback": "is spread by mosquitoes that are active during day time"
  },
  {
    "question": "A selective attentional mechanism is required",
    "feedback": "because of the limited capacity of the central decision maker and working memory"
  },
  {
    "question": "A person is anaemic when a deficiency exists of:",
    "feedback": "Haemoglobin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Human error rates during the performance of a simple and repetitive task can normally be expected to be approximately:",
    "feedback": "1 in 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is hypoxia ?",
    "feedback": "Any condition where the oxygen concentration of the body is below normal limits or where the oxygen available to the body cannot be used due to some pathological condition"
  },
  {
    "question": "Exchange of gases between the body and the environment takes place at the:",
    "feedback": "lungs"
  },
  {
    "question": "In airline operations decompression sickness symptoms",
    "feedback": "may develop after a decompression from 7000 FT cabin pressure altitude to 30000 FT flight altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "CRM (Crew Resource Management) training is:",
    "feedback": "intended to develop effectiveness of crew performance by improving attitudes towards flight safety and human relationship management"
  },
  {
    "question": "A sloping cloud formation, an obscured horizon and a dark scene spread with ground lights and stars can create an illusion\nknown as:",
    "feedback": "False horizon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct as regards factors that influence decision making?\n1) People tend to conform to opinions expressed by a majority within the group they belong to.2) People always keep the future decisions in line with those their superiors have made in the past3) People more easily tend to select data which meet their expectations4) People rarely base decisions on their personal preferences but rather on rational information",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Anxiety and fear can cause",
    "feedback": "hyperventilation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Among the factors which can cause illusions while taxiing are:",
    "feedback": "relative movement and cockpit height above the ground."
  },
  {
    "question": "The relationship between arousal and flying performance is depicted in figure:",
    "feedback": "B"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can the process of learning be enhanced?",
    "feedback": "By reinforcing successful performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by metabolism?",
    "feedback": "The generation and utilisation of energy by the body's cells and tissues"
  },
  {
    "question": "Records of radiation are normally kept for flights above:",
    "feedback": "49000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Acute stress quickly leads to",
    "feedback": "the mobilization of resources required to cope with the stressor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Resignation is a dangerous attitude, because it:",
    "feedback": "Lowers the self-confidence of the affected flight crew member"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following strategies is most appropriate to delay the onset of drowsiness (hypovigilance), especially on long-range flights or when lying across multiple time zones?",
    "feedback": "Engage in social conversation and alternate between periods of activity and relaxation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true regarding sleep?    \n\n1)  Metabolic rate falls    \n2)  Arterial blood pressure falls   \n3)  The pulse rate decreases    \n4)  The sensitivity level of the senses is increased",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Although we have a field of vision of more than 180° it is important during flight to use the scanning technique, because",
    "feedback": "only in the foveal area resolution is good enough to see an object clearly"
  },
  {
    "question": "Oxygen transport to the tissues:",
    "feedback": "depends on haemoglobin level and blood flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "A typical example of an environmental threat according to the TEM model would be:",
    "feedback": "Missing or confusing markings of taxiways and runways"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the two inputs to a simple model of stress?",
    "feedback": "The perceived demand of the task to the pilot and the pilot's perceived ability to complete the task"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following maneuvers may be used to treat a hyperventilation except",
    "feedback": "increasing rate and depth of breathing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name a potential threat of standard operating procedures (SOPs):",
    "feedback": "Misunderstandings can result if pilots change to a new employer"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the pre-flight phase in the cockpit the captain notices that his copilot on the one hand is rather inexperienced and insecure but on the other hand highly motivated. \n\nWhich kind of leadership behaviour is most likely inappropriate?",
    "feedback": "The captain lets the copilot fly and observes his behaviour without any comments"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following describes an external error generated in the flight crew compartment due to poor ergonomics?",
    "feedback": "Incorrect selection of the speed brake instead of flaps due to the proximity and similar design of the levers"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying through a thunderstorm with lightning you can protect yourself from flash blindness by:\n\na) turning up the intensity of cockpit lights\nb) looking inside the cockpit\nc) wearing sunglasses\nd) using face blinds or face curtains when installed",
    "feedback": "a), b), c) and d) are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What communication practice involves soliciting the ideas and opinions of all group memebers and encouraging any expressions of doubt as a way of preventing or solving conflict?",
    "feedback": "Active listening"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you approach an airfield VFR at a prescribed altitude, exactly following the approach procedure, and you encounter no inexpected or new problems you show:",
    "feedback": "skill-based behaviour"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sound is measured in:",
    "feedback": "dB"
  },
  {
    "question": "A system is all the more reliable if it offers good detectability. The latter is the result of:\n-1 : tolerance of the various systems to errors.\n-2 : the sum of the automatic monitoring, detection and warning facilities.\n-3 : the reliability of the Man-Man and Man-Machine links.\n-4 : the alerting capability of the Man-Machine interface.\n\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2 and 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The total pressure of a mixture of gases is equal to the sum of the partial pressures of the gases which compose the mixture corresponds to:",
    "feedback": "Dalton´s law"
  },
  {
    "question": "A long-term method of stress management must take into consideration:",
    "feedback": "The fact that stress is cumulative and it is difficult to recognise"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an example of an external error caused due to economical reasons?",
    "feedback": "Pilots accepting an ATC clearance, providing a short cut. Upon arrival, they realise that they are too high and unstable on the approach"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cosmic radiation:",
    "feedback": "is at its strongest at very high altitudes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of the following statements concerning the effects of circadian rhythms on performance, we know that :",
    "feedback": "Sensorimotor performance is better in the evening whereas intellectual performance is better in the morning"
  },
  {
    "question": "The consumption of medicines or other substances may have consequences on qualification to fly for the following reasons:\n\n1. The disease requiring a treatment may be cause for disqualification.\n2. Flight conditions may modify the reactions of the body to a treatment.\n3. Drugs may cause adverse side effects impairing flight safety.\n4. The effects of medicine do not necessarily immediately disappear when the treatment is stopped.",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "When you stare at a single light against the dark (f.e. an isolated star) you will find the light appears to move after some time. This phenomenon is called:",
    "feedback": "autokinetic phenomenon"
  },
  {
    "question": "The proprioceptors do not orient an individual to his/her surroundings, but inform him/her of:",
    "feedback": "the relative motion and relative position of his body parts"
  },
  {
    "question": "How should you scan for other traffic at night?",
    "feedback": "look to the side of the object and scan slowly"
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of hypoxia, which occurs at altitude is explained by:",
    "feedback": "Dalton´s law"
  },
  {
    "question": "Illusions that pilots experience in conditions of fog or mist are that:",
    "feedback": "Objects appear further away than they really are and can lead to steep approaches"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a cabin pressure loss in approximately 35 000 FT the TUC (Time of Useful Consciousness) will be approximately:",
    "feedback": "30 -90 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"Leans\" or Somatogyral illusion can be caused by:",
    "feedback": "reducing bank following a prolonged turn"
  },
  {
    "question": "Threat and Error Management (TEM) is an overarching safety concept regarding aviation operations and human performance. Within the TEM framework, and according to ICAO Annex 1 on Personnel Licensing, error is defined as ......",
    "feedback": "an action or inaction by an operational person that leads to deviations from organisational or the operational person's intentions or expectations"
  },
  {
    "question": "Many pilots think up systems to deal with affairs so they don't have to think up every time what they have to do.",
    "feedback": "this has to be positively appreciated for it increases consistency in action"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following may occur during gradual depressurisation between 12,000 and 18,000 ft :",
    "feedback": "a loss of coordination associated with fatigue and headache"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the following list the main objectives of CRM and MCC training:\n1) Communication2) PF and PM concept3) Leadership4) Cross-check and monitoring5) Situational awareness6) Standard operating procedures7) Checklists",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a motor programme with respect to completing a task?",
    "feedback": "A behavioural sub-routine which once running does not require conscious thought"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying immediately after SCUBA diving involves the risk of getting:",
    "feedback": "decompression sickness without having a decompression"
  },
  {
    "question": "The time between inadequate oxygen supply and incapacitation is called TUC (Time of Useful Consciousness). It",
    "feedback": "varies individually and depends on cabin pressure altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about alcohol is true?",
    "feedback": "Alcohol will lower the tolerance for hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Oxygen, combined with hemoglobin in blood is transported by",
    "feedback": "red blood cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "The expression \"when perception matches reality\" describes:",
    "feedback": "situational awareness"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cohesion is a major advantage in times of:",
    "feedback": "difficulty"
  },
  {
    "question": "When assessing an individual's risk in developing coronary artery disease, the following factors may contribute:\n1.obesity\n2.distress\n3.smoking\n4.family history",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Disturbances of pressure equalization in air-filled cavities of the head (nose, ear etc.) are called:",
    "feedback": "barotrauma"
  },
  {
    "question": "The 'Black hole' phenomenon occurs during approaches at  night and over water, jungle or desert. When the pilot is lacking of visual cues other than those of the aerodrome there is an illusion of",
    "feedback": "being too high and too far away, dropping low and landing short"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lowest level of Maslow's Model of the Hierarchy of Human Needs is:",
    "feedback": "physiological needs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Fixation or tunnel vision is primarily to be expected when :",
    "feedback": "stress is high"
  },
  {
    "question": "Error tolerance, which in an error management strategy, aims at making....",
    "feedback": "the system better able to sustain itself despite error, e.g. by minimising the consequences of errors"
  },
  {
    "question": "The semicircular canals detect",
    "feedback": "angular accelerations"
  },
  {
    "question": "After two years flying on one aircraft type, a pilot has just completed a type rating course for a new aircraft. He/she is on his/her first flight on the new type as Copilot.\nWhich option is correct as regards following the SOPs on the new type?",
    "feedback": "There is a higher risk of making errors such as slips and lapses, if the new aircraft type is very similar to the one previously flown"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is flying through bad weather and tries to remember the temperature below which he/she has to be aware of icing. This value has been told to him/her a week ago in his/her company's winter operations course.\nWhat type(s) of memory were involved in the process of saving and recalling that information?",
    "feedback": "All memory types. The information is perceived while in the sensory memory, transferred to the short-term memory and evaluated, and then moved to the long-term memory to keep it"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main purpose of lumbar support is to:",
    "feedback": "Produce an even pressure on the discs by allowing the lower spine to curve naturally"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying from London to Oslo as commander. One of your passengers suffers a heart attack during flight, and the situation is life threatening for him. You evaluate the situation, and decide to divert to Amsterdam. What type of behaviour is this, according to Jens Rasmussen?",
    "feedback": "Knowledge-based behaviour"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is a typical \"primary group\"?",
    "feedback": "A family, gathered to celebrate mother's 40th birthday"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what altitude  (breathing 100% oxygen without pressure) could symptoms of hypoxia be expected?",
    "feedback": "Approximately 38 - 40 000 ft."
  },
  {
    "question": "The operator of an aircraft takes disciplinary action against the captain of a flight, claiming that he/she violated established operating procedures by landing with insufficient fuel on board. The captain can plausibly demonstrate that he/she has only made a mistake when documenting the fuel mass in the technical logbook after the flight, while the actual fuel on board after landing was well within the operational limits. The operator decides to suspend the pilot from work for 10 days.\nSelect from the following the correct statement with regard to the operator's safety culture.",
    "feedback": "The operator does not apply the principle of \"just culture\" to foster trust and collaboration. Such an unintended slip should be reported and discussed to prevent their future re-occurrence, it should not be punished"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the relationship between the perceived level of arousal and the difficulty of a task to be completed?",
    "feedback": "At the outset, the level of arousal should be within the optimum range and therefore at a level where performance does not suffer"
  },
  {
    "question": "The changes in atmospheric gas pressure with altitude are:",
    "feedback": "non-linear, with a higher rate of change at lower levels"
  },
  {
    "question": "What may be the origins of representation errors ?\n1. Perception errors\n2. The catering for all available information \n3. Incorrect information from the observed world\n4. The receipt of a bad piece of information",
    "feedback": "1,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Carbon dioxide:",
    "feedback": "is a normal product of internal respiration"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Wicken's theory, the human brain has:",
    "feedback": "different reservoirs of resources depending on whether one is in the information-gathering, information-processing or action phase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Excessive exposure to noise damages:",
    "feedback": "the sensitive membrane in the cochlea"
  },
  {
    "question": "An example of potential conflict between status and role is:",
    "feedback": "a junior ranked captain flying with a senior ranked co-pilot"
  },
  {
    "question": "What could be symptoms of hypoxia (when flying without oxygen) above 12,000 ft?",
    "feedback": "Headache, fatigue, dizziness, lack of coordination"
  },
  {
    "question": "The fovea",
    "feedback": "is an area in which cones predominate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Symptoms of gastrointestinal upset can include:\n1) Halitosis (bad breath)2) Loss of appetite3) Gain of weight4) Heartburn5) Altered perception of taste6) Pressure pain during climb7) Desire for certain food types8) Gastric and duodenal ulcers9) Loss of weight",
    "feedback": "2, 4, 8"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gaseous exchange in the human body depends on:\n1. diffusion gradients between the participating gases\n2. permeable membranes\n3. partial pressure of oxygen in the alveolus air\n4. acid-base balance in the blood",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vibrations within the frequency band of  1/10 to 2 Hertz  are a factor contributing to air-sickness, because they",
    "feedback": "upset  the  vestibular apparatus"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot approaching a runway which is narrower than normal may feel he is at a greater height than he actually is. To compensate he may fly a",
    "feedback": "flatter than normal approach with the tendency to undershoot"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does motivation affect an individual completing a task?",
    "feedback": "Motivation reflects the difference between what an individual can do and what the individual will do"
  },
  {
    "question": "Glaucoma is:",
    "feedback": "high intra-ocular pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is an item of information that is important for a pilot to hold in their working memory during a flight?",
    "feedback": "The 4 digit squawk code assigned by ATC during flight, up to the point when the pilot sets it into the transponder"
  },
  {
    "question": "Using the sleep credit/debit model, 8 hours sleep produces a sleep credit of:",
    "feedback": "16 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "The percentage of oxygen in the air at an altitude of approximately \n34 000 ft is :",
    "feedback": "21%"
  },
  {
    "question": "If during flight a pilot is in a mental condition of \"optimum arousal\" he/she will be:",
    "feedback": "prepared best to cope with a difficult task"
  },
  {
    "question": "The proprioceptive senses (seat-of-the-pants sense) are important  for motor coordination. \nThey",
    "feedback": "are completely unreliable for orientation when flying in IMC"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a training on engine failure during the go-around, the release of hormones, adrenaline and sugars into the blood is a ...... reaction to the increase in stress.",
    "feedback": "physiological"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following beverages or food stuffs are most likely to contain caffeine? 1) Coca Cola 2) Tea 3) Carrots 4) Chocolate  The combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Boyle's law states",
    "feedback": "the volume of a gas is inversely proportional to its pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the conflict resolution process it is important to:\n\n1) realise and to accept the conflict\n2) verbalise mutual expectations\n3) search for common agreements\n4) express one's own viewpoint\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Due to high arousal or overstress, an individual starts to hyperventilate. Cosenquently, the carbon dioxide level in the blood is lowered which results in:",
    "feedback": "Less oxygen to be diffused into the cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following options is an example of an environmental threat in the TEM model?",
    "feedback": "A volcanic eruption on the route of flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "The crew of a business jet have completed the pre-flight checks and are ready to start the engines. The passenger arrives late and the crew complete the start and taxi checks. In order to keep to the original time for take-off the PIC requests an immediate take-off clearance which is granted. To save time, the PIC also completes the pre-take-off checks from memory while taxiing and does not use the checklist. After take-off, the crew realise that the pitot heat (an item on the checklist) had been forgotten.\nWhat types of error are shown in this scenario?",
    "feedback": "The PIC's decision to complete the pre-take-off checks from memory was a violation. As a result, a lapse occurred in the execution, which was failing to check the pitot heat setting"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who in the aviation industry is responsible for flight safety?",
    "feedback": "Everyone involved"
  },
  {
    "question": "When exhaling, the expired air contains:",
    "feedback": "more carbon dioxide than the inspired air"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the major goals in the design of human centred man-machine interface is to make it.....",
    "feedback": "simple and also at the same time make it difficult for a human or automation to make an error"
  },
  {
    "question": "Carbon monoxide poisoning can be treated by:",
    "feedback": "increasing the amount of oxygen being physically dissolved in the blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "Approximately what percentage of all communication is achieved by factors other than words (metacommunications)?",
    "feedback": "80%"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the \"H\" in the SHELL model mean?",
    "feedback": "Hardware"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hyperventilation is:",
    "feedback": "a normal compensatory physiological reaction to a drop in partial oxygen pressure (i.e. when climbing a high mountain)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  sensations does a pilot get, when he is rolling out of a prolonged level turn?",
    "feedback": "Turning into the opposite direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "In terms of flight safety, what fundamental principle governs the balance between manual piloting and automation utilization?",
    "feedback": "Automation when used correctly and with an awareness of its weaknesses and dangers adds to the overall safety of flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "Henry's law states",
    "feedback": "the quantity of a gas dissolved in a liquid is proportional to the partial pressure of the gas"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under what circumstances will a pilot change from automated level to rule-based level ?",
    "feedback": "When detecting, that an automated behaviour will no longer lead to the intended outcome"
  },
  {
    "question": "A barotrauma of the middle ear  is",
    "feedback": "an acute or chronic trauma of the middle ear caused by a difference of pressure on either side of the eardrum"
  },
  {
    "question": "What may the impacts of excessive exposure to radiation (such as solar radiation) be?",
    "feedback": "It may have a detrimental effect on your central nervous system, damage your internal organs, and cause skin cancer"
  },
  {
    "question": "The chemical composition of the earth´s atmosphere (ICAO standard atmosphere) is",
    "feedback": "78 % nitrogen, 21 % oxygen, 0,9 % argon, 0,03 % carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering a typical civil aviation environment, the safety culture is relatively enduring, stable and resistant to change. This statement is:",
    "feedback": "True"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is instructed by ATC to maintain an altitude of 3500 ft, turn onto a heading of 275° and change frequency to 132.425.\nWhy might there be an increased risk for the pilot making an error?",
    "feedback": "Our short-term memory can only hold up to about 7 digits"
  },
  {
    "question": "When consciously breathing fast or hyperventilating due to high arousal or overstress, the carbon dioxide level in the blood is lowered, resulting in:",
    "feedback": "less oxygen to be diffused into the cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Short term memory can already be affected when flying as low as:",
    "feedback": "8000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Our body takes its energy from :\n1:   minerals\n2:   protein\n3:   carbohydrates\n4:   vitamins",
    "feedback": "2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is correct about pre-flight briefings? \nPre-flight briefings should ......",
    "feedback": "be adapted to the specific flight, for the crew to operate effectively"
  },
  {
    "question": "Circadian cycles cause body temperature to change. At approximately what time of day is our temperature at its lowest value?",
    "feedback": "0500"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot may get the illusion of low altitude on approach although the aircraft is on the correct glidepath:",
    "feedback": "when the runway is wider than he is used to"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following occurs in man if the internal body temperature increases to 38°C :",
    "feedback": "impairment of physical and mental performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "An experienced pilot is empoyed by an airline operator on a fixed-term contract as First Officer. The Operator will offer a permanent contract to only one pilot at the end of the year, so the First Officer is really motivated to perform at his/her best.\nThe Commander of the aircraft who flies with the First Officer should be aware that......",
    "feedback": "strong motivation to achieve is a cognitive stressor, and it can negatively affect performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to minimize the effects of crossing more than 3-4 time zones with a layover more than 24 hrs, it is advisable to :\n1. Adapt as quickly as possible to the rhythm of the arrival country\n2. Keep in swing with the rhythm of the departure country for as long as possible\n3. Maintain regular living patterns (waking ,sleeping alternation and regular meal pattern )\n4. Try to sleep as much as possible to overcome negative arousal effects",
    "feedback": "1,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figures: Which best represents the arousal/performance curve?",
    "feedback": "B"
  },
  {
    "question": "Modern aircraft increasingly rely on high levels of cockpit automation and information integration. Which of the following are methods to overcome some of the disadvantages of automation?",
    "feedback": "Practice basic manual flying skills and continually maintain a mental picture of the current situation"
  },
  {
    "question": "An under-confident and self-effacing co-pilot is promoted to captain. It is not uncommon for such a person to have a behavioural pattern which is:",
    "feedback": "aggressive if challenged by another member of the crew"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following concepts relating to human reliability is true?",
    "feedback": "If equipment is designed in such a way that it can be operated wrongly, then sooner or later, it will be"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is hypoxia especially dangerous for pilots flying solo?",
    "feedback": "Since the first signs of hypoxia are generally hard to detect (hypoxia of the brain), the solo pilot may not be able to react in time (i.e. activate his emergency oxygen system)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alcohol,  when taken simultaneously with drugs, may",
    "feedback": "intensify the effects of the drugs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is true about communication on the flight deck during periods of high workload?",
    "feedback": "Side-by-side flight deck seating makes it very difficult for flight crew members to notice each other's body language or actions in periods of high workload"
  },
  {
    "question": "Discussing private matters in the cockpit",
    "feedback": "can improve team spirit"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following correctly describes the basic functions of the different parts of the auditory system after sound waves enter through the outer ear?",
    "feedback": "Sound waves cause the eardrum to vibrate. Ossicles transmit the vibrations to the cochlea, which translates them into electrical impulses. The auditory nerve carries the impulses to the brain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Scanning at night should be performed by:",
    "feedback": "slight eye movements to the side of the object"
  },
  {
    "question": "How would you describe the leadership style of a captain who primarily is interested in a friendly atmosphere within his crew, who is always constructive and encouraging, who usually compromises in interpersonal conflicts, who trusts in the capabilities of his crew-members, and who leaves the crew freedom for own decisions, even if this makes the process more difficult?",
    "feedback": "Low task-orientation and high relationship-orientation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Any prolonged exposure to noise in excess of 85 db can end up in",
    "feedback": "noise induced hearing loss"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which steps within the Aeronautical Decision Making process relate to the Decide Model?",
    "feedback": "Detect, Estimate, Choose, Identify, Do, Evaluate"
  },
  {
    "question": "The human circadian rhythm is based on a cycle of about:",
    "feedback": "24  hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a visual final approach at night, the pilot asks the control tower to dim the runway lights, as he/she realises, that his/her capacity to judge the distance from the runway is diminished. Is that request justified?",
    "feedback": "Yes, because depth perception may be impaired if the rods and cones on the retina are exposed to bright light after dark adaptation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main effects of a lack of sleep on performance ?",
    "feedback": "It increases fatigue, concentration and attention difficulties, the risk of sensory illusions and mood disorders"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by \"groupthink\"?",
    "feedback": "More or less unconscious support of a solution from group member(s)"
  },
  {
    "question": "You don't feel respected by your colleague.\nWhich category of Maslow's Needs has been ignored?",
    "feedback": "Ego needs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Visual perception of depth at close to medium distance is primarily due to",
    "feedback": "binocular vision"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the inverted U-curve, also called the Yerkes-Dodson curve, being on the extreme left side indicates:",
    "feedback": "Sleep"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding alcohol in the human body?",
    "feedback": "Judgement and decision making can be affected even by a small amount of alcohol."
  },
  {
    "question": "A small aircraft has joined the circuit and is on final approach. Code 4202 is set on the transponder and the QNH of 1009 hPa is set on the altimeter. The pilot receives the following message from ATC: \"G-ABCD cleared to land runway 01, wind 350 degrees, 10 knots\".\nWhich option lists the information that the pilot is expected to hold in working memory at this point?",
    "feedback": "The direction (350 degrees) and speed (10 knots) of the wind vector"
  },
  {
    "question": "The capacity of the short-term memory is",
    "feedback": "about 7 items"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal sleep cycle is approximately every .... minutes",
    "feedback": "90"
  },
  {
    "question": "What law(s) governs the oxygen transfer at the alveoli?",
    "feedback": "Gas Diffusion Laws"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Stereotypes\" are preconceptions or prejudices which can lead us to:",
    "feedback": "mis-judge individuals even if we have contact with them"
  },
  {
    "question": "The best way to design a checklist will include:",
    "feedback": "1) Good cross-referenced indexing2) Colour coding of pages by topic3) Dividing pages with thumb locators4) Capital letters only used for emphasis"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a pilot is facing a problem during flight he should",
    "feedback": "take as much time as he needs and is available to make up his mind"
  },
  {
    "question": "For the flight crew, what is one of the most important attributes for positive leadership?",
    "feedback": "Cohesion"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to the humidity of air in current in a pressurized cabin, we know that it : -1 : varies between 40 and 60% -2 : varies between 5 and 15% -3 : may cause dehydration affecting the performance of the crew -4 : has no special effects on crew members",
    "feedback": "2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Carbon monoxide is particularly dangerous because:\n\n1) its initial symptoms are not alarming\n2) it is colourless\n3) it is odourless\n4) it is highly toxic\n5) its effects are cumulative\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Equalization of pressure is limited between the middle ear and the ambient, when:",
    "feedback": "the eustachian tube is blocked"
  },
  {
    "question": "All pilots are going to suffer some hearing deterioration as part of the process of growing old. The effects of aging",
    "feedback": "are to cut out the high tones first"
  },
  {
    "question": "A newly promoted captain who has recently successfully completed the command course is flying with a line training captain. The new captain is flying in the commander's seat and has been assigned the commander of the flight. Select from the options below the correct statement:",
    "feedback": "The new captain is only commander of the flight if he has been designated the commander by the aircraft operator"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does stress management involve?",
    "feedback": "Recognising stress, accepting it and developing a coping strategy"
  },
  {
    "question": "One major component of an SMS is:",
    "feedback": "Safety risk management"
  },
  {
    "question": "Evaluate what is possibly achievable in commercial aviation in respect of flight safety:",
    "feedback": "Risk should be decreased as much as commercially possible"
  },
  {
    "question": "List the constituent parts of the blood and state their function:",
    "feedback": "red cells carry oxygen, white cells are involved in immunity and platelets coagulate blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is self-concept?",
    "feedback": "How you see yourself"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does an increase in altitude affect the haemoglobin oxygen saturation?",
    "feedback": "As altitude increases, the haemoglobin oxygen saturation decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "We generate mental models on:",
    "feedback": "past experience and learning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Decompression symptoms are caused by:",
    "feedback": "dissolved gases from tissues and fluids of the body"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Grey out\" occurs in case of:",
    "feedback": "+ gZ"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following situations can lead to stagnant hypoxia",
    "feedback": "excessive G forces"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is one advantage of mental schemata when completing a familiar but complex task?",
    "feedback": "They allow a pilot to plan his/her current actions based on past experience"
  },
  {
    "question": "The atmospheric pressure at 18,000 feet altitude is half the atmospheric pressure at sea level.\nIn accordance with this statement,",
    "feedback": "the partial oxygen pressure at that altitude will also drop to 1/2 of the pressure of oxygen at sea level"
  },
  {
    "question": "Visual disturbances can be caused by:\n1. hyperventilation\n2. hypoxia\n3. hypertension\n4. fatigue",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The incidence of type 2 diabetes is increasing worldwide. Risk factors for diabetes type 2 are:\n1) Obesity\n2) Genetic background\n3) Physical activity\n4) Low calorie intake\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot using a checklist is an example of the interaction within the SHELL concept of:",
    "feedback": "L and S"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is characterized by a \"laissez-faire\" cockpit ?",
    "feedback": "A passive approach by the captain allows decisions, choices and actions by other crew members"
  },
  {
    "question": "What diseases can be associated with contaminated water?",
    "feedback": "Typhoid, Cholera, Dysentery"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following drawbacks are associated with automation?\n1) Reduced competence in manually controlling the aircraft2) Increased likelihood of slips while programming automatic systems3) Difficulties in adapting to the use of a sidestick4) General decrease in technical reliability",
    "feedback": "1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying immediately following a dive with SCUBA diving equipment (> 10 m depth)",
    "feedback": "can cause decompression sickness  even when flying at pressure altitudes below 18 000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "The crucial symptom of hypoxia that is considered to be the most dangerous with regard to safe flight is:",
    "feedback": "A reduction in reasoning and perception"
  },
  {
    "question": "Fatigue and stress",
    "feedback": "lower the tolerance to hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Tunnel vision\" (loss of peripherical vision) can be observed if a pilot is subjected to more than:",
    "feedback": "+ 3.5  Gz"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main factors which bring about reduced or low vigilance (hypovigilance) ?\n1. The monotony of the task\n2. Tiredness, the need for sleep\n3. A lack of stimulation\n4. Excessive stress",
    "feedback": "1,2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The negative (radial) acceleration of an airplane affects the sitting pilot with inertia along :",
    "feedback": "the vertical body axis upwards"
  },
  {
    "question": "Internal factors that can cause error generation include.....",
    "feedback": "over-confidence, insufficient care and improper technique"
  },
  {
    "question": "The vestibular apparatus consists of the:",
    "feedback": "Semi-circular canals and the otoliths"
  },
  {
    "question": "The behavioural effects of stress may include:\n\n1) manifestation of aggressiveness\n2) a willingness to improve communication\n3) a willingness for group cohesion\n4) a tendency to withdrawal\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct? Crew decision making is generally most efficient, if all crew members concerned",
    "feedback": "adapt their management style to meet the situational demands"
  },
  {
    "question": "To prevent gastro-intestinal problems in tropical climates you should:\n1) Not eat salad or raw vegetables\n2) Always peel fruit\n3) Only eat food that has been properly cooked\n4) Avoid ice cream\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Incapacitation caused by barotrauma from gaseous expansion after decompression at high altitude may be associated with the following part(s) of the body:\n1 the digestive tract\n2 the ears\n3 the eyes\n4 the sinuses",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Prolonged exposure to jet engine noise levels can cause noise induced hearing loss (NIHL) when these are above ....",
    "feedback": "85 dB"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about crew briefings is correct?",
    "feedback": "Briefings should be conducted during low-workload periods"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the most effective measures to take to reduce the effects of low humidity on the human body (the eyes and skin)?",
    "feedback": "Drink water, use hydrating eye drops, and apply aqueous creams"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is desirable to standardize as many patterns of behaviour (operating procedures) as possible in commercial aviation mainly because",
    "feedback": "such behaviour reduces errors even under adverse circumstances"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Scotopic Vision is vision through the operation of the Rods"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the short-term-memory, information is stored for approximately",
    "feedback": "20 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "What should a pilot do if he has no information about the dimensions of the runway and the condition of the terrain underneath the approach? He should",
    "feedback": "make an instrument approach and be aware of the illusory effects that can be induced"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following personality characteristics makes crew decision making most effective?",
    "feedback": "Assertiveness."
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the following list environmental stressors:\n\n1) heat\n2) humidity\n3) divorce\n4) lack of rest\n5) loss of job\n6) noise",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "A First Officer forgots to switch the anti-icing off after leaving icing conditions. The Commander realises this and yells at the FO for it. What type of culture is the Commander portraying?",
    "feedback": "A punitive culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "Active errors/failures are committed at:",
    "feedback": "the human/system interface and have an immediate effect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about hyperthermia is correct ?",
    "feedback": "Complete adaption to the heat in a hot country takes about a fortnight."
  },
  {
    "question": "Physical stress takes place:",
    "feedback": "when outside conditions put a strain upon the homeostatic mechanisms of the body"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a high altitude flight (no cabin pressure system available), a pilot gets severe flatulence due to trapped gases. The correct counter-measure is:",
    "feedback": "descend to lower altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following behaviours is most disruptive to teamwork under high workload conditions in the cockpit?",
    "feedback": "Mentally absent."
  },
  {
    "question": "What does not apply to a constructive and helpful feedback?",
    "feedback": "Feedback should always state bluntly the personal failings of the receiver"
  },
  {
    "question": "The otoliths in the inner ear are sensitive to:",
    "feedback": "linear acceleration and gravity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypoxia can be caused by:\n1. low partial pressure of oxygen in the atmosphere when flying at high altitudes without pressurisation and supplemental oxygen\n2. a decreased saturation of oxygen in the blood due to carbon monoxide attached to the hemoglobin\n3. blood pooling in the lower extremities due to inertia (+ Gz)\n4. malfunction of the body cells to metabolize oxygen (i.e. after a hangover)",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following correctly describes the cardiac output for a healthy adult at rest?",
    "feedback": "Stroke volume x heart rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a characteristic of the alarm stage of the General Adaptation Syndrome (GAS)?",
    "feedback": "The body prepares for action"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is true concerning carbon monoxide?",
    "feedback": "It is to be found in the smoke of cigarettes lifting up a smoker's \"physiological altitude\"."
  },
  {
    "question": "The following course of action must be taken if gastrointestinal complaints in flight crew occur before take-off:\n\n-1 : take the standard medicines and advise the doctor on returning from the flight\n-2 : assess your own ability to fly, if necessary with the help of a doctor\n-3 : if in doubt about fitness to fly - do not fly!\n-4 : reduce the cabin temperature, and drink before you are thirsty so as to avoid dehydration",
    "feedback": "2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is an example of an error caused by liveware-hardware interface problems?",
    "feedback": "Switches, control or displays with poor design."
  },
  {
    "question": "Internal conflict within oneself is termed as:",
    "feedback": "intra-personal conflict"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of a fuel spillage onto the body it is advisable that the affected area is?",
    "feedback": "Initially washed with copious water and without the use of soap"
  },
  {
    "question": "Smoking can cause hypoxia due to an increase in carbon monoxide. This is called a",
    "feedback": "hypemic hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Murphy's law states :",
    "feedback": "If equipment is designed in such a way that it can be operated wrongly, then sooner or later, it will be"
  },
  {
    "question": "The quality of learning :",
    "feedback": "is promoted by feedback on the value of one's own performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effects of galactic radiation:",
    "feedback": "increase with altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "A non synergistic cockpit:",
    "feedback": "is characterised by withdrawn crewmembers and unclear communication"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hepatitis \"A\" is transmitted through?",
    "feedback": "Food or water which has been contaminated"
  },
  {
    "question": "Decompression sickness can be prevented by:\n1. avoiding cabin altitudes above 18 000 FT\n2. maintaining cabin pressure below 8 000FT when flying at high \n    altitudes\n3. performing physical exercises before and during the flight\n4. breathing 100 % oxygen for 30 min prior and during the flight",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The relationship between arousal and flying performance is",
    "feedback": "approximately the form of an inverted U"
  },
  {
    "question": "Different non-technical related opinions between pilots from different cultural backgrounds  might be seen in connection with:\n-1 : the variations of technical training and skills.\n-2 : communication problems.\n-3 : conflicting ways of management.\n-4 : interpersonal problems.\n\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2,3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Visual acuity during flight at high altitudes can be affected by:  \n1. anaemia  \n2. smoking in the cockpit  \n3. carbon monoxide poisoning  \n4. hypoxia",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An illusion of obtaining greater height above ground can occur when:",
    "feedback": "suddenly flying over small trees after prolonged flying over tall trees"
  },
  {
    "question": "Physical exercise in high temperatures (tropical climates) may:",
    "feedback": "cause painful muscle and abdominal cramps"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following diseases may be spread by mosquitoes?\n1) Cholera2) Tetanus3) Hepatitis A4) Yellow Fever5) Typhoid Fever6) Malaria",
    "feedback": "4, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the tropics gastroenteritis is a common disease among travellers. Which of the following statements are correct?\n\n1) Gastroenteritis is often caused by bacteria\n2) Washing your hands is one of the most effective ways of preventing infection\n3) The need for liquids is greater than normal when suffering from gastroenteritis\n4) Gastroenteritis is the most common cause of pilot incapacitation",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Among the physiological responses to stress are:",
    "feedback": "sweating, dry mouth and breathing difficulties"
  },
  {
    "question": "An important contributor to human error is a false hypothesis or mistaken assumption. What should a pilot be aware of once he has made a decision?",
    "feedback": "The pilot should monitor carefully evidence which contradicts his decision"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following human error rates can be described as both realistic and pretty good, after methodical training",
    "feedback": "1 in 1000 times"
  },
  {
    "question": "Carbon monoxide, a product of incomplete combustion, is toxic because",
    "feedback": "it competes with oxygen in its union with haemoglobin"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the advantages of coordination?",
    "feedback": "Redundancy, synergy, clarification of responsibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following list are factors necessary for the promotion of good quality learning?\n1) Quality of instruction 2) Motivation 3) Knowledge of results (feedback) 4) A large amount of reference material 5) No time restrictions",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to James Reason, an organisation which collects and analyses relevant data relates to which component of safety culture?",
    "feedback": "Informed culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "During their approach, the crew of a Lockheed Tristar noticed that a green light indicating a locked nose gear had failed to illuminate and requested permission to enter a holding pattern for troubleshooting. They were assigned a position over an uninhabited swamp area, which was completely dark that night. While all the crew members were occupied with the landing gear indicator, one of the pilots inadvertently knocked a control wheel, bringing the aircraft into a gradual descent, which went unnoticed. The air traffic controller discovered that the aircraft had descended to 900 ft and asked if there was any trouble, but did not mention the altitude loss directly. The crew confirmed that everything was alright. Only seconds before the crash, the First Officer realised that they were descending into the swampland, but the crash could no longer be prevented at the stage.\nSelect the statement which is not true with regard to the above-mentioned accident:",
    "feedback": "One of the major errors in the chain of events was due to environmental capture"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is correct?",
    "feedback": "70% - 80% of information processed by man enters the visual channel"
  },
  {
    "question": "List advantages of automation:",
    "feedback": "reduced workload, more time to monitor systems, and, when managed properly, better situational awareness."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main adverse effect of expectation with regards to perception?",
    "feedback": "Expectation often guides the  focus of attention towards a particular aspect, while possible alternates are neglected"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is inadvisable to fly when suffering from a cold. The reason for this is:",
    "feedback": "pain and damage to the eardrum can result, particularly during fast descents"
  },
  {
    "question": "The choice of the moment you select flaps depending on situation and conditions of the landing is:",
    "feedback": "skill-based behaviour"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot can prevent hypoxia by:",
    "feedback": "using additional oxygen when flying above 10000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot, climbing in a non-pressurised aircraft and without using supplemental oxygen will pass the \"critical threshold\" at approximately:",
    "feedback": "20000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Skill-based behaviour is based on practice and prior learning to become part of the \"muscle memory\", or motor programmes, of your body. Because motor programmes are not continuously monitored, you should.....",
    "feedback": "The correct answers are: be conciously aware of your actions and check that the appropriate actions have been executed, take the appropriate action without considering the available options"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding decision making?",
    "feedback": "Deciding means choosing between alternatives."
  },
  {
    "question": "Concerning the capacity of the human long-term memory",
    "feedback": "its storage capacity is unlimited"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main limits of short-term memory ?\nIt is :\n-1 : very sensitive to interruptions and interference\n-2 : difficult to access\n-3 : limited in size\n-4 : subject to a biochemical burn-in of information",
    "feedback": "1,3 ,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"Swiss Cheese Model\" deals with:",
    "feedback": "Analysis of weaknesses of the organization structure and model of operation with respect to the possibility of an accident occurence."
  },
  {
    "question": "Noise induced hearing loss (NIHL) is caused by:",
    "feedback": "damage of the sensitive membrane in the cochlea due to overexposure to noise"
  },
  {
    "question": "Below 70000 ft, what gas makes up the major part of the atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "Nitrogen"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\n\n1) Interesting information is easier to take into consideration for creating a mental picture than boring information\n2) The sequence in which information is offered is also important for the use the pilot makes of it",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are both correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The risk of spatial disorientation increases when:",
    "feedback": "there is  contradictory information between the instruments and the vestibular organs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pilots should not take antihistamines because they may cause:\n1) Drowsiness and dizziness\n2) Hypoglycaemia\n3) Hyperventilation\n4) Flatulence\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Symptoms caused by gas bubbles in the lungs, following a decompression are called:",
    "feedback": "chokes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The visual approach to a high altitude aerodrome requires a relatively tight right turn to avoid high ground to the left. When lined up on the runway, the approach continues over terrain that slopes down to the runway threshold.\nWhat visual illusion could be associated with this approach?",
    "feedback": "The proximity to the terrain below the aircraft, when at the correct height for the approach, can create the illusion that the aircraft is too low; the pilot might reduce the rate of descent and land beyond the normal touchdown point"
  },
  {
    "question": "Within communication, what element suggests that a message has been received and understood?",
    "feedback": "Feedback"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statement is false?",
    "feedback": "Stress has essentially negative effects and the human will operate efficiently with an absence of stress"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can spatial disorientation in IMC be avoided? By",
    "feedback": "maintaining a good instrument cross check."
  },
  {
    "question": "Preventing hypoxia at altitude is achieved by:",
    "feedback": "pressurizing the air inside the aircraft to achieve oxygen saturation in blood of more than 90%"
  },
  {
    "question": "The three types of Authority Gradient Cockpits are:",
    "feedback": "autocratic, laissez-faire and synergistic"
  },
  {
    "question": "To optimise one's night-vision performance, it is necessary:\n\n- 1 : to spend some time getting adapted to low levels of illumination\n- 2 : to increase the instrument panel lighting by reducing the cockpit lighting\n- 3 : not to focus on the point to be observed\n- 4 : to avoid blinding",
    "feedback": "1,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The phenomenon where a group of people conforming to one another come to a false conclusion is known as:",
    "feedback": "Groupthink"
  },
  {
    "question": "At rest the cardiac output (the quantity of blood the heart pumps in one minute) of an adult is approximately:",
    "feedback": "5 liters/min"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the context of operating complex and highly automated aircraft, the term \"mode awareness\" is used to describe that.....",
    "feedback": "the pilot should always be aware of the automation mode under which the aircraft is operating and understand the interaction between a mode of automation and a particular phase of flight or pilot input"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which data compose the ICAO standard atmosphere ?\n1. Density\n2. Pressure\n3. Temperature\n4. Humidity",
    "feedback": "1,2 ,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following components belong to the middle ear?",
    "feedback": "Ossicles"
  },
  {
    "question": "Approximately how long will a blood/alcohol level of 60 mgm/100 ml take to return to normal?",
    "feedback": "6 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "After checking the flight planning sheets in flight, when the pilot looks out again he/she realises that the aircraft is banked 20 degrees to the right. The pilot immediately restores level flight, however feels that he/she is turning left.\nWhat is being described?",
    "feedback": "This is a vestibular illusion called \"the leans\", which can occur during VFR and IFR flights: It must be counteracted by referring to the instruments, since the false sensation of bank may last for quite a while"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main variable to control human respiration?",
    "feedback": "Carbon dioxide concentration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Before take-off, a briefing:",
    "feedback": "must be done systematically in order to refresh the memory of the crew members and to co-ordinate actions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Motor programmes are:",
    "feedback": "stored routines that enable patterns of behaviour to be executed without continuous conscious control"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whilst on final approach at night the aircraft in front of you has reported being illuminated by a green laser. Diversion is not an option. In order to minimise the chance of flash blindness:\n1) The crew should increase cockpit lighting2) The crew should decrease cockpit lighting3) The crew shoudld rub the eyes4) One crew member should look at the instruments only",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following scenarios most clearly describes a situation of one or both pilots being in a state of reduced vigilance?",
    "feedback": "During the cruise, the Pilot Monitoring (PM) stays silent for several minutes, staring at the instrument panel without moving"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot can overcome hyperventilation by:",
    "feedback": "controlling the rate and depth of breathing, breathing into a bag or speaking with a loud voice"
  },
  {
    "question": "The problems of hyperventilation are caused by",
    "feedback": "increased exhaling of carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "Shortsightedness means",
    "feedback": "subjects start later with presbyopia than usual"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct with regard to alcohol?",
    "feedback": "It is absorbed directly from the stomach and intestines into the bloodstream"
  },
  {
    "question": "Between which components is an interface mismatch causing disturbance of the biological rhythm, thus leading to reduced human peformance?",
    "feedback": "Liveware - Environment"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the 'End Deterioration Effect'('Home-itis') mean?",
    "feedback": "The tendency to sudden, imperceptible errors shortly before the end of a flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following applies when alcohol has been consumed?",
    "feedback": "Even after the consumption of small amounts of alcohol, normal cautionary attitudes may be lost"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by \"passive monitoring\" in terms of automation complacency?",
    "feedback": "A pilot watching what is going on rather than analyzing and constantly checking"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main sources of radiation at height?",
    "feedback": "Galactic (cosmic) radiation caused by galactic particles and solar radiation caused by solar flares"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is chronic stress associated with?",
    "feedback": "The resistance and exhaustion phases of the General Adaptation Syndrome, and it can lead to long-term psychological and physiological health problems"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a company, a safety culture is established where a person is not legally prosecuted when committing an error without consent, but where intentional violation or negligent behaviour are not tolerated. This safety culture is called:",
    "feedback": "Just culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main sources of error in a pilot's decision-making mechanism?",
    "feedback": "Situation assessment and its associated level of risk; selection of the appropriate course of action"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following statement about UV radiation is false:",
    "feedback": "light- skinned, blond, blue-eyed subjects are least sensitive to UV radiation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The rate of absorption of alcohol depends on many factors. However, the rate of metabolism or digestion of alcohol in the body is relatively constant. It is about:\n(Unit: g/100 ml per hour)",
    "feedback": "0,01 - 0,015"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a two-hour domestic flight, the Commander keeps testing the knowledge of the Copilot, arrogantly lecturing and advising him/her for 1 hour after take-off. After this, the Copilot remains generally quiet and submissive. The Commander then asks the Copilot to set in the Flight Management System some unauthorised waypoints for the approach. The Copilot is aware of the violation but does not challenge the Commander about his/her decision and does what the Commander orders.\nWhich of the following is correct?",
    "feedback": "The Copilot is behaving in an obedient manner"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following tasks are possible to do simultaneously without mutual interference?",
    "feedback": "Maintain manual straight and level flight and solve a problem."
  },
  {
    "question": "State the primary purpose of Standard Operating Procedures (SOP) in a company:",
    "feedback": "SOP shall ensure a common path which all crew members can understand and follow during any given phase of flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "Contrary to a person's personality, attitudes:",
    "feedback": "Are the product of personal disposition and past experience with reference  to an object or a situation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The readjustment of the biological rhythms after a time shift is normally more difficult",
    "feedback": "with flights towards the East"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these represents the steepest trans-cockpit authority gradient?",
    "feedback": "The captain makes a decision, orders the copilot, but does not give any explanation to his decision"
  },
  {
    "question": "The behaviour of a leader depends on:",
    "feedback": "the situation, the goals and composition of the group"
  },
  {
    "question": "Information stays in the short-term memory",
    "feedback": "about 20 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Please check the following statements:\n1. A stressor causes activation \n2. Activation stimulates a person to cope with it",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are both correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under normal circumstances, which gas will diffuse from the blood into the lungs?",
    "feedback": "Carbon dioxide."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning tiredness is correct ?",
    "feedback": "Tiredness is a subjective sensation which is reflected in hypovigilance or in poor management of intellectual capabilities"
  },
  {
    "question": "Accommodation, which enables a clear image to be obtained, is accomplished by which of the following ?",
    "feedback": "The crystalline lens"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are two types of attention?",
    "feedback": "Selective and divided."
  },
  {
    "question": "The eye can fully adjust to:",
    "feedback": "high levels of illumination in 10 seconds and darkness in 30 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following terms describe some of the different parts of the auditory system?",
    "feedback": "Auditory canal, eardrum, ossicles, cochlea, and auditory nerve"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following abilities will not improve efficient decision making in the cockpit?",
    "feedback": "Ability to persuade others to follow the own point of view."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are main signs indicating the loss of vigilance ?\n1. Decrease in sensory perception\n2. Increase in selective attention\n3. Sensation of muscular heaviness\n4. Decrease in complacency",
    "feedback": "1,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The vestibular apparatus",
    "feedback": "reacts to linear/angular acceleration and gravity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Subcutaneous pressure receptors are stimulated by:",
    "feedback": "the pressure created on the corresponding body parts when sitting, standing or lying down"
  },
  {
    "question": "Divided attention is  the ability :\n1. to execute several mental activities at almost the same time (i.e. when switching attention from outside the aircraft to the airspeed indicator on the instrument panel)\n2. to monitor the progress of a motor programme (i.e. flying or taxiing the airplane) on a relatively subconscious level, while making a radio call at the same time (requiring a rather conscious level)\n3 .to select information and check if it is relevant to the task in hand. At the same time no other operation can be performed.\n4. to delegate tasks to the copilot while concentrating on the procedures",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are correct, 3 and 4 are false"
  },
  {
    "question": "The metabolisation of alcohol",
    "feedback": "is a question of time"
  },
  {
    "question": "A commercial organisation invests heavily in new technology solely to reduce a hazard that has a safety risk index of \"acceptable\". According to ICAO DOC 9859, what is the probable outcome?",
    "feedback": "The cost can reduce profits with minimal safety improvements, and could lead to bankruptcy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Although the anticipation of possible events is a good attitude for pilots to acquire, it can sometimes lead to hazardous situations. With this statement in mind, select the response below which could lead to such a hazard:",
    "feedback": "mishearing  the contents of a reply from an air traffic controller when a non-standard procedure was given but a standard procedure was anticipated"
  },
  {
    "question": "Among the symptoms of hypoglycaemia are:",
    "feedback": "headache and lack of concentration."
  },
  {
    "question": "Inhaling carbon monoxide can be extremely dangerous during flying. \nWhich of the following statement(s) is/are correct?",
    "feedback": "Carbon monoxide is odourless and cannot be smelled."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following definitions of human blood pressure is correct?",
    "feedback": "Systolic pressure is generated by the contractions of the heart, when it pumps blood towards the periphery of the body, and it is the highest pressure value"
  },
  {
    "question": "A bias is a tendency that can prevent open-minded decision making. Which of the following is an example of a bias in aeronautical decision making?",
    "feedback": "Confirmation bias: the tendency to search for information that confirms one's preconceptions"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal breathing frequency (times per minute) of an adult at rest is:",
    "feedback": "10-15"
  },
  {
    "question": "During flight in IMC, the most reliable sense which should be used to overcome illusions is the:",
    "feedback": "visual sense,  interpreting the attitude indicator"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying above 10.000 feet hypoxia arises because:",
    "feedback": "the partial oxygen pressure is lower than at sea level."
  },
  {
    "question": "Being a copilot implies:",
    "feedback": "All of the above mentioned alternatives"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stress can be defined as:",
    "feedback": "the unresolved pressure, strain or force acting upon an individual's physical or mental systems and the human response"
  },
  {
    "question": "The chemical substance responsible for addiction to tobacco is",
    "feedback": "nicotine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "Stressors accumulate thus increasing the likelihood to exhaustion."
  },
  {
    "question": "The Peripheral Nervous System passes information from the:",
    "feedback": "sensory inputs to the CNS through sensory and motor nerves"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following symptoms is not typical for a decompression sickness:",
    "feedback": "red out"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct statement from the answers given below:",
    "feedback": "Galactic radiation effects increase with altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "The symptoms caused by gas bubbles under the skin following a  decompression are called:",
    "feedback": "creeps"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a glass-cockpit aircraft, communication between the members of the crew:",
    "feedback": "does not lose its importance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Autokinesis can give the pilot the impression that:",
    "feedback": "a star is another aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct ?\n- 1: The retina has rods on its peripheral zone and cones on its central zone\n- 2: The retina has cones and the crystalline lens has rods\n- 3: The rods allow for night-vision\n- 4: The cones are located on the peripheral zone of the retina",
    "feedback": "1,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What could cause hyperventilation ?",
    "feedback": "Fear, anxiety and distress"
  },
  {
    "question": "When focussing on near objects:",
    "feedback": "the shape of lens gets more spherical"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct definition of vigilance:",
    "feedback": "A vigilant task is one that requires consistent monitoring without lapses in attention. Vigilance is simply defined as\nsustained attention."
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to get rid of excess nitrogen following scuba diving, subsequent flights should be delayed",
    "feedback": "24 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Communication has been recognized as a cause of accidents and incidents. Among the following options, which one provides the most accurate definition for good communication?",
    "feedback": "The effective transmission of a message"
  },
  {
    "question": "The duration of a period of sleep is governed primarily by",
    "feedback": "the point within your circadian rhythm at which you try to sleep"
  },
  {
    "question": "Carbon monoxide poisoning",
    "feedback": "is more likely to occur in aeroplanes where the cabin heat is technically supplied by coating the exhaust"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is synergy in a crew ?",
    "feedback": "The coordinated action of all members towards a common objective, in which collective performance is proving to be more than the sum of the individual performances"
  },
  {
    "question": "We know that, in the mechanism of sight, the retina allows for :",
    "feedback": "the acquisition of the visual signal and its coding into physiological data"
  },
  {
    "question": "Empty field myopia is caused by:",
    "feedback": "lack of distant focal points"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a multi-crew aircraft taking a nap in the cockpit:",
    "feedback": "should last between 15 to 40 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Suppose you make an approach to a runway which is narrower than standard. Which of the following errors are you likely to commit?",
    "feedback": "Initiate a flare too late"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is described by the term \"Irony of Automation\"?",
    "feedback": "Computers are able to perform a task at which we are good even better than us, but at the same time require us to perform a task we want to be better at"
  },
  {
    "question": "Type 2 diabetes may be prevented by:",
    "feedback": "avoiding being overweight"
  },
  {
    "question": "What may trigger stress in humans?",
    "feedback": "The subjective interpretation an individual gives to a situation experienced"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term \"pilot error\" constitute a certain relative amount of main causes in air accidents. Which of the following is correct?",
    "feedback": "Around 70%"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"ideal\" cockpit can be termed as:",
    "feedback": "synergistic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Liveware - Liveware interaction is:",
    "feedback": "the interface between people."
  },
  {
    "question": "Standard Operating Procedures (SOP) can contribute to avoiding, reducing and managing threats and/or errors in daily flight operations.\nHow can this be achieved?",
    "feedback": "Reliable behaviour of crew members acting according to SOP reduces the stress in individuals and makes them less prone to commit errors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following characteristics apply to short-term memory ?\n- 1 : It is limited in time and size\n- 2 : It is unlimited in time and limited in size\n- 3 : It is stable and insensitive to disturbances\n- 4 : It is limited in time and unlimited in size",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can vertigo be prevented in conditions of good visibility?",
    "feedback": "By looking at the horizon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Breathing pure oxygen (without pressure) will be sufficient up to an altitude of:",
    "feedback": "40000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Working memory enables us, for example,",
    "feedback": "to remember a clearance long enough to write it down"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gastrointestinal upset is one of the most common causes of crew incapacitation in flight. In can be caused by which of the following?\n1) Viral infection from food or water2) Bacterial infection from food or water3) Diarrhoea4) Alcohol5) Vomiting6) Spicy food",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4,, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Pilot's vertigo\"",
    "feedback": "is the condition of dizziness and/or tumbling sensation caused by contradictory impulses to the central nervous system (CNS)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the current approach to human error?",
    "feedback": "Realisation that humans are fallible and that systems and procedures should be designed to minimise human error"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate Time of Useful Consciousness for a seated pilot following a rapid decompression at 35000 ft?",
    "feedback": "45 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Breathing 100% oxygen at 40000 ft is equivalent to breathing ambient air at :",
    "feedback": "10 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"Seat-of-the-Pants-Sense\"",
    "feedback": "can give false inputs to body orientation when visual reference is lost"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot should not fly immediately after donating blood because:",
    "feedback": "you have an increased susceptibility to fainting"
  },
  {
    "question": "While monitoring the instruments during the cruise, the flight crew are in a state of (1) ...... and their (2) ...... is drawn by one of the engines' oil cages indicating that the oil pressure is dropping.",
    "feedback": "(1) vigilance, (2) attention"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tetanus is transmitted through?",
    "feedback": "Bacteria in the form of spores via puncture in the skin"
  },
  {
    "question": "The level of automation helps to conserve resources. On the other hand, it may result in:",
    "feedback": "routine errors (slips)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is one of the advantages of Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs) in flight operations?",
    "feedback": "SOPs are an effective aid to decision-making for the flight crew, reducing their workload and reducing the probability of taking poor decisions and making errors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why do older and more experienced pilots often say \"West is best\"?",
    "feedback": "The day stretches when travelling West"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate percentage of oxygen in the atmosphere at 18000 ft?",
    "feedback": "21 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "The ability of the lens to change its shape is called:",
    "feedback": "accommodation"
  },
  {
    "question": "General Adaptation Syndrome is characterised by the following phases :\n-1 : alarm\n-2 : alert phase\n-3 : resistance phase\n-4 : exhaustion phase\n-5 : vigilance phase",
    "feedback": "1,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "To maintain good situational awareness you should:\n\n(1) believe only in your own interpretation of the data\n(2) gather as much data as possible from every possible source before making inferences\n(3) question whether your hypothesis still fits the situation as events progress and try to make time to review the situation\n(4) consider ways of testing your situational hypothesis to see whether it is correct",
    "feedback": "2, 3 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Many pilots prefer to perform simulator sessions during the day rather than at night time, due to the circadian body rhythm.\nWhich statement about the effect of the body temperature's circadian rhythm is correct?",
    "feedback": "When the body temperature is falling it is harder to work, than when it is rising"
  },
  {
    "question": "During gas exchange, the partial pressure of carbon dioxide in the alveoli is:",
    "feedback": "lower than in the blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most dangerous type of incapacitation in flight is one that:",
    "feedback": "develops slowly and gradually (insidious)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pre-thought action plans may be said to:\n-1 : ease access to information which may be necessary.\n-2 : sensitize and prepare for a possible situation to come.\n-3 : be readily interchangeable and can therefore be reformulated \n       at any time during the flight.\n-4 : define a framework and a probable strategy for the \n       encountered situation.\n\nThe combination of correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2 and 4 are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Situational awareness is defined as.....",
    "feedback": "the accurate perception of operational and environmental factors that affect the flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "A person being exposed to extreme or prolonged stress factors can perceive:",
    "feedback": "distress"
  },
  {
    "question": "An experienced Commander is flying with an equally experienced Copilot, who is new to the company. The Commander does not have much experience with flying over high seas, but the Copilot has gained experience with his previous employer. When they fly over high seas, the Copilot gives the Commander a lot of advice, but the Commander won't listen. The Commander then commits an error that the Copilot helps him correct.\nWhat is the correct description of the cockpit authority situation?",
    "feedback": "The Commander is autocratic and the Copilot does not act as a good follower"
  },
  {
    "question": "Barotrauma of the middle ear is usually accompanied by",
    "feedback": "a reduction in hearing ability and the feeling of increasing pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which part of the inner ear is responsible for the perception of sound?",
    "feedback": "The cochlea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tattooing and immunisation with the use of improperly sterilised needles or syringes may expose the receiver to which of the following?",
    "feedback": "Hepatitis B or C"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are disorientated during night flying you must:",
    "feedback": "rely on instruments"
  },
  {
    "question": "The flight crew is a small social group. Interdependencies within this group ....",
    "feedback": "may influence a crew member's opinions, actions or perceptions, and lead to group conformity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the correct action to counteract vertigo?",
    "feedback": "Believe the instruments"
  },
  {
    "question": "Angular accelerations are picked up in the inner ear by",
    "feedback": "the semicircular canals"
  },
  {
    "question": "How should a pilot react, when suffering from chronic stress?",
    "feedback": "Attempt to reduce the stress by using a concept which approaches the entire body and improves wellness."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning culture is correct?",
    "feedback": "An informed culture actively collects, analyses and distributes safety-related data"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pilot stress reactions :",
    "feedback": "differ from pilot to pilot, depending on how a person manages the particular stressors"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is desirable to standardize as many patterns of behaviour (operating procedures) as possible in commercial aviation mainly because:",
    "feedback": "such behaviour reduces errors even under adverse circumstances"
  },
  {
    "question": "Among the measures that a pilot should take when in an area where gastro-intestinal upsets are endemic is?",
    "feedback": "Avoidance of ice in cold drinks"
  },
  {
    "question": "What effect does the blind spot have on the pilot's ability to conduct an efficient visual search for other traffic?",
    "feedback": "When the pilot is scanning the area ahead and on either side of the aircraft, with an unobscured field of view, another aircraft on a constant relative bearing could be lost in the blind spot of either eye"
  },
  {
    "question": "The impression of  an apparent movement of  light  when stared at for a relatively long period of time in the dark is called",
    "feedback": "\"autokinesis\""
  },
  {
    "question": "As a cause of accidents, the human factor",
    "feedback": "is cited in approximately 70 - 80 % of aviation accidents"
  },
  {
    "question": "In general, which are the main factors that determine a pilot's behaviour?",
    "feedback": "Personality and attitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "The 5 human senses tend to adapt.",
    "feedback": "This statement is true"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the sender's frequent reason to communicate implicitly ('between the lines')?",
    "feedback": "Afterwards he/she always can claim to have been misunderstood."
  },
  {
    "question": "The amount of light which strikes the retina is controlled by:",
    "feedback": "the pupil"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a stop-over is more than 24 hours, the correct action is?",
    "feedback": "Move to the new time zone as soon as possible"
  },
  {
    "question": "Is it possible to survive depressurized flight at 40000 feet for more than 10 minutes?",
    "feedback": "Yes- provided 100 % oxygen under pressure is immediately available from masks"
  },
  {
    "question": "A high level of motivation is related",
    "feedback": "to high levels of arousal"
  },
  {
    "question": "The General Adaptation Syndrome is associated with the:",
    "feedback": "ANS (Autonomic Nervous System)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Decision-making results in:",
    "feedback": "a choice between different solutions for achieving a goal"
  },
  {
    "question": "The earth's atmosphere consists of different gases in various concentration. Match the following:\n\n1 nitrogen                         A     0,03%\n2 oxygen                          B     0,92%\n3 carbon dioxide           C   20.95%\n4 rare gas                        D  78,10%",
    "feedback": "1D, 2C, 3A, 4B"
  },
  {
    "question": "State the conditions which cause the \"black hole effect\" and the danger to flight safety:",
    "feedback": "The \"black hole effect\" can be caused by flying over water at night on the approach to an airfield which can create the illusion that the aircraft is at a higher altitude than it is, leading to a low approach being flown"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements best characterise a synergetic cockpit?\n\n1. Decisions are taken by the captain, but prepared by the crew\n2. There is little delegating of tasks\n3. Communications are few in number but precise and geared purely to the flight\n4. Fluid, consensual boundaries exist in regard to leadership-style",
    "feedback": "1,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to the average influence of age on pilot performance, it may be said that age:",
    "feedback": "has little impact when the pilot is able to compensate for it by his/her flight experience"
  },
  {
    "question": "Attitudes are defined as:",
    "feedback": "tendencies to respond to people, institutions or events either positively or negatively"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can a pilot prevent \"pilots-vertigo\"?",
    "feedback": "Avoid steep turns and abrupt flight maneouvers and maintain an effective instrument cross check."
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct statement regarding decision making and biases:",
    "feedback": "Confirmation bias is a tendency to give undue weight to information supporting the current mental picture"
  },
  {
    "question": "The part(s) of the eye responsible for night vision",
    "feedback": "are the rods"
  },
  {
    "question": "Decompression sickness occurs in association with exposure to reduced atmospheric pressure.\nThe evolution of bubbles of nitrogen coming out of solution in body tissues can be derived from:",
    "feedback": "Henry´s law"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following signs distinguishes hypoxia from hyperventilation?",
    "feedback": "Cyanosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The W/V (°/kt) at 50°N 015°W is:",
    "feedback": "290/75"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 200 hPa pressure altitude level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "feedback": "FL 390."
  },
  {
    "question": "What information could you find in a gridded dataset?",
    "feedback": "Flight level and temperature of the tropopause, CB turbulence, icing W/V"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average wind for the route Athens-Geneva, FL 160:",
    "feedback": "23040KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what type of cloud is a Cumulonimbus classified?",
    "feedback": "Low level"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning volume and temperature of a descending parcel of air is correct?",
    "feedback": "The volume decreases while the temperature increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "During summer in the centre of a warm anticyclone over land, what are cloudiness and visibility like?",
    "feedback": "The sky is clear or bears few clouds; visibility is moderate to poor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Between which flight levels and at what intensity could you encounter turbulence in CAT area 2?",
    "feedback": "From FL 200 to FL 380, moderate, occasionally severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "Describe the main role of the World Meteorological Organisation (WMO) with regard to aviation.",
    "feedback": "Establish and implement, together with ICAO, a global regulatory framework for aviation meteorological services"
  },
  {
    "question": "When compared to icing in stratiform clouds, icing in cumuliform clouds is generally:",
    "feedback": "more severe due to the higher supercooled water content of cumuliform cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider an anticyclone. If the geostrophic wind speed is 40 kt, the gradient wind speed for the same isobar interval is ....",
    "feedback": "greater than 40 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"S\" is",
    "feedback": "overcast with drizzle and orographic fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather forecast for a low level route includes a warning of possible moderate to severe turbulence. For an aircraft in flight and operating along this route, which of the following, if available, would provide the most up-to-date information that could help the pilot to avoid the worst turbulence?",
    "feedback": "Pilot reports can provide the most valuable information on any weather hazards, including turbulence, that is useful to other pilots approaching the same area"
  },
  {
    "question": "The isohypse 11880 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "feedback": "200 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft, flying so that the altimeter indicates 2500ft with the current regional QNH set in the subscale, is flying towards an area of lower pressure. If the pilot fails to revise the subscale setting as the QNH changes, then the aircraft will:",
    "feedback": "Gradually descend"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the route indicated from Recife to Dakar the mean height of the tropopause during January is approximately",
    "feedback": "56000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Convective activity over land in mid-latitudes is greatest in",
    "feedback": "summer in the afternoon."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the weather at a stationary front is true?",
    "feedback": "Stationary fronts are accompanied by a cloud band and precipitation of varying intensity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "Fog can be supercooled and can also contain ice crystals."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following combinations contain the greatest air density?",
    "feedback": "High pressure and low temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from B to A on the diagram at FL090. About halfway through the flight, a cold front is passed. The wind direction (1) ....... and the wind speed will (2) ........",
    "feedback": "(1) veer; (2) decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the vicinity of industrial areas, smoke is most likely to affect surface visibility when",
    "feedback": "there is a low level inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Your destination aerodrome in Western Europe lies on the crest of a ridge, inland, with an elevation of 700 feet AMSL. Before take-off, the METAR for your destination is: \"0850Z  27015KT  0100  R29/0650  FG  VV///  03/03  Q1005\"\nThere is another aerodrome a few miles west of the destination aerodrome at an elevation of 200 feet AMSL. The METAR for this aerodrome is: \"0850Z  26011KT  9999  SCT050  05/03  Q1005\".\nConsidering this situation, what type of fog is present at the destination aerodrome and which of these statements correctly describes the dissipation of this fog?",
    "feedback": "Orographic fog; and as the temperature rises with diurnal heating, the fog is likely to lift into cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the weather phenomena to be expected when flying from Perth (32°S 116°E) to Melbourne (38°S 144°E) at FL250?",
    "feedback": "Individual thunderstorms with hail and moderate or severe turbulence and ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about turbulence are correct or incorrect?\n1) Severe CAT may be expected in the core of a jet stream\n2) At 500 ft/AGL mechanical turbulence does occur more often than at 5000 ft/AGL",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most hazardous type of cloud that may be encountered on a cross country flight is",
    "feedback": "cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "A SPECI is",
    "feedback": "an aviation selected special weather report"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is correct regarding the dissipation of the Nocturnal Jet?",
    "feedback": "It dissipates in the morning as the air warms and vertical mixing sets in"
  },
  {
    "question": "At the same latitude the geostrophic wind is greater than the gradient wind around a low pressure system with equal pressure gradient because the",
    "feedback": "centrifugal force opposes the pressure gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why are polar regions colder than equatorial regions?",
    "feedback": "Because the angle of incidence of the solar radiation is very small in polar regions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is encountered during the summer, over land, in the centre of a cold air drop?",
    "feedback": "Showers and thunderstorms."
  },
  {
    "question": "In a mountainous area a minimum safe altitude of 8000 ft is given. An airport in the vicinity with an elevation of 0 ft reports the following data:\n\nAir temperature -24° C at FL 100\nPressure value QNH 990 hPa\n\nWhich is the lowest usable flight level under these conditions?",
    "feedback": "FL 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "The isohypse 5700 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "feedback": "500 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aircraft making an approach to an airfield located in square 3B, away from the vicinity of the fronts, the most likely weather conditions in winter are",
    "feedback": "poor visibility in mist and drizzle"
  },
  {
    "question": "The images are examples of visible and infrared satellite images respectively, valid for the same time.\nUsing these satellite images, it can be concluded that the clouds stretching in a band from the Gulf of Mexico northeastward into New York are of the type:",
    "feedback": "Cumulus and Cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about air masses are correct or incorrect?\n1) The polar ice caps are source regions of polar air\n2) Tropical air may have cold air mass properties",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of front is to be found at position V?",
    "feedback": "Stationary front"
  },
  {
    "question": "The environmental lapse rate in an actual atmosphere",
    "feedback": "varies with time"
  },
  {
    "question": "A given volume of 1 m3 of air is saturated with water vapour. With decreasing air temperature the",
    "feedback": "relative humidity will remain the same"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a common cause of ground or surface temperature inversion ?",
    "feedback": "Terrestrial radiation on a clear night with no or very light winds."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate speed of a 40-knot wind, expressed in m/sec?",
    "feedback": "20 m/sec"
  },
  {
    "question": "What pressure is defined as QFE?",
    "feedback": "The pressure at field elevation"
  },
  {
    "question": "A layer is conditionally unstable if the air",
    "feedback": "is unstable for saturated air and stable for dry air."
  },
  {
    "question": "You are in the process of planning a flight from Brussels (50°55'N 004°30'E) to Deauville (49°00'N 000°00'E) on 12th March 2017, departing at 20:00 UTC and with a flight time of approximately 3 hours. The route will follow the line from B to D on the chart, and the minimum altitude that can be flown is 3200 feet.\nWhich altitude would allow the flight to remain clear of forecasted moderate or severe icing conditions along the entire route?",
    "feedback": "Icing conditions cannot be avoided on this route"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements is true?",
    "feedback": "Local snow and severe aircraft icing can be expected over Germany"
  },
  {
    "question": "The extent of the vertical development of the jet stream located at 43°N 090°W is ....",
    "feedback": "39000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the final temperature of unsaturated surface air at 12° C, which rises to 6000 ft?",
    "feedback": "-06°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Glaze or clear ice is formed when supercooled droplets are",
    "feedback": "large and at a temperature just below freezing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The sketch indicates a single-cell thunderstorm in the mature stage which is travelling in the direction of the wind arrow. Which of the following statements correctly identifies the likely locations of various weather phenomena?",
    "feedback": "Severe icing in area E, gust front in area F, and microbursts in area H"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the following aerodrome warnings, a pilot on approach to land at (1) ...... airport has reported (2) .......\nLDRI WS WRNG 1 160520 VALID 160520/161200 WS ALL RWY FCST=LGTS WS WRNG 1 160520 MBST APCH RWY 16 REP AT 0500 A320 35KT LOSS 1 NM FNA=LGAV WS WRNG 1 160520 MBST IN CLIMB OUT REP AT 0500 A320=EDDF WS WRNG 1 160520 VALID 160520/161200 WS RWY18 FCST=",
    "feedback": "(1) LGTS, (2) a microburst"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what flight level is the jet stream core that is situated over Germany?",
    "feedback": "FL 330"
  },
  {
    "question": "When water evaporates into unsaturated air",
    "feedback": "heat is absorbed"
  },
  {
    "question": "During summer, a weak pressure gradient covers a coastal airfield in Eastern England resulting in mainly clear skies. The surface wind at dawn was calm.\nIf the alignment of the coastline in the vicinity of the airfield is predominantly north/south, the surface wind is likely to become",
    "feedback": "easterly to south-easterly and increase in velocity by afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Define a \"High\":",
    "feedback": "an area with higher pressure than that of the horizontal environments"
  },
  {
    "question": "The frontal picture represents the situation at 0600 UTC. What is the most applicable surface weather situation at 1200 UTC over Southern England at longitude 0°?",
    "feedback": "5 to 7 oktas of stratified clouds, basis 1500 ft/GND, SHRA, BR, winds veering from south to southwest"
  },
  {
    "question": "The indicated clouds overhead Scandinavia are most likely an indicator for a(n)....",
    "feedback": "cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the role of a MWO?",
    "feedback": "Analyze charts and prepare SIGMETS within the FIR"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characteristics will the surface winds have in an area where the isobars on the weather map are very close together?",
    "feedback": "Strong and flowing across the isobars."
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot plans to depart from ESSA airport. During the briefing the meteorologist informs him/her that there is strong instability in the area and presents the following special weather report:SPECI ESSA 31035G45KT 270V360 3000 BKN010CB BKN023TCU OVC040 24/20 Q0990 RERA WS=\nGiven the information available to the pilot, a tornado....",
    "feedback": "could form because of the existent circular air motion and the prevailing low pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements describes a microburst ?",
    "feedback": "A high speed downburst of air with a generally lower temperature than its surroundings"
  },
  {
    "question": "State the four families of clouds:",
    "feedback": "High, medium and low clouds, and clouds with extensive vertical development."
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet stream is located at 42°N 090°W. What is its extent of the vertical development?",
    "feedback": "39000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The QNH of an airport at sea level is 983 hPa and the temperature deviation from ISA is -15°C below FL100. What is the approximate true altitude of FL100?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "8500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line of the graph renders the behaviour of the dew point of unsaturated air parcels in vertical motions?",
    "feedback": "The dashed lines"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct/incorrect?\n1) The tropopause height increases with increasing latitude\n2) The tropopause is a continuous levelled surface",
    "feedback": "1) incorrect, 2) incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following choices lists only main cloud genera that are mostly the clue for an unstable thermal stratification in the atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "Cirrocumulus, altocumulus, cumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Moist air is:",
    "feedback": "Less dense than dry air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: State the height of the freezing level over Tunis, considering the common vertical temperature gradient:",
    "feedback": "FL 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate value of atmospheric pressure at 5500 m AMSL in comparison to the atmospheric pressure at mean sea level?",
    "feedback": "One half"
  },
  {
    "question": "The dry adiabatic lapse rate",
    "feedback": "has a constant fixed value"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the tracks (dashed lines) is represented by the cross-section shown on the right?",
    "feedback": "D - A"
  },
  {
    "question": "After landing at an aerodrome (aerodrome elevation 1750 ft), the altimeter indicates an altitude of 1300 ft. The altimeter is set to the pressure value of 1013 hPa. What is the QNH at this aerodrome?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "1028 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "In relation to the total weight of the atmosphere, the weight of the atmosphere between mean sea level and a height of 5500 m is:",
    "feedback": "50 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the International Standard Atmosphere the decrease in temperature with height below 11 km is",
    "feedback": "0.65°C per 100m"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option best describes turbulence?",
    "feedback": "Airflow that causes random deviations from the desired flight path which need immediate corrective action"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Runway Visual Range (RVR) is measured along the runway and reported in increments depending on the horizontal visiblity. It is reported in steps of (1) ..... if the RVR is less than 400 m, in steps of (2) ..... if the RVR is between 400 m and 800 m, and in steps of (3) .... if the RVR is more than 800 m.",
    "feedback": "(1) 25 m, (2) 50 m, (3) 100 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "The trade winds over the Atlantic Ocean in July will be found in the latitude band indicated by the letter (1) ..... and the typical conditions are (2) ...... :",
    "feedback": "(1) V, (2) fair weather Cumulus or Stratocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the QNH at Locarno (200 metres above sea level) is 1025 hPa, what is the approximate QFE?(assume 1 hPa = 8 m)",
    "feedback": "1000 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "To build a hurricane, the following conditions, among others, must be fulfilled:",
    "feedback": "The surface temperature at least +27°C, and the building area  8 - 15° away from the equator."
  },
  {
    "question": "Relative humidity at a given temperature is the relation between",
    "feedback": "actual water vapour content and saturated water vapour content"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what airframe temperatures would you expect the worst icing effects?",
    "feedback": "Between 0°C and -15°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Absolute instability in a layer of air is characterized by the vertical temperature gradient in the layer being:",
    "feedback": "Greater than 1°/100 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "Two aircraft are flying simultaneously in level flight at different flight levels on opposite tracks overhead a given position.\n\nAircraft A flying at FL 070 experiences a 30 kt headwind.\nAircraft B flying at FL 060 experiences a 20 kt headwind.\n\nNone of the aircraft experiences cross wind. This wind condition will be referred to as",
    "feedback": "vertical wind shear only"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which best describes the significant cloud, if any, forecast for the area southwest of BODO (67°N 014°E)",
    "feedback": "5 to 7 oktas CU and CB, base below FL100, tops FL180"
  },
  {
    "question": "QNH is defined as",
    "feedback": "QFE reduced to MSL using the values of the standard atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "What surface weather is associated with a stationary high pressure region over land in the winter?",
    "feedback": "A tendency for fog and low ST."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a cold-air drop?",
    "feedback": "A topographic depression filled with cold air"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the difference between a macroburst and a microburst?",
    "feedback": "A macroburst affects a greater area"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the route between Frankfurt EDDF and New York KJFK at FL340. Determine the approximate forecast wind direction at position 55°N 20°W:",
    "feedback": "280°"
  },
  {
    "question": "The greater the pressure gradient the",
    "feedback": "closer the isobars and the stronger the wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "Surface visibility at your destination in the centre of France in August is reported as 1500 metres in haze, with an inversion at 500 feet above aerodrome level and sky clear above.\nWhen making a non-precision approach to runway 18 shortly before sunset with a minimum descent altitude of 600 feet above aerodrome level, at what range would you expect to see the runway and why?",
    "feedback": "More than 1500 metres because the aircraft will still be flying above the haze"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind speed in a system with curved isobars compared to a system with straight isobars is (other conditions being the same)",
    "feedback": "higher if curvature is anticyclonic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the heaviest type of precipitation, if any, forecast for BORDEAUX/MERIGNAC at 1000 UTC ?",
    "feedback": "light rain"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which conditions would you most likely encounter clear icing, and how would it normally appear?",
    "feedback": "Cumuliform clouds, large water droplets, temperatures between 0°C and -15°C.\nAppears smooth and tends to spread back over an aircraft wing."
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of clouds are associated with rain showers ?",
    "feedback": "Towering cumulus and cumulonimbus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements:\n1) The cooling of air by advection over a cooler surface is the result of an adiabatic process\n2) The change of temperature in rising and sinking air is the result of an adiabatic process",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The decrease in temperature, per 100 metres, in a saturated rising parcel of air at lower level of the atmosphere is approximately",
    "feedback": "0.6°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rain is formed within warm clouds when a particle, such as a grain of dust, attracts a drop of moisture to itself. In a next step, this initial cloud droplet will....",
    "feedback": "collide with other droplets, thereby growing in size and eventually forming a rain drop"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ice accretion occurs when the ambient temperature is (1) .... in flight. Ice can also form when water molecules change their state directly from (2) .... to (3) .... . This process is called (4) ....",
    "feedback": "(1) 0°C or below; (2) vapour; (3) solid; (4) sublimation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the displayed cloud forms is representative of altocumulus lenticularis?",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main icing zone in the ITCZ is located between:",
    "feedback": "FL 160 - FL 260"
  },
  {
    "question": "St. Elmo's fire near thunderstorms can be described as...",
    "feedback": "an electric discharge from the aircraft caused by static build-up on the airframe"
  },
  {
    "question": "When examining the SWC, an interesting significant weather feature called \"Carlos\" (22°S 053°E) is shown off the east coast of Madagascar. This phenomenon is correctly described as ....",
    "feedback": "an Indian Ocean tropical cyclone"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider grid point forecasts provided by World Area Forecast Centres (WAFCs). According to ICAO Annex 3, which of the following are included in these forecasts?\n1) Wind and temperature data for various flight levels from FL050 to FL530 2) Flight level and temperature of the tropopause 3) Horizontal and vertical extent of precipitation 4) Density for various flight levels 5) Humidity for various flight levels",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct or incorrect?\n1) Ice water content (IWC) is a special form of ice crystal icing (ICI)2) The ice mass per unit volume of air is called ice water content (IWC)",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The presence of altocumulus lenticularis is an indication of the",
    "feedback": "presence of mountain waves"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind is 25009KT. It is autumn and the sea water temperature is 18°C. What is a condition for the possible formation of advection fog on the western shoreline of a continent?",
    "feedback": "The ground surface ashore being cool"
  },
  {
    "question": "An isothermal layer is a layer of air",
    "feedback": "in which the lapse rate is zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "A cumulonimbus cloud at mid-latitudes in summer contains",
    "feedback": "a combination of ice crystals, water droplets and supercooled water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming a generalised zonal system of world climatic and wind circulation, zone \"u\" is an area of",
    "feedback": "NE trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "What runway is the most likely to be affected by a reduction of visibility during a landing at sunset, particularly in hazy conditions?",
    "feedback": "27"
  },
  {
    "question": "The schematic view of the earth shows some isobars (short black lines) and the corresponding areas of lower and higher pressure at the surface.\n\nWhat are the approximate wind directions aloft between 2000 and 3000 ft above ground at the two red points shown on the diagram?",
    "feedback": "1: SW, 2: NE"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements:\n1) The transfer of heat by radiation and advection is non-adiabatic\n2) The ascent and descent of air cause adiabatic changes of temperature",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What OAT would you expect at FL 200 over Geneva ?",
    "feedback": "-24°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Determine whether the temperature and air pressure will increase or decrease at the location indicated in the image.",
    "feedback": "Temperature decreases, pressure increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a moderate duststorm with the sky obscured is reported, the visibility will be....",
    "feedback": "between 200 and 600 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "Thunderstorms can occur on a warm front if the",
    "feedback": "warm air is moist and the environmental lapse rate exceeds the saturated adiabatic lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "The average change of pressure with height in the lower atmosphere is:",
    "feedback": "1 hPa/30ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the approach, the surface temperature is given as -5°C. The freezing level is at 3000 FT/AGL. At 4000 FT/AGL, there is a solid cloud layer from which rain is falling.\nAccording to the weather briefing, the clouds are due to an inversion caused by warm air sliding up and over an inclined front. Would you expect icing?",
    "feedback": "Yes, between ground level and 3000 FT/AGL."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 30065 FT pressure level (FL 300)?",
    "feedback": "300 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flies from London to South France and experiences a strong wind from the right. Which of the following is correct?",
    "feedback": "The true altitude will increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of cloud can produce hail showers?",
    "feedback": "CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following weather conditions favour the formation of radiation fog?",
    "feedback": "Light wind, little or no cloud, moist air."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft in flight experiences airframe icing which makes a change of heading and/or altitude desirable.\n\nWhich intensity of ice accretion is present according to ICAO terms?",
    "feedback": "Moderate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the criterion for the vertical division of the lower part of the atmosphere into troposphere and stratosphere?",
    "feedback": "Vertical temperature profile"
  },
  {
    "question": "A special air-report",
    "feedback": "may trigger a SIGMET message"
  },
  {
    "question": "The icing in cloud which forms over hills is likely to be more severe than in the same type of cloud over level terrain because",
    "feedback": "enforced ascent of air releases more water, which is retained in the cloud by the increased upward components"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the Northern Hemisphere, an aircraft flies from A to B:",
    "feedback": "The wind is increasing and veering"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass affecting position B is most likely to be:",
    "feedback": "Maritime polar."
  },
  {
    "question": "Orographic thunderstorms may occur:",
    "feedback": "at any time during day and night."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a cold-air drop?",
    "feedback": "A low pressure area with colder air compared to its surroundings. It can be found by looking at upper contour charts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Weather conditions at Mumbai during January are mainly influenced by the",
    "feedback": "NE monsoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are at FL60, but you forget to switch to the standard pressure setting and remain instead on the local QNH of 1025 hPa. How much higher or lower are you from the other aircraft at FL60 with the standard pressure setting correctly set?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "360 ft lower"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is 17:30 UTC on a day in March. You are listening to the ATIS for an aerodrome with a single runway near London. The following is reported:\n\"Visibility 3000 metres in haze, sky clear\".\nWhen about to land on runway 27, the runway in use,what flight visibility would you expect (no RVR information is given in the ATIS message)?",
    "feedback": "Considerably less than 3000 metres, but more than 1500 metres when flying into the sun"
  },
  {
    "question": "Relative humidity depends on",
    "feedback": "moisture content and temperature of the air"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a characteristic phenomenon for a stable atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "Stratified clouds."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at 2600 ft with the altimeter set to 1000 hPa (QNH of a nearby airfield at 600 ft). Considering that the air mass at the airfield is on average 8°C warmer than standard, calculate the aircraft's true altitude over the field:",
    "feedback": "2664 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "When does frontal fog, also known as mixing fog, occur?",
    "feedback": "When very humid warm air meets with very humid cold air."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud, normally found in the medium level, may extend to the low and high  levels?",
    "feedback": "NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "The core of the polar front jet stream is usually located in the",
    "feedback": "tropical air below the tropopause"
  },
  {
    "question": "A high pressure area (slack pressure gradient) covers an area of the Mediterranean Sea and coastal region during the summer. What surface wind direction is likely at an airport at the coast on a sunny afternoon?",
    "feedback": "Sea to land."
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass type advected from a direction indicated by arrow number 6 is designated",
    "feedback": "maritime polar"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft lands at an airport (airport elevation 600 ft, QNH 993 hPa) with the altimeter set to 1013 hPa. What will it indicate?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "1200 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In still air the temperature decreases at an average of 1.2°C per 100 m increase in altitude. This temperature change is called:",
    "feedback": "environmental lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate height of the tropopause between Munich and Helsinki?",
    "feedback": "FL 340"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight in summer was planned to take-off from Phuket, Thailand at 08:00 LT, but the departure was delayed to 11:00 LT.\nWhat could happen to the take-off performance? The climb performance during take-off (1)....... because the air density (2)............",
    "feedback": "(1) degrades, (2) decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "These four elements have been removed from the tropical cyclone advisory extract below: INTSF, JACQUES, 976HPA, NADI\nTC ADVISORYDTG: 20130712/1900ZTCAC: (1) ..................TC: (2) ..................TC Advisory NR: 2013/6OBS PSN: 12/1800Z N2706 W07306CB: W1 120NM OF TC CENTRE TOP FL450MOV: SE 35 KMHINTST CHANGE: (3) ....................C: (4) ........................MAX WIND: 30MPS\nThe correct sequence is:",
    "feedback": "(1) NADI, (2) JACQUES, (3) INTSF, (4) 976 HPA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following types of clouds are evidence of unstable air conditions?",
    "feedback": "CU, CB."
  },
  {
    "question": "An OAT of -55°C at the 200 hPa pressure level:",
    "feedback": "equals approximately (+/-5°C) ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "A moist, stable layer of air is forced to rise against a mountain range and the stability does not change. Which of the following phenomena may develop?",
    "feedback": "Stratified clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the deviation of the temperature at FL 140 above Copenhagen compared to ISA?",
    "feedback": "9°C colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "The presence of standing lenticular AC clouds is a good indication of:",
    "feedback": "Updrafts and downdrafts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the altitude of the condensation level, when an air pacel is lifted from MSL to 20000 ft. Static air temperature at MSL + 20°C, dew point at MSL -5°C. \nGiven:\nBrown dashed line: Constant saturation mixing ratioGreen line: Dry adiabaticMagenta line: Saturated adiabatic",
    "feedback": "10000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is true about the St. Elmo's fire weather phenomenon?",
    "feedback": "The St. Elmo's fire is a permanent electrical discharge in the air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Weather satellite images are classified by the wave range of their sensors.\n\nWhich channels are commonly used in aviation?",
    "feedback": "Infrared, visual"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most effective way to dissipate cloud is by",
    "feedback": "subsidence"
  },
  {
    "question": "During flight planning for a low level flight, clear air turbulence can be expected when the route crosses ....",
    "feedback": "a squall line near a cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "The QFF at an airfield in California located 69 metres below sea level is 1030 hPa. The air temperature is 10°C lower than a standard atmosphere. What is the QNH?",
    "feedback": "More than 1030 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the lower part of the stratosphere the temperature",
    "feedback": "is almost constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "By volume, what percentage of the air in the lower troposphere consists of water vapour?",
    "feedback": "0-5 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "When en-route and maintaining a constant flight level, how can you correctly describe the relationship between the true altitude and changes to the atmospheric pressure?",
    "feedback": "As pressure decreases the true altitude decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the following METAR for a Spanish aerodrome in September, an hour before sunset, at what distance might a pilot expect to see the theshold of runway 26 whilst on final approach?\nMETAR LEXX 211730Z 26008KT 220V320 3000 HZ SKC Q1010",
    "feedback": "More than 1500 metres but less than 3000 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "The synoptic chart depicts a region in the Southern Hemisphere. A warm front is to be found ....",
    "feedback": "between positions K and L"
  },
  {
    "question": "A mountain range spans from South to North and the wind is from the west. Where is the orographic low expected?",
    "feedback": "On the leeward side of the mountain"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Bergeron Theory:",
    "feedback": "presumes that at high levels in a cloud, some water droplets turn to ice and grow by sublimation."
  },
  {
    "question": "The duration of the cumulus stage (building stage) of a single-cell TS is:",
    "feedback": "15-20 min"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. What is the correct description of the pressure system shown by \"J\"?",
    "feedback": "Frontal depression"
  },
  {
    "question": "A wind sounding in the region of a polar front jet stream gives the following wind profile (Northern hemisphere): 900hPa 220/20kt  800hPa 220/25kt  700hPa 230/35kt  500hPa 260/60kt  400hPa 280/85kt 300hPa 300/100kt 250hPa 310/120kt  200hPa 310/80kt Which system is the jet stream associated with?",
    "feedback": "With a warm front."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line of the graph renders the unsaturated lapse rate?",
    "feedback": "The green lines"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characterizes a stationary front ?",
    "feedback": "The surface wind usually has its direction parallel to the front"
  },
  {
    "question": "A cold-air drop can be best identified by means of",
    "feedback": "the isohypses on an upper air chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following symbols represents a squall line?",
    "feedback": "Symbol a)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "The wind speed in the core of the jet stream west of Rome is about 80 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a characteristic weather pattern at F?",
    "feedback": "The double rains"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct or incorrect?\n1) During a blocking omega situation, the blocking omega high pressure area causes a very short duration of fine weather 2) The tropopause is generally colder overhead the equator, compared to the temperature of the tropopause overhead the north pole",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"Q\" is",
    "feedback": "showery with generally good visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "Relative humidity",
    "feedback": "increases if the air is cooled whilst maintaining the vapour pressure constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which temperature range does mixed ice most commonly occur in NS clouds?",
    "feedback": "-7°C to -13°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which FL corresponds with the 400 hPa pressure level?",
    "feedback": "FL 240"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the strongest headwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "You have been flying for some time in dense layered cloud. The outside air temperature is -25°C. Which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "Severe airframe icing is unlikely under these conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight crew is preparing for departure from Rabat-Sale airport (GMME), Morocco on 13th October and the following message is included in their briefing pack:\nGMME AD WRNG 2 VALID 131500/131700 SS FCST=\nWhat information does this provide about the weather at Rabat-Sale airport?",
    "feedback": "There is a forecast of a sandstorm that afternoon between 15:00 UTC and 17:00 UTC"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the SWC for ICAO area EURO, a jet stream is located around 50°N and its core is at FL320. The crew should avoid flying (1) ..... and just (2) ..... the jet core in order to avoid the area where turbulence is most likely to be expected.",
    "feedback": "(1) in the cold air, (2) below or near"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are planning a flight at FL 290, which of these upper wind and temperature charts would be nearest your flight level ?",
    "feedback": "300 hPa"
  }
]